<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
"docbook-5.0.dtd" [
<!ENTITY book.part1 SYSTEM "part1.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part2 SYSTEM "part2.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.introduction SYSTEM "part1-introduction.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.getting-started SYSTEM "part1-getting-started.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.architecture SYSTEM "part1-architecture.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.application SYSTEM "part1-application.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.eclipse SYSTEM "part1-eclipse.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.components SYSTEM "part1-components.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.layout SYSTEM "part1-layout.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.themes SYSTEM "part1-themes.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.datamodel SYSTEM "part1-datamodel.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.gwt SYSTEM "part1-gwt.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.advanced SYSTEM "part1-advanced.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.uidl SYSTEM "part1-uidl.xml">
<!ENTITY book.part1.vaadin SYSTEM "part1-vaadin.xml">
<!ENTITY ouml "รถ">
]>
<book>
	<info>	
		<title>Book of Vaadin</title>
		
        <!-- This is a custom element so that we can have a graphical title. -->
		<titleimage>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata scale="30" fileref="img/vaadin-logo-hi.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</titleimage>
		
		<subtitle>Vaadin 6.2</subtitle>

		<author>
			<firstname>Marko</firstname>
			<surname>Gr&ouml;nroos</surname>
		</author>

		<websitenotice>
			<title>The latest version of this book can be viewed at</title>
			<uri>http://vaadin.com/book</uri>
		</websitenotice>

		<corpauthor>
			<orgname class="corporation">Oy IT Mill Ltd</orgname>
		</corpauthor>

		<publisher>		
			<publishername class="corporation">Oy IT Mill Ltd</publishername>
			<address>
				<street>Ruukinkatu 2-4</street>
				<postcode>20540</postcode>
				<city>Turku</city>
				<country>Finland</country>
			</address>
		</publisher>

        <!-- This value is now unused for PDF as it is set from the command-line. -->
        <!-- (It is still used for HTML until the automation is done for HTML too.)-->
		<pubdate>2009-01-06</pubdate>

		<productname>Vaadin</productname>
		
        <releaseinfo>
			<!-- This will be automatically replaced from 'manual.version'
		         command-line parameter. -->
			<productname>Vaadin</productname>
			<releasenumber>5.4.0</releasenumber>
		</releaseinfo>

		<edition>First</edition>

		<!-- The printer and print location (custom element). -->
		<printer>
			<orgname>Uniprint</orgname>
			<address>
				<city>Turku</city>
				<country>Finland</country>
			</address>
		</printer>

		<biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 978-952-92-6753-8 (print edition)</biblioid>
		<biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 978-952-92-6754-5 (PDF edition)</biblioid>

		<copyright>
			<year>2000-2009</year>
			<holder>Oy IT Mill Ltd.</holder>
		</copyright>

		<legalnotice>All rights reserved.</legalnotice>

		<abstract>
			<para>
                Vaadin is a server-side AJAX web application development framework that
                enables developers to build high-quality user interfaces with Java. It
                provides a library of ready-to-use user interface components and a clean
                framework for creating your own components. The focus is on ease-of-use,
                re-usability, extensibility, and meeting the requirements of large
                enterprise applications. Vaadin has been used in production since 2001 and
                it has proven to be suitable for building demanding business applications.
			</para>
		</abstract>

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata scale="50" fileref="img/vaadin-logo-hi.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>

        <!-- The headerdata and headerlogo are custom elements. -->
        <headerdata>
            <headerlogo>
                <imagedata depth="0.80cm" fileref="img/vaadin-logo-lo.png"/>
            </headerlogo>
        </headerdata>
	</info>

	<preface xml:id="preface">
		<title>Preface</title>

        <para>
            This book provides an overview of Vaadin and covers the most important topics
            which you might encounter when developing applications with it. A more
            detailed documentation of individual classes, interfaces, and methods is given
            in the Java API Reference.
        </para>

        <para>
            You can browse an online version of this book at the Vaadin website
            <uri>http://vaadin.com/</uri>. A PDF version is also included in the Vaadin
            installation package and if you install the Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse, you can
            browse it in the Eclipse Help. You may find the HTML or the Eclipse Help
            plugin version more easily searchable than this printed book or the PDF
            version, but the content is the same. Just like the rest of Vaadin, this book
            is open source.
        </para>

        <para>
            Writing this manual is ongoing work and this edition represents a snapshot
            around the release of Vaadin 6.2, containing a number of additions and
            corrections since the first edition, which was for Vaadin 6.1. Especially, the
            <xref linkend="gwt"/>, has been revised to comply with the new way of defining
            widget sets and the mapping from server-side components to their corresponding
            client-side widgets. Many sections are under work and will be expanded in
            future.
        </para>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Who is This Book For?</title>

            <para>
                This book is intended for software developers who use, or are considering
                to use, Vaadin to develop web applications.
            </para>

            <para>
                The book assumes that you have some experience with programming in Java,
                but if not, it is as easy to begin learning Java with Vaadin as with any
                other UI framework if not easier. No knowledge of AJAX is needed as it is
                well hidden from the developer.
            </para>

            <para>
                You may have used some desktop-oriented user interface frameworks for
                Java, such as AWT, Swing, or SWT. Or a library such as Qt for C++. Such
                knowledge is useful for understanding the scope of Vaadin, the
                event-driven programming model, and other common concepts of UI
                frameworks, but not necessary.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you don't have a web graphics designer at hand, knowing the basics of
                HTML and CSS can help, so that you can develop presentation themes for
                your application. A brief introduction to CSS is provided. Knowledge of
                Google Web Toolkit (GWT) may be useful if you develop or integrate new
                client-side components.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
		
		<simplesect>
            <title>Organization of This Book</title>
				
            <para>
                The Book of Vaadin gives an introduction to what
                <productname>Vaadin</productname> is and how you use it to develop web
                applications.
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="intro"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The chapter gives introduction to the application architecture
                            supported by Vaadin, the core design ideas behind the
                            framework, and some historical background.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="getting-started"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives practical instructions for installing
                            Vaadin and the reference toolchain, including the Vaadin
                            Plugin for Eclipse, how to run and debug the demos, and how to
                            create your own application project in the Eclipse IDE.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="architecture"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an introduction to the architecture of
                            Vaadin and its major technologies, including AJAX, Google Web
                            Toolkit, JSON, and event-driven programming.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="application"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives all the practical knowledge required for
                            creating applications with Vaadin, such as window management,
                            application lifecycle, deployment in a servlet container, and
                            handling events, errors, and resources.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="components"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter essentially gives the reference documentation for
                            all the core user interface components in Vaadin and their
                            most significant features. The text gives examples for using
                            each of the components.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="layout"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes the layout components, which are used
                            for managing the layout of the user interface, just like in
                            any desktop application frameworks.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="eclipse"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives instructions for using the visual editor
                            for Eclipse, which is included in the Vaadin Plugin for the
                            Eclipse IDE.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="themes"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an introduction to Cascading Style Sheets
                            (CSS) and explains how you can use them to build custom visual
                            themes for your application.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="datamodel"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an overview of the built-in data model of
                            Vaadin, consisting of properties, items, and containers.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="gwt"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes the process of creating new client-side
                            widgets with Google Web Toolkit (GWT) and integrating them
                            with server-side counterparts. The chapter also gives
                            practical instructions for creating widget projects in
                            Eclipse, and using the GWT Development Mode to debug widgets.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="advanced"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter provides many special topics that are commonly
                            needed in applications, such as opening new browser windows,
                            embedding applications in regular web pages, low-level
                            management of resources, shortcut keys, debugging, etc.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="uidl"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an outline of the low-level UIDL messaging
                            language, normally hidden from the developer. The chapter
                            includes the description of the serialization API needed for
                            synchronizing the component state between the client-side and
                            server-side components.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="vaadin"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Mythological background of the name Vaadin.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
                        
                       
        </simplesect>
			
        <simplesect>
            <title>Supplementary Material</title>

            <para>
                The Vaadin installation package and websites offer plenty of material that
                can help you understand what Vaadin is, what you can do with it, and how
                you can do it.
            </para>
				
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Demo Applications</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The installation package of Vaadin includes a number of demo
                            applications that you can run and use with your web
                            browser. The content browser allows you to view the source
                            code of the individual demo applications. You should find
                            especially the Sampler demo a good friend of yours.
                        </para>
					
                        <para>
                            You can find the demo applications online at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/">http://vaadin.com/</link>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Address Book Tutorial</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The Address Book is a sample application accompanied with a
                            tutorial that gives detailed step-by-step instructions for
                            creating a real-life web application with Vaadin. You can find
                            the tutorial from the product website.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Developer's Website</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Vaadin Developer's Site at <link
                            xlink:href="http://dev.vaadin.com/">http://dev.vaadin.com/</link>
                            provides various online resources, such as the ticket system,
                            a development wiki, source repositories, activity timeline,
                            development milestones, and so on.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            The wiki provides instructions for developers, especially for
                            those who wish to check-out and compile Vaadin itself from the
                            source repository. The technical articles deal with
                            integration of Vaadin applications with various systems, such
                            as JSP, Maven, Spring, Hibernate, and portals. The wiki also
                            provides answers to Frequently Asked Questions.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Online Documentation</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            You can read this book online at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/book">http://vaadin.com/book</link>. Lots of 
                            additional material, including technical HOWTOs, answers to Frequently Asked
                            Questions and other documentation is also available on
                            <link xlink:href="http://dev.vaadin.com/">Vaadin web-site</link>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Support</title>

            <para>
                Stuck with a problem? No need to lose your hair over it, the Vaadin
                developer community and the IT Mill company offer support for all of your
                needs.
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Community Support Forum</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            You can find the user and developer community forum for Vaadin
                            at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/forum">http://vaadin.com/forum</link>. Please
                            use the forum to discuss any problems you might encounter,
                            wishes for features, and so on. The answer for your problems
                            may already lie in the forum archives, so searching the
                            discussions is always the best way to begin.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Report Bugs</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            If you have found a possible bug in Vaadin, the demo
                            applications, or the documentation, please report it by filing
                            a ticket at the Vaadin developer's site at <link
                            xlink:href="http://dev.vaadin.com/">http://dev.vaadin.com/</link>. You
                            may want to check the existing tickets before filing a new
                            one. You can make a ticket to make a request for a new
                            feature as well, or to suggest modifications to an existing
                            feature.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Commercial Support</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            IT Mill offers full commercial support and training services
                            for the Vaadin products. Read more about the commercial products
                            at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/pro">http://vaadin.com/pro</link>
                            for details.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </simplesect>
		
        <!-- Author information only for the printed edition. -->
		<simplesect>
			<title>About the Author</title>

			<para>
                Marko Gr&ouml;nroos is a professional writer and software developer working at
                IT Mill Ltd in Turku, Finland. He has been involved in web application
                development since 1994 and has worked on several application development
                frameworks in C, C++, and Java. He has been active in many open source
                software projects and holds an M.Sc. degree in Computer Science from the
                University of Turku.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
            
        <?dbfo-need height="8cm" ?>
		<simplesect>
			<title>Acknowledgements</title>

			<para>
                Much of the book is the result of close work within the development team
                at IT Mill. Joonas Lehtinen, CEO of IT Mill Ltd, wrote the first outline
                of the book, which became the basis for the first two chapters. Since
                then, Marko Gr&ouml;nroos has become the primary author. The development team has
                contributed several passages, answered numerous technical questions,
                reviewed the manual, and made many corrections.
            </para>

			<para>
                The contributors are (in chronological order):
			</para>

            <itemizedlist mark="none" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>Joonas Lehtinen</listitem>
                <listitem>Jani Laakso</listitem>
                <listitem>Marko Gr&ouml;nroos</listitem>
                <listitem>Jouni Koivuviita</listitem>
                <listitem>Matti Tahvonen</listitem>
                <listitem>Artur Signell</listitem>
                <listitem>Marc Englund</listitem>
                <listitem>Henri Sara</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
            
		<simplesect>
			<title>About Oy IT Mill Ltd</title>

			<para>
                Oy IT Mill Ltd is a Finnish software company specializing in the design
                and development of Rich Internet Applications. The company offers
                planning, implementation, and support services for the software projects
                of its customers, as well as sub-contract software development. Vaadin,
                previously known as IT Mill Toolkit, is the flagship open source product
                of the company, for which it provides commercial development and support
                services.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
            
	</preface>
	
    <!-- No reason to enclose in a Part as the API doc is separate. -->
	<!-- part xml:id="part1" label="I">
		<title>Developer's Guide</title> -->
		&book.part1.introduction;
		&book.part1.getting-started;
		&book.part1.architecture;
		&book.part1.application;
		&book.part1.components;
		&book.part1.layout;
		&book.part1.eclipse;
		&book.part1.themes;
		&book.part1.datamodel;
		&book.part1.gwt;
		&book.part1.advanced;
		&book.part1.uidl;
		&book.part1.vaadin;
		&book.part1;
	<!-- /part -->

    <index/>

	<!-- Book part 2 describes API. It is probably not needed for 4.0.0 release. --> 
	<!-- &book.part2; -->

</book>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->

