<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<preface xml:id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>
        This book provides an overview of the Vaadin Framework and covers the most
        important topics that you might encounter while developing applications with it. A
        more detailed documentation of the individual classes, interfaces, and methods is
        given in the Vaadin API Reference.
    </para>

    <para>
        This edition mostly covers Vaadin 7.1 released in summer 2013. The release
        included support for server push, an updated debug window. WAI-ARIA support, and
        various other features.
    </para>

    <para>
        Writing this manual is an ongoing work and it is rarely completely up-to-date with
        the quick-evolving product. Some features may not be included in this book yet.
        For the most current version, please see the on-line edition available at
        <uri>http://vaadin.com/book</uri>. You can also find PDF and EPUB versions of the
        book there. You may find the other versions more easily searchable than the
        printed book. The index in the book is incomplete and will be expanded later. The
        web edition also has some additional technical content, such as some example code
        and other reference details that you may need when actually doing development. The
        purpose of the slightly abridged print edition is more to be an introductionary
        textbook to Vaadin, and still fit in your pocket.
    </para>

    <para>
        Also, many Vaadin 7 features are showcased as mini-tutorials, which are
        available in the Vaadin Wiki at <link
            xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Vaadin+7">https://vaadin.com/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Vaadin+7</link>.
    </para>


        <simplesect>
            <title>Who is This Book For?</title>

            <para>
                This book is intended for software developers who use, or are considering
                to use, Vaadin to develop web applications.
            </para>

            <para>
                The book assumes that you have some experience with programming in Java,
                but if not, it is at least as easy to begin learning Java with Vaadin as
                with any other UI framework. No knowledge of AJAX is needed as it is well
                hidden from the developer.
            </para>

            <para>
                You may have used some desktop-oriented user interface frameworks for
                Java, such as AWT, Swing, or SWT, or a library such as Qt for C++. Such
                knowledge is useful for understanding the scope of Vaadin, the
                event-driven programming model, and other common concepts of UI
                frameworks, but not necessary.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you do not have a web graphics designer at hand, knowing the basics of
                HTML and CSS can help so that you can develop presentation themes for
                your application. A brief introduction to CSS is provided. Knowledge of
                Google Web Toolkit (GWT) may be useful if you develop or integrate new
                client-side components.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
		
		<simplesect>
            <title>Organization of This Book</title>
				
            <para>
                The Book of Vaadin gives an introduction to what
                <productname>Vaadin</productname> is and how you use it to develop web
                applications.
            </para>

            <para>
                Part I: Introduction
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="intro"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The chapter gives an introduction to the application architecture
                            supported by Vaadin, the core design ideas behind the
                            framework, and some historical background.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="getting-started"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives practical instructions for installing
                            Vaadin and the reference toolchain, including the Vaadin
                            Plugin for Eclipse, how to run and debug the demos, and how to
                            create your own application project in the Eclipse IDE.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="architecture"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an introduction to the architecture of
                            Vaadin and its major technologies, including AJAX, Google Web
                            Toolkit, and event-driven programming.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

            <para>
                Part II: Server-Side Framework
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="application"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives all the practical knowledge required for
                            creating applications with Vaadin, such as window management,
                            application lifecycle, deployment in a servlet container, and
                            handling events, errors, and resources.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="components"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter essentially gives the reference documentation for
                            all the core user interface components in Vaadin and their
                            most significant features. The text gives examples for using
                            each of the components.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="layout"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes the layout components, which are used
                            for managing the layout of the user interface, just like in
                            any desktop application frameworks.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="eclipse"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives instructions for using the visual editor
                            for Eclipse, which is included in the Vaadin Plugin for the
                            Eclipse IDE.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="themes"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an introduction to Cascading Style Sheets
                            (CSS) and explains how you can use them to build custom visual
                            themes for your application.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="datamodel"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an overview of the built-in data model of
                            Vaadin, consisting of properties, items, and containers.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="sqlcontainer"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives documentation for the SQLContainer, which
                            allows binding Vaadin components to SQL queries.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="advanced"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter provides many special topics that are commonly
                            needed in applications, such as opening new browser windows,
                            embedding applications in regular web pages, low-level
                            management of resources, shortcut keys, debugging, etc.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="portal"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes the development of Vaadin
                            applications as portlets which you can deploy to any portal
                            supporting Java Portlet API 2.0 (JSR-286). The chapter also
                            describes the special support for Liferay and the Control
                            Panel, IPC, and WSRP add-ons.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            
            <para>
                Part III: Client-Side Framework
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="clientside"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives an introduction to creating and developing
                            client-side applications and widgets, including installation,
                            compilation, and debugging.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="clientsideapp"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes how to develop client-side applications
                            and how to integrate them with a back-end service.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="widgets"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes the built-in widgets (client-side
                            components) available for client-side development. The
                            built-in widgets include Google Web Toolkit widgets as well as
                            Vaadin widgets.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="gwt"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter describes how to integrate client-side widgets
                            with their server-side counterparts for the purpose of
                            creating new server-side components. The chapter also covers
                            integrating JavaScript components.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

            <para>
                Part IV: Vaadin Add-ons
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="addons"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives instructions for downloading and
                            installing add-on components from the Vaadin Directory.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="charts"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter documents the use of the Vaadin Charts add-on
                            component for interactive charting with many diagram
                            types. The add-on includes the Chart and Timeline components.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="jpacontainer"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives documentation of the JPAContainer add-on,
                            which allows binding Vaadin components directly to relational
                            and other databases using Java Persistence API (JPA).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="mobile"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives examples and reference documentation for
                            using the Vaadin TouchKit add-on for developing mobile
                            applications.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="testbench"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This chapter gives the complete documentation of using the
                            Vaadin TestBench tool for recording and executing user
                            interface regression tests of Vaadin applications.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <!-- Not enough content
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><xref linkend="vaadin6-migration"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This appendix covers migration from Vaadin 6 to Vaadin 7.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                -->
                <varlistentry condition="web">
                    <term><xref linkend="vaadin"/></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Mythological background of the name Vaadin.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
                        
                       
        </simplesect>
			
        <simplesect>
            <title>Supplementary Material</title>

            <para>
                The Vaadin websites offer plenty of material that can help you understand
                what Vaadin is, what you can do with it, and how you can do it.
            </para>
				
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Demo Applications</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The most important demo application for Vaadin is the Sampler,
                            which demonstrates the use of all basic components and
                            features. You can run it on-line at <link
                            xlink:href="http://demo.vaadin.com/">http://demo.vaadin.com/</link>
                            or download it as a WAR from the <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/download/">Vaadin download
                            page</link>.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Most of the code examples in this book and many others can be
                            found online at <link
                            xlink:href="http://demo.vaadin.com/book-examples-vaadin7/book/">http://demo.vaadin.com/book-examples-vaadin7/book/</link>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Cheat Sheet</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The two-page cheat sheet illustrates the basic relationship
                            hierarchy of the user interface and data binding classes and
                            interfaces. You can download it at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/book">http://vaadin.com/book</link>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Refcard</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The six-page DZone Refcard gives an overview to application
                            development with Vaadin. It includes a diagram of the user
                            interface and data binding classes and interfaces. You can
                            find more information about it at <link
                            xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/refcard">https://vaadin.com/refcard</link>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Address Book Tutorial</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The Address Book is a sample application accompanied with a
                            tutorial that gives detailed step-by-step instructions for
                            creating a real-life web application with Vaadin. You can find
                            the tutorial from the product website.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Developer's Website</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Vaadin Developer's Site at <link
                            xlink:href="http://dev.vaadin.com/">http://dev.vaadin.com/</link>
                            provides various online resources, such as the ticket system,
                            a development wiki, source repositories, activity timeline,
                            development milestones, and so on.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            The wiki provides instructions for developers, especially for
                            those who wish to check-out and compile Vaadin itself from the
                            source repository. The technical articles deal with
                            integration of Vaadin applications with various systems, such
                            as JSP, Maven, Spring, Hibernate, and portals. The wiki also
                            provides answers to Frequently Asked Questions.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Online Documentation</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            You can read this book online at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/book">http://vaadin.com/book</link>. Lots of 
                            additional material, including technical HOWTOs, answers to Frequently Asked
                            Questions and other documentation is also available on
                            <link xlink:href="http://dev.vaadin.com/">Vaadin web-site</link>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Support</title>

            <para>
                Stuck with a problem? No need to lose your hair over it, the Vaadin
                Framework developer community and the Vaadin company offer support to all
                of your needs.
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Community Support Forum</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            You can find the user and developer community forum at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/forum">http://vaadin.com/forum</link>. Please
                            use the forum to discuss any problems you might encounter,
                            wishes for features, and so on. The answer to your problems
                            may already lie in the forum archives, so searching the
                            discussions is always the best way to begin.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Report Bugs</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            If you have found a possible bug in Vaadin, the demo
                            applications, or the documentation, please report it by filing
                            a ticket at the Vaadin developer's site at <link
                            xlink:href="http://dev.vaadin.com/">http://dev.vaadin.com/</link>. You
                            may want to check the existing tickets before filing a new
                            one. You can make a ticket to make a request for a new
                            feature as well, or to suggest modifications to an existing
                            feature.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Commercial Support</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Vaadin offers full commercial support and training services
                            for the Vaadin Framework and related products. Read more about
                            the commercial products at <link
                            xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/pro">http://vaadin.com/pro</link>
                            for details.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </simplesect>
		
        <!-- Author information only for the printed edition. -->
		<simplesect>
			<title>About the Author</title>

			<para>
                Marko Gr&ouml;nroos is a professional writer and software developer working at
                Vaadin Ltd in Turku, Finland. He has been involved in web application
                development since 1994 and has worked on several application development
                frameworks in C, C++, and Java. He has been active in many open source
                software projects and holds an M.Sc. degree in Computer Science from the
                University of Turku.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
            
        <?dbfo-need height="8cm" ?>
		<simplesect>
			<title>Acknowledgements</title>

			<para>
                Much of the book is the result of close work within the development team
                at Vaadin Ltd. Joonas Lehtinen, CEO of Vaadin Ltd, wrote the first outline
                of the book, which became the basis for the first two chapters. Since
                then, Marko Gr&ouml;nroos has become the primary author and editor. The
                development team has contributed several passages, answered numerous
                technical questions, reviewed the manual, and made many corrections.
            </para>

			<para>
                The contributors are (in rough chronological order):
			</para>

            <itemizedlist mark="none" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>Joonas Lehtinen</listitem>
                <listitem>Jani Laakso</listitem>
                <listitem>Marko Gr&ouml;nroos</listitem>
                <listitem>Jouni Koivuviita</listitem>
                <listitem>Matti Tahvonen</listitem>
                <listitem>Artur Signell</listitem>
                <listitem>Marc Englund</listitem>
                <listitem>Henri Sara</listitem>
                <listitem>Jonatan Kronqvist</listitem>
                <listitem>Mikael Grankvist (TestBench)</listitem>
                <listitem>Teppo Kurki (SQLContainer)</listitem>
                <listitem>Tomi Virtanen (Calendar)</listitem>
                <listitem>Risto Yrj&auml;n&auml; (Calendar)</listitem>
                <listitem>John Ahlroos (Timeline)</listitem>
                <listitem>Petter Holmstr&ouml;m (JPAContainer)</listitem>
                <listitem>Leif &#xC5;strand</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
            
		<simplesect>
			<title>About Vaadin Ltd</title>

			<para>
                Vaadin Ltd is a Finnish software company specializing in the design and
                development of Rich Internet Applications. The company offers planning,
                implementation, and support services for the software projects of its
                customers, as well as sub-contract software development. Vaadin Framework,
                previously known as IT Mill Toolkit, is the flagship open source product
                of the company, for which it provides commercial development and support
                services.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
            
	</preface>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
