<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="datamodel">
	<title>Binding Components to Data</title>

    <indexterm xml:id="term.datamodel" class="startofrange">
        <primary>Vaadin Data Model</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
        This chapter describes the Vaadin Data Model and shows how you can use it to bind
        components directly to data sources, such as database queries.
    </para>

	<section xml:id="datamodel.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>

		<para>
            The Vaadin Data Model is one of the core concepts of the library. To allow the
            view (user interface components) to access the data model of an application
            directly, we have introduced a standard data interface.
		</para>

		<para>
			The model allows binding user interface components directly to the data that
			they display and possibly allow to edit. There are three nested levels of
			hierarchy in the data model: <emphasis>property</emphasis>,
			<emphasis>item</emphasis>, and <emphasis>container</emphasis>. Using a
			spreadsheet application as an analogy, these would correspond to a cell, a
			row, and a table, respectively.
		</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Vaadin Data Model</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/arch/datamodel-sml.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="20" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/arch/datamodel-whitebg.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		
		<para>
			The Data Model is realized as a set of interfaces in the
			<classname>com.vaadin.data</classname> package. The package contains the
			<classname>Property</classname>, <classname>Item</classname>, and
			<classname>Container</classname> interfaces, along with a number of more
			specialized interfaces and classes.
		</para>

		<para>
			Notice that the Data Model does not define data representation, but only
			interfaces. This leaves the representation fully to the implementation of the
			containers. The representation can be almost anything, such as a plain old Java
			object (POJO) structure, a filesystem, or a database query.
		</para>

		<para>
			The Data Model is used heavily in the core user interface components of
			Vaadin, especially the field components, that is, components that implement
			the <classname>Field</classname> interface or more typically extend
			<classname>AbstractField</classname>, which defines many common features. A
			key feature of all the built-in field components is that they can either
			maintain their data by themselves or be bound to an external data source. The
			value of a field is always available through the
			<classname>Property</classname> interface. As more than one component can be
			bound to the same data source, it is easy to implement various viewer-editor
			patterns.
		</para>

        <para>
            The relationships of the various interfaces are shown in <xref
            linkend="figure.datamodel.overview.relationships"/>; the value change event
            and listener interfaces are shown only for the <classname>Property</classname>
            interface, while the notifier interfaces are omitted altogether.
        </para>
		
		<figure xml:id="figure.datamodel.overview.relationships">
			<title>Interface Relationships in Vaadin Data Model</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/datamodel/datamodel-interfaces-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/datamodel/datamodel-interfaces-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		
		<para>
			The Data Model has many important and useful features, such as support for
			change notification. Especially containers have many helper interfaces,
			including ones that allow indexing, ordering, sorting, and filtering the
			data. Also <classname>Field</classname> components provide a number of
			features involving the data model, such as buffering, validation, and lazy
			loading.
		</para>

		<para>
            Vaadin provides a number of built-in implementations of the data model
            interfaces. The built-in implementations are used as the default data models
            in many field components.
        </para>

		<para>
            In addition to the built-in implementations, many data model implementations,
            such as containers, are available as add-ons, either from the Vaadin Directory
            or from independent sources. Both commercial and free implementations
            exist. The JPAContainer, described in <xref linkend="jpacontainer"/>, is the
            most often used conmmercial container add-on. The installation of add-ons is
            described in <xref linkend="addons"/>. Notice that unlike with most regular
            add-on components, you do not need to compile a widget set for add-ons that
            include just data model implementations.
        </para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="datamodel.properties">
		<title>Properties</title>

		<para>
			The <interfacename>Property</interfacename> interface is the base of the
			Vaadin Data Model. It provides a standardized API for a single data value
			object that can be read (get) and written (set). A property is always typed,
			but can optionally support data type conversions. The type of a property can
			be any Java class. Optionally, properties can provide value change events for
			following their changes.
		</para>

        <para>
            You can set the value of a property with <methodname>setValue()</methodname>
            and read with <methodname>getValue()</methodname>.
        </para>

        <para>
            In the following, we set and read the property value from a
            <classname>TextField</classname> component, which implements the
            <interfacename>Property</interfacename> interface to allow accessing the field
            value.
        </para>

        <book-example id="datamodel.properties.basic"></book-example>
        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[final TextField tf = new TextField("Name");
        
// Set the value
tf.setValue("The text field value");
        
// When the field value is edited by the user
tf.addValueChangeListener(
    new Property.ValueChangeListener() {
    public void valueChange(ValueChangeEvent event) {
        // Do something with the new value
        layout.addComponent(new Label(tf.getValue()));
    }
});]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Changes in the property value usually fire a
            <classname>ValueChangeEvent</classname>, which can be handled with a
            <classname>ValueChangeListener</classname>. The event object provides
            reference to the property with <methodname>getProperty()</methodname>. Note
            that its <methodname>getValue()</methodname> method returns the value with
            <classname>Object</classname> type, so you need to cast it to the proper type.
        </para>

		<!-- TODO this might not be the best place to explain this - maybe split the paragraph? -->
		<para>
			Properties are in themselves unnamed. They are collected in
			<emphasis>items</emphasis>, which associate the properties with names: the
			<emphasis>Property Identifiers</emphasis> or <emphasis>PID</emphasis>s.  Items
			can be further contained in containers and are identified with <emphasis>Item
			Identifiers</emphasis> or <emphasis>IID</emphasis>s. In the spreadsheet
			analogy, <emphasis>Property Identifiers</emphasis> would correspond to column
			names and <emphasis>Item Identifiers</emphasis> to row names. The identifiers
			can be arbitrary objects, but must implement the
			<methodname>equals(Object)</methodname> and
			<methodname>hashCode()</methodname> methods so that they can be used in any
			standard Java <classname>Collection</classname>.
		</para>

		<para>
			The <classname>Property</classname> interface can be utilized either by
			implementing the interface or by using some of the built-in property
			implementations. Vaadin includes a <classname>Property</classname> interface
			implementation for arbitrary function pairs and bean properties, with the
			<classname>MethodProperty</classname> class, and for simple object properties,
			with the <classname>ObjectProperty</classname> class, as described later.
		</para>

		<para>
			In addition to the simple components, selection components provide their
			current selection as the property value. In single selection mode, the
			property is a single item identifier, while in multiple selection mode it is a
			set of item identifiers. See the documentation of the selection components for
			further details.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Components that can be bound to a property have an internal default data
			source object, typically a <classname>ObjectProperty</classname>, which is
			described later. As all such components are viewers or editors, also described
			later, so you can rebind a component to any data source with
			<methodname>setPropertyDataSource()</methodname>.
		</para>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.viewers">
            <title>Property Viewers and Editors</title>

            <para>
                The most important function of the <classname>Property</classname> as well
                as of the other data model interfaces is to connect classes implementing
                the interface directly to editor and viewer classes. This means connecting
                a data source (model) to a user interface component (views) to allow
                editing or viewing the data model.
            </para>

            <para>
                A property can be bound to a component implementing the
                <classname>Viewer</classname> interface with
                <methodname>setPropertyDataSource()</methodname>.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have a data model
ObjectProperty property =
    new ObjectProperty("Hello", String.class);
        
// Have a component that implements Viewer
Label viewer = new Label();
        
// Bind it to the data
viewer.setPropertyDataSource(property);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                You can use the same method in the <classname>Editor</classname> interface
                to bind a component that allows editing a particular property type to a
                property.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have a data model
ObjectProperty property =
    new ObjectProperty("Hello", String.class);
        
// Have a component that implements Viewer
TextField editor = new TextField("Edit Greeting");
        
// Bind it to the data
editor.setPropertyDataSource(property);
]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                As all field components implement the <classname>Property</classname>
                interface, you can bind any component implementing the
                <classname>Viewer</classname> interface to any field, assuming that the
                viewer is able the view the object type of the field. Continuing from the
                above example, we can bind a <classname>Label</classname> to the
                <classname>TextField</classname> value:
            </para>
        
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[Label viewer = new Label();
viewer.setPropertyDataSource(editor);

// The value shown in the viewer is updated immediately
// after editing the value in the editor (once it
// loses the focus)
editor.setImmediate(true);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                If a field has validators, as described in <xref
                linkend="components.fields.validation"/>, the validators are executed
                before writing the value to the property data source, or by calling the
                <methodname>validate()</methodname> or <methodname>commit()</methodname>
                for the field.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.objectproperty">
            <title><classname>ObjectProperty</classname> Implementation</title>

            <para>
                The <classname>ObjectProperty</classname> class is a simple implementation
                of the <classname>Property</classname> interface that allows storing an
                arbitrary Java object.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have a component that implements Viewer interface
final TextField tf = new TextField("Name");
        
// Have a data model with some data
String myObject = "Hello";
        
// Wrap it in an ObjectProperty
ObjectProperty property =
    new ObjectProperty(myObject, String.class);
        
// Bind the property to the component
tf.setPropertyDataSource(property);]]></programlisting>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.converter">
            <title>Converting Between Property Type and Representation</title>

            <para>
                Fields allow editing a certain type, such as a
                <classname>String</classname> or <classname>Date</classname>. The bound
                property, on the other hand, could have some entirely different
                type. Conversion between a representation edited by the field and the
                model defined in the property is handler with a converter that implements
                the <interfacename>Converter</interfacename> interface.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most common type conversions, such as between string and integer, are
                handled by the default converters. They are created in a converter factory
                global in the application.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.converter.basic">
                <title>Basic Use of Converters</title>

                <para>
                    The
                    <methodname>setConverter(<interfacename>Converter</interfacename>)</methodname>
                    method sets the converter for a field. The method is defined in
                    <classname>AbstractField</classname>.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[// Have an integer property
final ObjectProperty<Integer> property =
        new ObjectProperty<Integer>(42); 
        
// Create a TextField, which edits Strings
final TextField tf = new TextField("Name");

// Use a converter between String and Integer
tf.setConverter(new StringToIntegerConverter());

// And bind the field
tf.setPropertyDataSource(property);]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The built-in converters are the following:
                </para>

                <table xml:id="datamodel.properties.converter.basic.built-in">
                    <title>Built-in Converters</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="11*"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="7*"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry>Converter</entry>
                                <entry>Representation</entry>
                                <entry>Model</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry><classname>StringToIntegerConverter</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>String</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Integer</classname></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry><classname>StringToDoubleConverter</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>String</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Double</classname></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry><classname>StringToNumberConverter</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>String</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Number</classname></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry><classname>StringToBooleanConverter</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>String</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Boolean</classname></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry><classname>StringToDateConverter</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>String</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Date</classname></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row valign="top">
                                <entry><classname>DateToLongConverter</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Date</classname></entry>
                                <entry><classname>Long</classname></entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>

                <para>
                    In addition, there is a <classname>ReverseConverter</classname> that
                    takes a converter as a parameter and reverses the conversion
                    direction.
                </para>

                <para>
                    If a converter already exists for a type, the
                    <methodname>setConverter(<interfacename>Class</interfacename>)</methodname>
                    retrieves the converter for the given type from the converter factory,
                    and then sets it for the field. This method is used implicitly when
                    binding field to a property data source.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.converter.custom">
                <title>Implementing a Converter</title>

                <para>
                    A conversion always occurs between a <emphasis>representation
                    type</emphasis>, edited by the field component, and a <emphasis>model
                    type</emphasis>, that is, the type of the property data
                    source. Converters implement the
                    <interfacename>Converter</interfacename> interface defined in the
                    <package>com.vaadin.data.util.converter</package> package.
                </para>

                <para>
                    For example, let us assume that we have a simple
                    <classname>Complex</classname> type for storing complex values.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class ComplexConverter
       implements Converter<String, Complex> {
    @Override
    public Complex convertToModel(String value, Locale locale)
            throws ConversionException {
        String parts[] =
            value.replaceAll("[\\(\\)]", "").split(",");
        if (parts.length != 2)
            throw new ConversionException(
                    "Unable to parse String to Complex");
        return new Complex(Double.parseDouble(parts[0]),
                           Double.parseDouble(parts[1]));
    }

    @Override
    public String convertToPresentation(Complex value,
                                        Locale locale)
            throws ConversionException {
        return "("+value.getReal()+","+value.getImag()+")";
    }

    @Override
    public Class<Complex> getModelType() {
        return Complex.class;
    }

    @Override
    public Class<String> getPresentationType() {
        return String.class;
    }
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The conversion methods get the locale for the conversion as a
                    parameter.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.converter.converterfactory">
                <title>Converter Factory</title>

                <para>
                    If a field does not directly allow editing a property type, a default
                    converter is attempted to create using an application-global converter
                    factory. If you define your own converters that you wish to include in
                    the converter factory, you need to implement one yourself. While you
                    could implement the <interfacename>ConverterFactory</interfacename>
                    interface, it is usually easier to just extend
                    <classname>DefaultConverterFactory</classname>.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[class MyConverterFactory extends DefaultConverterFactory {
    @Override
    public <PRESENTATION, MODEL> Converter<PRESENTATION, MODEL>
            createConverter(Class<PRESENTATION> presentationType,
                            Class<MODEL> modelType) {
        // Handle one particular type conversion
        if (String.class == presentationType &&
            Complex.class == modelType)
            return (Converter<PRESENTATION, MODEL>)
                   new ComplexConverter();

        // Default to the supertype
        return super.createConverter(presentationType,
                                     modelType);
    }
}

// Use the factory globally in the application
Application.getCurrentApplication().setConverterFactory(
        new MyConverterFactory());]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.properties.implementing">
            <title>Implementing the <classname>Property</classname> Interface</title>

            <para>
                Implementation of the <classname>Property</classname> interface requires
                defining setters and getters for the value and the
                <emphasis>read-only</emphasis> mode. Only a getter is needed for the
                property type, as the type is often fixed in property implementations.
            </para>

            <para>
                The following example shows a simple implementation of the
                <classname>Property</classname> interface:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[class MyProperty implements Property {
    Integer data     = 0;
    boolean readOnly = false;
    
    // Return the data type of the model
    public Class<?> getType() {
        return Integer.class;
    }

    public Object getValue() {
        return data;
    }
    
    // Override the default implementation in Object
    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return Integer.toHexString(data);
    }

    public boolean isReadOnly() {
        return readOnly;
    }

    public void setReadOnly(boolean newStatus) {
        readOnly = newStatus;
    }

    public void setValue(Object newValue)
            throws ReadOnlyException, ConversionException {
        if (readOnly)
            throw new ReadOnlyException();
            
        // Already the same type as the internal representation
        if (newValue instanceof Integer)
            data = (Integer) newValue;
        
        // Conversion from a string is required
        else if (newValue instanceof String)
            try {
                data = Integer.parseInt((String) newValue, 16);
            } catch (NumberFormatException e) {
                throw new ConversionException();
            }
        else
             // Don't know how to convert any other types
            throw new ConversionException();

        // Reverse decode the hexadecimal value
    }
}
        
// Instantiate the property and set its data
MyProperty property = new MyProperty();
property.setValue(42);
        
// Bind it to a component
final TextField tf = new TextField("Name", property);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The components get the displayed value by the
                <methodname>toString()</methodname> method, so it is necessary to override
                it. To allow editing the value, value returned in the
                <methodname>toString()</methodname> must be in a format that is accepted
                by the <methodname>setValue()</methodname> method, unless the property is
                read-only. The <methodname>toString()</methodname> can perform any type
                conversion necessary to make the internal type a string, and the
                <methodname>setValue()</methodname> must be able to make a reverse
                conversion.
            </para>

            <para>
                The implementation example does not notify about changes in the property
                value or in the read-only mode. You should normally also implement at
                least the <classname>Property.ValueChangeNotifier</classname> and
                <classname>Property.ReadOnlyStatusChangeNotifier</classname>. See the
                <classname>ObjectProperty</classname> class for an example of the
                implementation.
            </para>
        </section>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="datamodel.items">
		<title>Holding properties in Items</title>

		<para>
			The <classname>Item</classname> interface provides access to a set of named
			properties. Each property is identified by a <emphasis>property
			identifier</emphasis> (PID) and a reference to such a property can be queried
			from an <classname>Item</classname> with
			<methodname>getItemProperty()</methodname> using the identifier.
        </para>

        <para>
            Examples on the use of items include rows in a <classname>Table</classname>,
            with the properties corresponding to table columns, nodes in a
            <classname>Tree</classname>, and the the data bound to a
            <classname>Form</classname>, with item's properties bound to individual form
            fields.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Items are generally equivalent to objects in the object-oriented model, but
			with the exception that they are configurable and provide an event handling
			mechanism. The simplest way to utilize <classname>Item</classname> interface
			is to use existing implementations. Provided utility classes include a
			configurable property set (<classname>PropertysetItem</classname>) and a
			bean-to-item adapter (<classname>BeanItem</classname>). Also, a
			<classname>Form</classname> implements the interface and can therefore be used
			directly as an item.
		</para>

		<para>
			In addition to being used indirectly by many user interface components, items
			provide the basic data model underlying the <classname>Form</classname>
			component.  In simple cases, forms can even be generated automatically from
			items.  The properties of the item correspond to the fields of the form.
		</para>

        <para>
            The <classname>Item</classname> interface defines inner interfaces for
            maintaining the item property set and listening changes made to
            it. <classname>PropertySetChangeEvent</classname> events can be emitted by a
            class implementing the <classname>PropertySetChangeNotifier</classname>
            interface. They can be received through the
            <classname>PropertySetChangeListener</classname> interface.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.items.propertysetitem">
            <title>The <classname>PropertysetItem</classname> Implementation</title>

            <para>
                The <classname>PropertysetItem</classname> is a generic implementation of
                the <classname>Item</classname> interface that allows storing
                properties. The properties are added with
                <methodname>addItemProperty()</methodname>, which takes a name and the
                property as parameters.
            </para>

            <para>
                The following example demonstrates a typical case of collecting
                <classname>ObjectProperty</classname> properties in an item:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[PropertysetItem item = new PropertysetItem();
item.addItemProperty("name", new ObjectProperty("Zaphod"));
item.addItemProperty("age", new ObjectProperty(42));
        
// Bind it to a component
Form form = new Form();
form.setItemDataSource(item);]]></programlisting>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.items.beanitem">
            <title>Wrapping a Bean in a <classname>BeanItem</classname></title>

            <para>
                The <classname>BeanItem</classname> implementation of the
                <classname>Item</classname> interface is a wrapper for Java Bean
                objects. In fact, only the setters and getters are required while
                serialization and other bean features are not, so you can wrap almost any
                POJOs with minimal requirements.
            </para>

<programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Here is a bean (or more exactly a POJO)
class Person {
    String name;
    int    age;
    
    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }
    
    public void setName(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
    
    public Integer getAge() {
        return age;
    }
    
    public void setAge(Integer age) {
        this.age = age.intValue();
    }
}

// Create an instance of the bean
Person bean = new Person();
        
// Wrap it in a BeanItem
BeanItem<Person> item = new BeanItem<Person>(bean);
        
// Bind it to a component
Form form = new Form();
form.setItemDataSource(item);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                You can use the <methodname>getBean()</methodname> method to get a
                reference to the underlying bean.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.items.beanitem.nested">
                <title>Nested Beans</title>

                <para>
                    You may often have composite classes where one class "has a" another
                    class. For example, consider the following
                    <classname>Planet</classname> class which "has a" discoverer:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Here is a bean with two nested beans
public class Planet implements Serializable {
    String name;
    Person discoverer;
    
    public Planet(String name, Person discoverer) {
        this.name = name;
        this.discoverer = discoverer;
    }

    ... getters and setters ...
}

...
// Create an instance of the bean
Planet planet = new Planet("Uranus",
                    new Person("William Herschel", 1738));]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    When shown in a <classname>Form</classname>, for example, you would
                    want to list the properties of the nested bean along the properties of
                    the composite bean. You can do that by binding the properties of the
                    nested bean individually with a <classname>MethodProperty</classname>
                    or <classname>NestedMethodProperty</classname>. You should usually
                    hide the nested bean from binding as a property by listing only the
                    bound properties in the constructor.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Wrap it in a BeanItem and hide the nested bean property
BeanItem<Planet> item = new BeanItem<Planet>(planet,
        new String[]{"name"});
    
// Bind the nested properties.
// Use NestedMethodProperty to bind using dot notation.
item.addItemProperty("discoverername",
    new NestedMethodProperty(planet, "discoverer.name"));
    
// The other way is to use regular MethodProperty.
item.addItemProperty("discovererborn",
     new MethodProperty<Person>(planet.getDiscoverer(),
                                "born"));]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The difference is that <classname>NestedMethodProperty</classname>
                    does not access the nested bean immediately but only when accessing
                    the property values, while when using
                    <classname>MethodProperty</classname> the nested bean is accessed when
                    creating the method property. The difference is only significant if
                    the nested bean can be null or be changed later.
                </para>

                <para>
                    You can use such a bean item for example in a
                    <classname>Form</classname> as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Bind it to a component
Form form = new Form();
form.setItemDataSource(item);
    
// Nicer captions
form.getField("discoverername").setCaption("Discoverer");
form.getField("discovererborn").setCaption("Born");]]></programlisting>

                <figure xml:id="figure.datamodel.items.beanitem.nested">
                    <title>A <classname>Form</classname> with Nested Bean Properties</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/datamodel/beanitem-nested-beans.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>
                    The <classname>BeanContainer</classname> and
                    <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname> allow easy definition of
                    nested bean properties with
                    <methodname>addNestedContainerProperty()</methodname>, as described in
                    <xref linkend="datamodel.container.beancontainer.nestedproperties"/>.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding">
        <title>Creating Forms by Binding Fields to Items</title>

		<para>
            <emphasis>Because of pressing release schedules to get this edition to your
            hands, we were unable to completely update this chapter. Some form handling is
            still under work, especially form validation.</emphasis>
        </para>

        <para>
            Most applications in existence have forms of some sort. Forms contain fields,
            which you want to bind to a data source, an item in the Vaadin data
            model. <classname>FieldGroup</classname> provides an easy way to bind fields
            to the properties of an item. You can use it by first creating a layout with
            some fields, and then call it to bind the fields to the data source. You can
            also let the <classname>FieldGroup</classname> create the fields using a field
            factory. It can also handle commits. Notice that
            <classname>FieldGroup</classname> is not a user interface component, so you
            can not add it to a layout.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.simple">
            <title>Simple Binding</title>

            <!-- TODO Vaadin 7 -->
            <para>
                Let us start with a data model that has an item with a couple of
                properties. The item could be any item type, as described earlier.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have an item
PropertysetItem item = new PropertysetItem();
item.addItemProperty("name", new ObjectProperty<String>("Zaphod"));
item.addItemProperty("age", new ObjectProperty<Integer>(42));]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Next, you would design a form for editing the data. The
                <classname>FormLayout</classname> (<xref linkend="layout.formlayout"/> is
                ideal for forms, but you could use any other layout as well.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have some layout and create the fields
FormLayout form = new FormLayout();

TextField nameField = new TextField("Name");
form.addComponent(nameField);

TextField ageField = new TextField("Age");
form.addComponent(ageField);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Then, we can bind the fields to the data as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Now create the binder and bind the fields
FieldGroup binder = new FieldGroup(item);
binder.bind(nameField, "name");
binder.bind(ageField, "age");]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The above way of binding is not different from simply calling
                <methodname>setPropertyDataSource()</methodname> for the fields. It does,
                however, register the fields in the field group, which for example enables
                buffering or validation of the fields using the field group, as described
                in <xref linkend="datamodel.itembinding.buffering"/>.
            </para>

            <para>
                Next, we consider more practical uses for a
                <classname>FieldGroup</classname>.
            </para>

            <!-- TODO Vaadin 7: What's the point??? -->
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.fieldfactory">
            <title>Using a <interfacename>FieldFactory</interfacename> to Build and Bind Fields</title>

            <para>
                Using the <methodname>buildAndBind()</methodname> methods,
                <classname>FieldGroup</classname> can create fields for you using a
                <interfacename>FieldGroupFieldFactory</interfacename>, but you still have
                to add them to the correct position in your layout.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[// Have some layout
FormLayout form = new FormLayout();
        
// Now create a binder that can also create the fields
// using the default field factory
FieldGroup binder = new FieldGroup(item);
form.addComponent(binder.buildAndBind("Name", "name"));
form.addComponent(binder.buildAndBind("Age", "age"));]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.formclass">
            <title>Binding Member Fields</title>

            <para>
                The <methodname>bindMemberFields()</methodname> method in
                <classname>FieldGroup</classname> uses reflection to bind the properties of an
                item to field components that are member variables of a class. Hence, if
                you implement a form as a class with the fields stored as member
                variables, you can use this method to bind them super-easy.
            </para>

            <para>
                The item properties are mapped to the members by the property ID and the
                name of the member variable. If you want to map a property with a
                different ID to a member, you can use the <literal>@PropertyId</literal>
                annotation for the member, with the property ID as the parameter.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example:
            </para>

            <book-example id="datamodel.itembinding.formclass.extended"></book-example>
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have an item
PropertysetItem item = new PropertysetItem();
item.addItemProperty("name", new ObjectProperty<String>("Zaphod"));
item.addItemProperty("age", new ObjectProperty<Integer>(42));

// Define a form as a class that extends some layout
class MyForm extends FormLayout {
    // Member that will bind to the "name" property
    TextField name = new TextField("Name");
    
    // Member that will bind to the "age" property 
    @PropertyId("age")
    TextField ageField = new TextField("Age");
    
    public MyForm() {
        // Customize the layout a bit
        setSpacing(true);
        
        // Add the fields
        addComponent(name);
        addComponent(ageField);
    }
}
        
// Create one
MyForm form = new MyForm();
        
// Now create a binder that can also creates the fields
// using the default field factory
FieldGroup binder = new FieldGroup(item);
binder.bindMemberFields(form);

// And the form can be used in an higher-level layout
layout.addComponent(form);]]></programlisting>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.formclass.customcomponent">
                <title>Encapsulating in <classname>CustomComponent</classname></title>

                <para>
                    Using a <classname>CustomComponent</classname> can be better for hiding
                    the implementation details than extending a layout. Also, the use of the
                    <classname>FieldGroup</classname> can be encapsulated in the form class.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Consider the following as an alternative for the form implementation
                    presented earlier:
                </para>

                <book-example id="datamodel.itembinding.formclass.customcomponent"></book-example>
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[// A form component that allows editing an item
class MyForm extends CustomComponent {
    // Member that will bind to the "name" property
    TextField name = new TextField("Name");
    
    // Member that will bind to the "age" property 
    @PropertyId("age")
    TextField ageField = new TextField("Age");
    
    public MyForm(Item item) {
        FormLayout layout = new FormLayout();
        layout.addComponent(name);
        layout.addComponent(ageField);
        
        // Now use a binder to bind the members
        FieldGroup binder = new FieldGroup(item);
        binder.bindMemberFields(this);

        setCompositionRoot(layout);
    }
}
        
// And the form can be used as a component
layout.addComponent(new MyForm(item));]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.buffering">
            <title>Buffering Forms</title>

            <para>
                Just like for individual fields, as described in <xref
                linkend="components.fields.buffering"/>, a
                <classname>FieldGroup</classname> can handle buffering the form content so
                that it is written to the item data source only when
                <methodname>commit()</methodname> is called for the group. It runs
                validation for all fields in the group and writes their values to the item
                data source only if all fields pass the validation. Edits can be
                discarded, so that the field values are reloaded from the data source, by
                calling <methodname>discard()</methodname>. Buffering is enabled by
                default, but can be disabled by calling
                <methodname>setBuffered(false)</methodname> for the
                <classname>FieldGroup</classname>.
            </para>

            <book-example id="datamodel.itembinding.formclass.customcomponent"></book-example>
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have an item of some sort
final PropertysetItem item = new PropertysetItem();
item.addItemProperty("name", new ObjectProperty<String>("Q"));
item.addItemProperty("age",  new ObjectProperty<Integer>(42));

// Have some layout and create the fields
Panel form = new Panel("Buffered Form");
form.setContent(new FormLayout());

// Build and bind the fields using the default field factory
final FieldGroup binder = new FieldGroup(item);
form.addComponent(binder.buildAndBind("Name", "name"));
form.addComponent(binder.buildAndBind("Age",  "age"));

// Enable buffering (actually enabled by default)
binder.setBuffered(true);
        
// A button to commit the buffer
form.addComponent(new Button("OK", new ClickListener() {
    @Override
    public void buttonClick(ClickEvent event) {
        try {
            binder.commit();
            Notification.show("Thanks!");
        } catch (CommitException e) {
            Notification.show("You fail!");
        }
    }
}));

// A button to discard the buffer
form.addComponent(new Button("Discard", new ClickListener() {
    @Override
    public void buttonClick(ClickEvent event) {
        binder.discard();
        Notification.show("Discarded!");
    }
}));]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.beans">
            <title>Binding Fields to a Bean</title>

            <para>
                The <classname>BeanFieldGroup</classname> makes it easier to bind fields
                to a bean. It also handles binding to nested beans properties. The build a
                field bound to a nested bean property, identify the property with dot
                notation. For example, if a <classname>Person</classname> bean has a
                <literal>address</literal> property with an <classname>Address</classname>
                type, which in turn has a <literal>street</literal> property, you could
                build a field bound to the property with
                <methodname>buildAndBind("Street", "address.street")</methodname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                The input to fields bound to a bean can be validated using the Java Bean
                Validation API, as described in <xref
                linkend="datamodel.itembinding.beanvalidation"/>. The
                <classname>BeanFieldGroup</classname> automatically adds a
                <classname>BeanValidator</classname> to every field if a bean validation
                implementation is included in the classpath.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.beanvalidation">
            <title>Bean Validation</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin allows using the Java Bean Validation API 1.0 (JSR-303) for
                validating input from fields bound to bean properties before the values
                are committed to the bean. The validation is done based on annotations on
                the bean properties, which are used for creating the actual validators
                automatically. See <xref linkend="components.fields.validation"/> for
                general information about validation.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Using bean validation requires an implementation of the Bean Validation
                API, such as Hibernate Validator
                (<filename>hibernate-validator-4.2.0.Final.jar</filename> or later) or
                Apache Bean Validation. The implementation JAR must be included in the
                project classpath when using the bean validation, or otherwise an internal
                error is thrown.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Bean validation is especially useful when persisting entity beans with the
                Vaadin JPAContainer, described in <xref linkend="jpacontainer"/>.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.beanvalidation.annotations">
                <title>Annotations</title>

                <para>
                    The validation constraints are defined as annotations. For example,
                    consider the following bean:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Here is a bean
public class Person implements Serializable {
    @NotNull
    @javax.validation.constraints.Size(min=2, max=10)
    String name;
    
    @Min(1)
    @Max(130)
    int age;
    
    // ... setters and getters ...
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    For a complete list of allowed constraints for different data types,
                    please see the <link
                    xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/6/tutorial/doc/gircz.html">Bean
                    Validation API documentation</link>.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.beanvalidation.validating">
                <title>Validating the Beans</title>

                <para>
                    Validating a bean is done with a <classname>BeanValidator</classname>,
                    which you initialize with the name of the bean property it should
                    validate and add it the the editor field.
                </para>

                <para>
                    In the following example, we validate a single unbuffered field:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[Person bean = new Person("Mung bean", 100);
BeanItem<Person> item = new BeanItem<Person> (bean);
    
// Create an editor bound to a bean field
TextField firstName = new TextField("First Name",
        item.getItemProperty("name"));
    
// Add the bean validator
firstName.addValidator(new BeanValidator(Person.class, "name"));
    
firstName.setImmediate(true);
layout.addComponent(firstName);]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    In this case, the validation is done immediately after focus leaves
                    the field. You could do the same for the other field as well.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Bean validators are automatically created when using a
                    <classname>BeanFieldGroup</classname>.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have a bean
Person bean = new Person("Mung bean", 100);
        
// Form for editing the bean
final BeanFieldGroup<Person> binder =
        new BeanFieldGroup<Person>(Person.class);
binder.setItemDataSource(bean);
layout.addComponent(binder.buildAndBind("Name", "name"));
layout.addComponent(binder.buildAndBind("Age", "age"));

// Buffer the form content
binder.setBuffered(true);
layout.addComponent(new Button("OK", new ClickListener() {
    @Override
    public void buttonClick(ClickEvent event) {
        try {
            binder.commit();
        } catch (CommitException e) {
        }
    }
}));]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.itembinding.beanvalidation.locale">
                <title>Locale Setting for Bean Validation</title>

                <para>
                    The validation error messages are defined in the bean validation
                    implementation, in a
                    <filename>ValidationMessages.properties</filename> file. The message
                    is shown in the language specified with the locale setting for the
                    form. The default language is English, but for example Hibernate
                    Validator contains translations of the messages for a number of
                    languages. If other languages are needed, you need to provide a
                    translation of the properties file.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="datamodel.container">
		<title>Collecting Items in Containers</title>

        <indexterm xml:id="term.datamodel.container" class="startofrange">
            <primary><classname>Container</classname></primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>
            The <classname>Container</classname> interface is the highest containment
            level of the Vaadin data model, for containing items (rows) which in turn
            contain properties (columns). Containers can therefore represent tabular data,
            which can be viewed in a <classname>Table</classname> or some other selection
            component, as well as hierarchical data.
        </para>

        <para>
            The items contained in a container are identified by an <emphasis>item
            identifier</emphasis> or <emphasis>IID</emphasis>, and the properties by a
            <emphasis>property identifier</emphasis> or <emphasis>PID</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.container.intro">
            <title>Basic Use of Containers</title>

            <para>
                The basic use of containers involves creating one, adding items to it, and
                binding it as a container data source of a component.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.intro.default">
                <title>Default Containers and Delegation</title>

                <para>
                    Before saying anything about creation of containers, it should be
                    noted that all components that can be bound to a container data source
                    are by default bound to a default container. For example,
                    <classname>Table</classname> is bound to a
                    <classname>IndexedContainer</classname>, <classname>Tree</classname>
                    to a <classname>HierarchicalContainer</classname>, and so forth.
                </para>

                <para>
                    All of the user interface components using containers also implement
                    the relevant container interfaces themselves, so that the access to
                    the underlying data source is delegated through the component.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[// Create a table with one column
Table table = new Table("My Table");
table.addContainerProperty("col1", String.class, null);

// Access items and properties through the component
table.addItem("row1"); // Create item by explicit ID
Item item1 = table.getItem("row1");
Property property1 = item1.getItemProperty("col1");
property1.setValue("some given value");

// Equivant access through the container
Container container = table.getContainerDataSource();
container.addItem("row2");
Item item2 = container.getItem("row2");
Property property2 = item2.getItemProperty("col1");
property2.setValue("another given value");]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.intro.creating">
                <title>Creating and Binding a Container</title>

                <para>
                    A container is created and bound to a component as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// Create a container
Container container = new IndexedContainer();

// Define the properties (columns) if required by container
container.addContainerProperty("name", String.class, "none");
container.addContainerProperty("volume", Double.class, 0.0);

... add items ...

// Bind it to a component
Table table = new Table("My Table");
table.setContainerDataSource(container);]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Most components also allow passing the container in the constructor.
                    Creation depends on the container type. For some containers, such as
                    the <classname>IndexedContainer</classname>, you need to define the
                    contained properties (columns) as was done above, while some others
                    determine them otherwise. The definition of a property with
                    <methodname>addContainerProperty()</methodname> requires a unique
                    property ID, type, and a default value. You can also give
                    <parameter>null</parameter>.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Vaadin has a several built-in in-memory container implementations,
                    such as <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> and
                    <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname>, which are easy to use for
                    setting up nonpersistent data storages. For persistent data, either
                    the built-in <classname>SQLContainer</classname> or the
                    <classname>JPAContainer</classname> add-on container can be used.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.intro.adding">
                <title>Adding Items and Accessing Properties</title>

                <para>
                    Items can be added to a container with the
                    <methodname>addItem()</methodname> method. The parameterless version
                    of the method automatically generates the item ID.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[// Create an item
Object itemId = container.addItem();]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Properties can be requested from container by first requesting an item
                    with <methodname>getItem()</methodname> and then getting the
                    properties from the item with
                    <methodname>getItemProperty()</methodname>.
                </para>


                <programlisting><![CDATA[// Get the item object
Item item = container.getItem(itemId);

// Access a property in the item
Property<String> nameProperty =
        item.getItemProperty("name");

// Do something with the property
nameProperty.setValue("box");]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    You can also get a property directly by the item and property ids with
                    <methodname>getContainerProperty()</methodname>.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[container.getContainerProperty(itemId, "volume").setValue(5.0);]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.intro.givenid">
                <title>Adding Items by Given ID</title>

                <para>
                    Some containers, such as <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> and
                    <classname>HierarchicalContainer</classname>, allow adding items by a
                    given ID, which can be any <classname>Object</classname>.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[Item item = container.addItem("agivenid");
item.getItemProperty("name").setValue("barrel");
Item.getItemProperty("volume").setValue(119.2);]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Notice that the actual item <emphasis>is not</emphasis> given as a
                    parameter to the method, only its ID, as the interface assumes that
                    the container itself creates all the items it contains. Some container
                    implementations can provide methods to add externally created items,
                    and they can even assume that the item ID object is also the item
                    itself. Lazy containers might not create the item immediately, but
                    lazily when it is accessed by its ID.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.container.inner">
            <title>Container Subinterfaces</title>

            <para>
                The <classname>Container</classname> interface contains inner interfaces
                that container implementations can implement to fulfill different features
                required by components that present container data.
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><interfacename>Container.Filterable</interfacename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Filterable containers allow filtering the contained items by
                            filters, as described in <xref
                            linkend="datamodel.container.filtered"/>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><interfacename>Container.Hierarchical</interfacename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Hierarchical containers allow representing hierarchical
                            relationships between items and are required by the
                            <classname>Tree</classname> and
                            <classname>TreeTable</classname> components. The
                            <classname>HierarchicalContainer</classname> is a built-in
                            in-memory container for hierarchical data, and is used as the
                            default container for the tree components. The
                            <classname>FilesystemContainer</classname> provides access to
                            browsing the content of a file system. Also
                            <classname>JPAContainer</classname> is hierarchical, as
                            described in <xref
                            linkend="jpacontainer.usage.hierarchical"/>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><interfacename>Container.Indexed</interfacename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            An indexed container allows accessing items by an index
                            number, not just their item ID. This feature is required by
                            some components, especially <classname>Table</classname>,
                            which needs to provide lazy access to large containers. The
                            <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> is a basic in-memory
                            implementation, as described in <xref
                            linkend="datamodel.container.indexedcontainer"/>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><interfacename>Container.Ordered</interfacename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            An ordered container allows traversing the items in successive
                            order in either direction. Most built-in containers are
                            ordered.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><interfacename>Container.SimpleFilterable</interfacename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This interface enables filtering a container by string
                            matching with
                            <methodname>addContainerFilter()</methodname>. The filtering
                            is done by either searching the given string anywhere in a
                            property value, or as its prefix.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><interfacename>Container.Sortable</interfacename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            A sortable container is required by some components that allow
                            sorting the content, such as <classname>Table</classname>,
                            where the user can click a column header to sort the table by
                            the column. Some other components, such as
                            <classname>Calendar</classname>, may require that the content
                            is sorted to be able to display it properly. Depending on the
                            implementation, sorting can be done only when the
                            <methodname>sort()</methodname> method is called, or the
                            container is automatically kept in order according to the last
                            call of the method.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

            <para>
                See the API documentation for a detailed description of the interfaces.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.container.indexedcontainer">
            <title><classname>IndexedContainer</classname></title>

            <para>
                The <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> is an in-memory container that
                implements the <interfacename>Indexed</interfacename> interface to allow
                referencing the items by an index. <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> is
                used as the default container in most selection components in Vaadin.
            </para>

            <para>
                The properties need to be defined with
                <methodname>addContainerProperty()</methodname>, which takes the property
                ID, type, and a default value. This must be done before any items are
                added to the container.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Create the container
IndexedContainer container = new IndexedContainer();
        
// Define the properties (columns)
container.addContainerProperty("name", String.class, "noname");
container.addContainerProperty("volume", Double.class, -1.0d);

// Add some items
Object content[][] = {{"jar", 2.0}, {"bottle", 0.75},
                      {"can", 1.5}};
for (Object[] row: content) {
    Item newItem = container.getItem(container.addItem());
    newItem.getItemProperty("name").setValue(row[0]);
    newItem.getItemProperty("volume").setValue(row[1]);
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                New items are added with <methodname>addItem()</methodname>, which returns
                the item ID of the new item, or by giving the item ID as a parameter as
                was described earlier. Note that the <classname>Table</classname>
                component, which has <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> as its
                default container, has a conveniency <methodname>addItem()</methodname>
                method that allows adding items as object vectors containing the property
                values.
            </para>

            <para>
                The container implements the
                <interfacename>Container.Indexed</interfacename> feature to allow
                accessing the item IDs by their index number, with
                <methodname>getIdByIndex()</methodname>, etc. The feature is required
                mainly for internal purposes of some components, such as
                <classname>Table</classname>, which uses it to enable lazy transmission of
                table data to the client-side.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.container.beancontainer">
            <title><classname>BeanContainer</classname></title>

            <para>
                The <classname>BeanContainer</classname> is an in-memory container for
                JavaBean objects. Each contained bean is wrapped inside a
                <classname>BeanItem</classname> wrapper. The item properties are
                determined automatically by inspecting the getter and setter methods of
                the class. This requires that the bean class has public visibility, local
                classes for example are not allowed. Only beans of the same type can be
                added to the container.
            </para>

            <para>
                The generic has two parameters: a bean type and an item identifier type.
                The item identifiers can be obtained by defining a custom resolver, using
                a specific item property for the IDs, or by giving item IDs explicitly. As
                such, it is more general than the
                <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname>, which uses the bean object
                itself as the item identifier, making the use usually simpler. Managing the item
                IDs makes <classname>BeanContainer</classname> more complex to use, but it
                is necessary in some cases where the <methodname>equals()</methodname> or
                <methodname>hashCode()</methodname> methods have been reimplemented in the
                bean.
            </para>

            <book-example id="datamodel.container.beancontainer.basic" style="float: right"></book-example>
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Here is a JavaBean
public class Bean implements Serializable {
    String name;
    double energy; // Energy content in kJ/100g
    
    public Bean(String name, double energy) {
        this.name   = name;
        this.energy = energy;
    }
    
    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }
    
    public void setName(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
    
    public double getEnergy() {
        return energy;
    }
    
    public void setEnergy(double energy) {
        this.energy = energy;
    }
}

void basic(VerticalLayout layout) {
    // Create a container for such beans with
    // strings as item IDs.
    BeanContainer<String, Bean> beans =
        new BeanContainer<String, Bean>(Bean.class);
    
    // Use the name property as the item ID of the bean
    beans.setBeanIdProperty("name");

    // Add some beans to it
    beans.addBean(new Bean("Mung bean",   1452.0));
    beans.addBean(new Bean("Chickpea",    686.0));
    beans.addBean(new Bean("Lentil",      1477.0));
    beans.addBean(new Bean("Common bean", 129.0));
    beans.addBean(new Bean("Soybean",     1866.0));

    // Bind a table to it
    Table table = new Table("Beans of All Sorts", beans);
    layout.addComponent(table);
}]]></programlisting>
            
            <para>
                To use explicit item IDs, use the methods <methodname>addItem(Object,
                Object)</methodname>, <methodname>addItemAfter(Object, Object,
                Object)</methodname>, and <methodname>addItemAt(int, Object,
                Object)</methodname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                It is not possible to add additional properties to the container, except
                properties in a nested bean.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.beancontainer.nestedproperties">
                <title>Nested Properties</title>

                <indexterm xml:id="term.datamodel.container.beancontainer.nestedproperties" class="startofrange">
                    <primary>nested bean properties</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <para>
                    If you have a nested bean with a 1:1 relationship inside a bean type
                    contained in a <classname>BeanContainer</classname> or
                    <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname>, you can add its properties
                    to the container by specifying them with
                    <methodname>addNestedContainerProperty()</methodname>. The feature is
                    defined at the level of <classname>AbstractBeanContainer</classname>.

                    <indexterm><primary><methodname>addNestedContainerProperty()</methodname></primary></indexterm>
                </para>

                <para>
                    As with a top-level bean in a bean container, also a nested bean must
                    have public visibility or otherwise an access exception is
                    thrown. Intermediary getters returning a nested bean must always
                    return a non-null value.
                </para>

                <para>
                    For example, assume that we have the following two beans with the
                    first one nested inside the second one.
                </para>
 
                <book-example id="datamodel.container.beanitemcontainer.nestedbean" style="float: right"></book-example>
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[/** Bean to be nested */
public class EqCoord implements Serializable {
    double rightAscension; /* In angle hours */
    double declination;    /* In degrees     */

    ... constructor and setters and getters for the properties ...
}

/** Bean containing a nested bean */
public class Star implements Serializable {
    String  name;
    EqCoord equatorial; /* Nested bean */

    ... constructor and setters and getters for the properties ...
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    After creating the container, you can declare the nested properties by
                    specifying their property identifiers with the
                    <methodname>addNestedContainerProperty()</methodname> in dot
                    notation.
                </para>

                <book-example id="datamodel.container.beanitemcontainer.nestedbean" style="float: right"></book-example>
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Create a container for beans
final BeanItemContainer<Star> stars =
    new BeanItemContainer<Star>(Star.class);

// Declare the nested properties to be used in the container
stars.addNestedContainerProperty("equatorial.rightAscension");
stars.addNestedContainerProperty("equatorial.declination");

// Add some items
stars.addBean(new Star("Sirius",  new EqCoord(6.75, 16.71611)));
stars.addBean(new Star("Polaris", new EqCoord(2.52, 89.26417)));]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    If you bind such a container to a <classname>Table</classname>, you
                    probably also need to set the column headers. Notice that the entire
                    nested bean itself is still a property in the container and would be
                    displayed in its own column. The <methodname>toString()</methodname>
                    method is used for obtaining the displayed value, which is by default
                    an object reference. You normally do not want this, so you can hide
                    the column with <methodname>setVisibleColumns()</methodname>.

                    <indexterm><primary><methodname>setVisibleColumns()</methodname></primary></indexterm>
                </para>

                <book-example id="datamodel.container.beanitemcontainer.nestedbean" style="float: right"></book-example>
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Put them in a table
Table table = new Table("Stars", stars);
table.setColumnHeader("equatorial.rightAscension", "RA");
table.setColumnHeader("equatorial.declination",    "Decl");
table.setPageLength(table.size());

// Have to set explicitly to hide the "equatorial" property
table.setVisibleColumns(new Object[]{"name",
    "equatorial.rightAscension", "equatorial.declination"});]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The resulting table is shown in <xref
                    linkend="figure.datamodel.container.beancontainer.nestedproperties"/>.
                </para>

                <figure xml:id="figure.datamodel.container.beancontainer.nestedproperties">
                    <title><classname>Table</classname> Bound to a <classname>BeanContainer</classname> with Nested Properties</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/datamodel/beanitemcontainer-nested-beans.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/datamodel/beanitemcontainer-nested-beans.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>
                    The bean binding in <classname>AbstractBeanContainer</classname>
                    normally uses the <classname>MethodProperty</classname> implementation
                    of the <classname>Property</classname> interface to access the bean
                    properties using the setter and getter methods. For nested properties,
                    the <classname>NestedMethodProperty</classname> implementation is
                    used.
                    
                    <indexterm><primary><classname>MethodProperty</classname></primary></indexterm>
                    <indexterm><primary><classname>NestedMethodProperty</classname></primary></indexterm>
                </para>

                <indexterm startref="term.datamodel.container.beancontainer.nestedproperties" class="endofrange"/>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.beancontainer.idresolver">
                <title>Defining a Bean ID Resolver</title>

                <para>
                    If a bean ID resolver is set using
                    <methodname>setBeanIdResolver()</methodname> or
                    <methodname>setBeanIdProperty()</methodname>, the methods
                    <methodname>addBean()</methodname>,
                    <methodname>addBeanAfter()</methodname>,
                    <methodname>addBeanAt()</methodname> and
                    <methodname>addAll()</methodname> can be used to add items to the
                    container. If one of these methods is called, the resolver is used to
                    generate an identifier for the item (must not return
                    <parameter>null</parameter>).
                </para>

                <para>
                    Note that explicit item identifiers can also be used when a resolver has
                    been set by calling the <methodname>addItem*()</methodname> methods - the
                    resolver is only used when adding beans using the
                    <methodname>addBean*()</methodname> or
                    <methodname>addAll(Collection)</methodname> methods.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.container.beanitemcontainer">
            <title><classname>BeanItemContainer</classname></title>

            <para>
                <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname> is a container for JavaBean
                objects where each bean is wrapped inside a
                <classname>BeanItem</classname> wrapper. The item properties are
                determined automatically by inspecting the getter and setter methods of
                the class. This requires that the bean class has public visibility, local
                classes for example are not allowed. Only beans of the same type can be
                added to the container.
            </para>

            <para>
                <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname> is a specialized version of the
                <classname>BeanContainer</classname> described in <xref
                linkend="datamodel.container.beancontainer"/>. It uses the bean itself as
                the item identifier, which makes it a bit easier to use than
                <classname>BeanContainer</classname> in many cases. The latter is,
                however, needed if the bean has reimplemented the
                <methodname>equals()</methodname> or <methodname>hashCode()</methodname>
                methods.
            </para>

            <para>
                Let us revisit the example given in <xref
                linkend="datamodel.container.beancontainer"/> using the
                <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname>.
            </para>

            <book-example id="datamodel.container.beanitemcontainer.basic" style="float: right"></book-example>
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[// Create a container for the beans
BeanItemContainer<Bean> beans =
    new BeanItemContainer<Bean>(Bean.class);
    
// Add some beans to it
beans.addBean(new Bean("Mung bean",   1452.0));
beans.addBean(new Bean("Chickpea",    686.0));
beans.addBean(new Bean("Lentil",      1477.0));
beans.addBean(new Bean("Common bean", 129.0));
beans.addBean(new Bean("Soybean",     1866.0));

// Bind a table to it
Table table = new Table("Beans of All Sorts", beans);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                It is not possible to add additional properties to a
                <classname>BeanItemContainer</classname>, except properties in a nested
                bean, as described in <xref linkend="datamodel.container.beancontainer"/>.

                <indexterm><primary>nested bean properties</primary></indexterm>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Iterating Over a Container</title>

            <para>
                As the items in a <classname>Container</classname> are not necessarily
                indexed, iterating over the items has to be done using an
                <classname>Iterator</classname>. The <methodname>getItemIds()</methodname>
                method of <classname>Container</classname> returns a
                <classname>Collection</classname> of item identifiers over which you can
                iterate. The following example demonstrates a typical case where you
                iterate over the values of check boxes in a column of a
                <classname>Table</classname> component. The context of the example is the
                example used in <xref linkend="components.table"/>.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Collect the results of the iteration into this string.
String items = "";

// Iterate over the item identifiers of the table.
for (Iterator i = table.getItemIds().iterator(); i.hasNext();) {
    // Get the current item identifier, which is an integer.
    int iid = (Integer) i.next();
    
    // Now get the actual item from the table.
    Item item = table.getItem(iid);
    
    // And now we can get to the actual checkbox object.
    Button button = (Button)
            (item.getItemProperty("ismember").getValue());
    
    // If the checkbox is selected.
    if ((Boolean)button.getValue() == true) {
        // Do something with the selected item; collect the
        // first names in a string.
        items += item.getItemProperty("First Name")
                     .getValue() + " ";
    }
}

// Do something with the results; display the selected items.
layout.addComponent (new Label("Selected items: " + items));]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Notice that the <methodname>getItemIds()</methodname> returns an
                <emphasis>unmodifiable collection</emphasis>, so the
                <classname>Container</classname> may not be modified during iteration. You
                can not, for example, remove items from the
                <classname>Container</classname> during iteration. The modification
                includes modification in another thread. If the
                <classname>Container</classname> is modified during iteration, a
                <classname>ConcurrentModificationException</classname> is thrown and the
                iterator may be left in an undefined state.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="datamodel.container.filtered">
            <title><classname>Filterable</classname> Containers</title>

            <indexterm xml:id="term.datamodel.container.filtered.filterable" class="startofrange">
                <primary>Container</primary>
                <secondary>Filterable</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm xml:id="term.datamodel.container.filtered.filters" class="startofrange">
                <primary><classname>Filter</classname> (in <classname>Container</classname>)</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>
                Containers that implement the <classname>Container.Filterable</classname>
                interface can be filtered. For example, the built-in
                <classname>IndexedContainer</classname> and the bean item containers
                implement it. Filtering is typically used for filtering the content of a
                <classname>Table</classname>.

                <indexterm><primary><classname>IndexedContainer</classname></primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary><classname>Table</classname></primary></indexterm>
            </para>

            <para>
                Filters implement the <classname>Filter</classname> interface and you add
                them to a filterable container with the
                <methodname>addContainerFilter()</methodname> method. Container items that
                pass the filter condition are kept and shown in the filterable component.

                <indexterm><primary><methodname>addContainerFilter()</methodname></primary></indexterm>
            </para>

            <book-example id="datamodel.container.filter.basic" style="float: right"></book-example>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[Filter filter = new SimpleStringFilter("name",
        "Douglas", true, false);
table.addContainerFilter(filter);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                If multiple filters are added to a container, they are evaluated using the
                logical AND operator so that only items that are passed by all the filters
                are kept.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.filtered.composite">
                <title>Atomic and Composite Filters</title>

                <para>
                    Filters can be classified as <emphasis>atomic</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis>composite</emphasis>. Atomic filters, such as
                    <classname>SimpleStringFilter</classname>, define a single condition,
                    usually for a specific container property. Composite filters make
                    filtering decisions based on the result of one or more other
                    filters. The built-in composite filters implement the logical
                    operators AND, OR, or NOT.
                </para>

                <para>
                    For example, the following composite filter would filter out items where
                    the <literal>name</literal> property contains the name "Douglas" somewhere
                    <emphasis>and</emphasis> where the <literal>age</literal> property has
                    value less than 42. The properties must have <classname>String</classname>
                    and <classname>Integer</classname> types, respectively.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[
filter = new Or(new SimpleStringFilter("name",
        "Douglas", true, false),
        new Compare.Less("age", 42));]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.filtered.builtin">
                <title>Built-In Filter Types</title>

                <para>
                    The built-in filter types are the following:
                </para>

                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><classname>SimpleStringFilter</classname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>SimpleStringFilter</classname></primary></indexterm>
                            <para>
                                Passes items where the specified property, that must be of
                                <classname>String</classname> type, contains the given
                                <parameter>filterString</parameter> as a substring. If
                                <parameter>ignoreCase</parameter> is
                                <parameter>true</parameter>, the search is case
                                insensitive. If the <parameter>onlyMatchPrefix</parameter> is
                                <parameter>true</parameter>, the substring may only be in the
                                beginning of the string, otherwise it may be elsewhere as
                                well.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><classname>IsNull</classname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>IsNull</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <para>
                                Passes items where the specified property has null value. For
                                in-memory filtering, a simple <literal>==</literal> check is
                                performed. For other containers, the comparison implementation
                                is container dependent, but should correspond to the in-memory
                                null check.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><classname>Equal</classname>,
                            <classname>Greater</classname>,
                            <classname>Less</classname>,
                            <classname>GreaterOrEqual</classname>, and
                            <classname>LessOrEqual</classname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>Equal</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>Greater</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>Less</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>GreaterOrEqual</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>LessOrEqual</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <para>
                                The comparison filter implementations compare the specified
                                property value to the given constant and pass items for which
                                the comparison result is true. The comparison operators are
                                included in the abstract <classname>Compare</classname> class.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                For the <classname>Equal</classname> filter, the
                                <methodname>equals()</methodname> method for the property is
                                used in built-in in-memory containers. In other types of
                                containers, the comparison is container dependent and may use,
                                for example, database comparison operations.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                For the other filters, the property value type must implement
                                the <classname>Comparable</classname> interface to work with
                                the built-in in-memory containers. Again for the other types
                                of containers, the comparison is container dependent.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><classname>And</classname> and <classname>Or</classname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>And</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>Or</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <para>
                                These logical operator filters are composite filters that
                                combine multiple other filters.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><classname>Not</classname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <indexterm><primary><classname>Not</classname> (filter)</primary></indexterm>
                            <para>
                                The logical unary operator filter negates which items are
                                passed by the filter given as the parameter.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="datamodel.container.filtered.custom">
                <title>Implementing Custom Filters</title>

                <para>
                    A custom filter needs to implement the
                    <classname>Container.Filter</classname> interface.
                </para>

                <para>
                    A filter can use a single or multiple properties for the filtering
                    logic. The properties used by the filter must be returned with the
                    <methodname>appliesToProperty()</methodname> method. If the filter
                    applies to a user-defined property or properties, it is customary to
                    give the properties as the first argument for the constructor of the
                    filter.
                </para>

                <book-example id="datamodel.container.filter.custom" style="float: right"></book-example>
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[class MyCustomFilter implements Container.Filter {
    protected String propertyId;
    protected String regex;
    
    public MyCustomFilter(String propertyId, String regex) {
        this.propertyId = propertyId;
        this.regex      = regex;
    }

    /** Tells if this filter works on the given property. */
    @Override
    public boolean appliesToProperty(Object propertyId) {
        return propertyId != null &&
               propertyId.equals(this.propertyId);
    }]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The actual filtering logic is done in the
                    <methodname>passesFilter()</methodname> method, which simply returns
                    <literal>true</literal> if the item should pass the filter and
                    <literal>false</literal> if it should be filtered out.
                </para>

                <book-example id="datamodel.container.filter.custom" style="float: right"></book-example>
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[    /** Apply the filter on an item to check if it passes. */
    @Override
    public boolean passesFilter(Object itemId, Item item)
            throws UnsupportedOperationException {
        // Acquire the relevant property from the item object
        Property p = item.getItemProperty(propertyId);
        
        // Should always check validity
        if (p == null || !p.getType().equals(String.class))
            return false;
        String value = (String) p.getValue();
        
        // The actual filter logic
        return value.matches(regex);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

				<?dbfo-need height="4cm" ?>
                <para>
                    You can use such a custom filter just like any other:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[c.addContainerFilter(
    new MyCustomFilter("Name", (String) tf.getValue()));]]></programlisting>

            </section>

            <indexterm startref="term.datamodel.container.filtered.filters" class="endofrange"/>
            <indexterm startref="term.datamodel.container.filtered.filterable" class="endofrange"/>
        </section>

        <indexterm startref="term.datamodel.container" class="endofrange"/>
	</section>

    <indexterm startref="term.datamodel" class="endofrange"/>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->

