<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="spreadsheet">
	<title>Vaadin Spreadsheet</title>

    <indexterm xml:id="term.spreadsheet" class="startofrange">
        <primary>Spreadsheet</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
        This chapter describes how to use Vaadin Spreadsheet, a Vaadin add-on component
        for displaying and editing Excel spreadsheets within any Vaadin application.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="spreadsheet.overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            Spreadsheet applications have been the sonic screwdriver of business
            computation and data collection for decades. In recent years, spreadsheet web
            services have become popular with cloud-based services that offer better
            collaboration, require no installation, and some are even free to
            use. However, both desktop and third-party cloud-based services are difficult
            to integrate well with web applications. Being a Vaadin UI component, Vaadin
            Spreadsheet allows complete integration with Vaadin applications and further
            with the overall system. The ability to work on Excel spreadsheets allows
            desktop interoperability and integration with document management.
        </para>

        <para>
            By eliminating the dependency on third-party cloud-based services, Vaadin
            Spreadsheet also gives control over the privacy of documents. Growing security
            concerns over cloud-based information storage have increased privacy
            requirements, with lowering trust in global third-party providers. Vaadin
            applications can run on private application servers, and also in the cloud if
            necessary, allowing you to prioritize between security and local and global
            availability.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.spreadsheet.overview.demo">
            <title>Demo for Vaadin Spreadsheet</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="80" smallscale="80%" align="center" fileref="img/spreadsheet/spreadsheet-demo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Vaadin Spreadsheet is a UI component that you use much like any other
            component. It has full size by default, to use all the available space in the
            containing layout. You can directly modify the cell data in the active
            worksheet by entering textual and numerical values, as well as using Excel
            formulas for spreadsheet calculations.
        </para>

        <programlisting lang="java"><![CDATA[Spreadsheet sheet = new Spreadsheet();
sheet.setWidth("400px"); // Full size by default
sheet.setHeight("250px");

// Put customary greeting in a cell
sheet.createCell(0, 0, "Hello, world");

// Have some numerical data
sheet.createCell(1, 0, 6);
sheet.createCell(1, 1, 7);

// Perform a spreadsheet calculation
sheet.createCell(1, 2, ""); // Set a dummy value
sheet.getCell(1, 2).setCellFormula("A2*B2");

// Resize a column to fit the cell data
sheet.autofitColumn(0);

layout.addComponent(sheet);
layout.setSizeFull(); // Typically]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The result is shown in <xref linkend="figure.spreadsheet.overview.example"/>.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.spreadsheet.overview.example">
            <title>Simple Spreadsheet</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="100%" scale="35" align="center" fileref="img/spreadsheet/spreadsheet-basic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Cell values and formulas can be set, read, and styled through the server-side
            API, so you can easily implement custom editing features through menus or
            toolbars.
        </para>

        <para>
            Full integration with a Vaadin application is reached through the server-side
            access to the spreadsheet data as well as visual styling. Changes in cell
            values can be handled in the Vaadin application and you can use almost any
            Vaadin components within a spreadsheet. Field components can be bound to cell
            data.
        </para>

        <para>
            Vaadin Spreadsheet uses Apache POI to work on Microsoft Excel documents. You
            can access the Apache POI data model to perform low-level tasks, although you
            should note that if you make modifications to the data model, you have the
            responsibility to notify the spreadsheet to update itself.
        </para>

        <simplesect xml:id="spreadsheet.overview.features">
            <title>Features</title>

            <para>
                The basic features of Vaadin Spreadsheet are as follows:
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Support for touch devices</listitem>

                <listitem>Excel XLSX files, limited support for XLS files</listitem>

                <listitem>Support for Excel formulas</listitem>

                <listitem>Excel-like editing with keyboard support</listitem>

                <listitem>Lazy loading of cell data from server to browser in large spreadsheets</listitem>

                <listitem>Protected cells and sheets</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                The following features support integration with Vaadin Framework and
                add-ons:
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Handle changes in cell data</listitem>

                <listitem>Vaadin components in spreadsheet cells</listitem>

                <listitem>Support for Vaadin declarative format</listitem>

                <listitem>Vaadin TestBench element API for UI testing</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="spreadsheet.overview.demo">
            <title>Spreadsheet Demo</title>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Spreadsheet Demo showcases the most important Spreadsheet
                features. You can try it out at <link
                xlink:href="http://demo.vaadin.com/spreadsheet">http://demo.vaadin.com/spreadsheet</link>. See
                <xref linkend="spreadsheet.installation.demo"/> for instructions for
                importing the project in Eclipse.

                <phrase condition="web">The <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/vaadin/spreadsheet-demo">source code is
                available and browseable at Github</link>.</phrase>
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="spreadsheet.overview.limitations">
            <title>Requirements</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Vaadin 7.4 or later</listitem>

                <listitem>Same browser requirements as Vaadin Framework, except Internet
                Explorer 9 or later is required</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="spreadsheet.overview.limitations">
            <title>Limitations</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin Spreadsheet 1.0 has the following limitations:
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    Vaadin Charts component can not be used inside Spreadsheet
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    No provided toolbars or menus for formatting cells
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    Limited support for the older XSL format
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <link xlink:href="http://poi.apache.org/spreadsheet/limitations.html">Limitations of Apache POI</link>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="spreadsheet.overview.license">
            <title>Licensing</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin Spreadsheet is a commercial product licensed under the CVAL license
                (<link xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/license/cval-3">Commercial Vaadin
                Add-On License</link>). Development licenses need to be purchased for each
                developer working with Vaadin Spreadsheet, regardless of whether the
                resulting applications using it are deployed publicly or privately in an
                intranet.
            </para>

            <para>
                A <link xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/pro/">Vaadin Pro Tools</link>
                subscription includes a subscription license for Vaadin
                Spreadsheet. Perpetual licenses can be purchased from the <link
                xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/spreadsheet">Vaadin Spreadsheet product
                page</link>, where you can also find the licensing details. For evaluation
                purposes, a free trial key allows using Vaadin Spreadsheet for a 30-day
                evaluation period.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation" condition="web">
        <title>Installing Vaadin Spreadsheet</title>

        <para>
            You can download and install Spreadsheet from Vaadin Directory at <link
            xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/addon/vaadin-spreadsheet">vaadin.com/addon/vaadin-spreadsheet</link>
            as an installation package, or get it with Maven or Ivy. You can purchase the
            required CVAL license or get a free trial key from Vaadin Directory or
            subscribe to the Pro Tools at <link
            xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/pro">vaadin.com/pro</link>.
        </para>

        <para>
            Add-on installation is described in detail in <xref linkend="addons"/>. The
            add-on includes both a widget set and a theme, so you need to compile the
            widget sets and themes in your project.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation.ivy" condition="web">
            <title>Installing as Ivy Dependency</title>

            <para>
                If you use the add-on in an Eclipse project created with the Vaadin Plugin
                for Eclipse, you can define an Ivy dependency to automatically download
                the library. Include the following declaration inside the
                <literal>dependencies</literal> section in the
                <filename>ivy.xml</filename>:
            </para>

            <programlisting>&lt;dependency org="com.vaadin.addon"
            name="vaadin-spreadsheet"
            rev="<emphasis role="bold">latest.release</emphasis>"
            conf="default->default" /&gt;</programlisting>

            <para>
                You can use <literal>latest.release</literal> revision tag to always use
                the latest release or (preferably) specify a version by its version
                number. IvyDE should resolve the dependency immediately as you save the
                file. See <xref linkend="addons.eclipse"/> for further details.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation.maven" condition="web">
            <title>Defining the Maven Dependency</title>

            <para>
                You can install Vaadin Spreadsheet in a Maven project by adding it as a
                dependency, you need to include the following dependency in the POM. The
                <literal>artifactId</literal> should be
                <literal>vaadin-spreadsheet</literal>.
            </para>

            <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;com.vaadin.addon&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;vaadin-spreadsheet&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;<emphasis role="bold">LATEST</emphasis>&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>

            <para>
                You can use the <parameter>LATEST</parameter> version as shown above or
                (preferably) a specific version by its version number.
            </para>

            <para>
                You also need to define the repository for the Vaadin add-ons under the
                <literal>&lt;repositories&gt;</literal> element:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[<repository>
    <id>vaadin-addons</id>
    <url>http://maven.vaadin.com/vaadin-addons</url>
</repository>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Finally, you need to enable the widget set compilation in the POM, as
                described in <xref linkend="addons.maven.widgetset"/>, and compile it.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation.downloading" condition="web">
            <title>Installing the Zip Package</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin Spreadsheet is distributed as a Zip package that contains the
                Spreadsheet JAR, a JavaDoc JAR, license texts, and other documentation.
                You can download the Zip package from Vaadin Directory.
            </para>

            <para>
                The <filename>vaadin-spreadsheet-&lt;version&gt;.jar</filename>,
                as well as all the dependency libraries in the <filename>lib</filename>
                folder, should be put in the <filename>WEB-INF/lib</filename> folder of
                the web application.
            </para>

            <para>
                The <filename>vaadin-spreadsheet-&lt;version&gt;-sources.jar</filename>
                and <filename>vaadin-spreadsheet-&lt;version&gt;-javadoc.jar</filename>
                are development libraries that should not normally be deployed with the web
                application, so you should put them to a separate non-deployment
                folder. In Eclipse projects, this is usually a <filename>lib</filename>
                sub-folder in the project folder.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you intend to use Vaadin TestBench for testing your Spreadsheet, you
                will benefit from the Vaadin Spreadsheet TestBench API libraries included
                in the <filename>testbench-api</filename> folder. They should be copied to
                a non-deployment library folder in the project.
            </para>

            <para>
                Please see the <filename>README.html</filename> for more information about
                the package contents.
            </para>
        </section>

        <!-- Copied from Charts chapter -->
        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installing.license">
            <title>Installing License Key</title>
        
            <para>
                You need to install a license key before compiling the widget set. The
                license key is checked during widget set compilation, so you do not need
                it when deploying the application.
            </para>

            <para>
                You can purchase Vaadin Spreadsheet or obtain a free trial key from the <link
                xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/directory#addon/vaadin-spreadsheet">Vaadin
                Spreadsheet download page</link> in Vaadin Directory. You need to register in
                Vaadin Directory to obtain the key.
            </para>

            <para>
                See <xref linkend="addons.cval"/> for detailed instructions on
                obtaining and installing the license key.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation.widgetset">
            <title>Compiling Widget Set</title>

            <para>
                Compile the widget set as instructed in <xref
                linkend="addons.maven.compiling"/>. Widget set compilation should
                automatically update your project widget set to include the Spreadsheet
                widget set:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[<inherits name="com.vaadin.addon.spreadsheet.Widgetset"/>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                If you have set the widget set to be manually edited, you need to add the
                element yourself.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation.theme">
            <title>Compiling Theme</title>

            <para>
                Compile the theme as instructed in <xref linkend="themes.compiling"/>. If
                you compile in Eclipse or with Maven, the <filename>addons.scss</filename>
                file in your theme should be automatically updated to include the
                Spreadsheet theme:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[@import "../../../VAADIN/addons/spreadsheet/spreadsheet.scss";
@mixin addons {
	 @include spreadsheet;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                If you are compiling the theme otherwise, or the theme addons are not
                automatically updated for some reason, you need to add the statements
                yourself.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.installation.demo">
            <title>Importing the Demo</title>

            <para>
                The Demo, illustrated in <xref
                linkend="figure.spreadsheet.overview.demo"/> in the overview, showcases
                most of the functionality in Vaadin Spreadsheet. You can try out the demo
                online at <link
                xlink:href="http://demo.vaadin.com/spreadsheet">demo.vaadin.com/spreadsheet</link>.
            </para>

            <para>
                You can browse the sources on-line or, more conveniently, import the
                project in Eclipse (or other IDE). As the project is Maven-based, Eclipse
                users need to install the m2e plugin to be able to import Maven projects,
                as well as EGit to be able to import Git repositories. Once they are
                installed, you should be able to import demo as follows.
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem></menuchoice></listitem>
                <listitem>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Maven</guimenu><guimenuitem>Check out Maven Project from SCM</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</listitem>
                
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        You may need to install the EGit SCM connector if you have not
                        done so previously. If Git is not available in the SCM list, click
                        <guibutton>m2e marketplace</guibutton>, select the EGit connector,
                        and click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>. You need to restart
                        Eclipse and redo the earlier steps above.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        Instead of using m2e EGit connector, you can also check out the
                        project with another Git tool and then import it in Eclipse as a
                        Maven project.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    In <guilabel>SCM URL</guilabel>, select <guilabel>git</guilabel> and enter
                    the repository URL <uri>https://github.com/vaadin/spreadsheet-demo</uri>.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>Click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>.</listitem>

                <listitem>
                    Compile the widget set either by clicking <guibutton>Compile
                    Widgetset</guibutton> in the Eclipse toolbar or by running the
                    <literal>vaadin:compile</literal> goal with Maven.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    Deploy the application to a server. See <xref
                    linkend="getting-started.first-project.server"/> for instructions for
                    deploying in Eclipse.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    Open the URL <uri>http://localhost:8080/spreadsheet</uri> with a
                    browser.
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="spreadsheet.using">
        <title>Basic Use</title>

        <para>
            <classname>Spreadsheet</classname> is a Vaadin component, which you can use as
            you would any component. You can create it, or load from an Excel file, create
            cells and new sheets, define formulas, and so forth. In the following, we go
            through these basic steps.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.using.creating">
            <title>Creating a Spreadsheet</title>

            <para>
                The default constructor for <classname>Spreadsheet</classname> creates an
                empty spreadsheet with a default sheet. The spreadsheet component has full
                size by default, so the containing layout must have defined size in both
                dimensions; a spreadsheet may not have undefined size.
            </para>

            <para>
                In the following example, we create an empty spreadsheet with a fixed
                size and add it to a layout.
            </para>

            <programlisting lang="java"><![CDATA[Spreadsheet sheet = new Spreadsheet();
sheet.setWidth("400px");
sheet.setHeight("300px");

layout.addComponent(sheet);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                An empty spreadsheet automatically gets an initial worksheet with some
                default size and settings.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="spreadsheet.using.creating.loading">
                <title>Loading an Excel Spreadsheet</title>

                <para>
                    You can load an Excel file from the local filesystem with a
                    <classname>File</classname> reference or from memory or other source
                    with an <classname>InputStream</classname>.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="spreadsheet.using.creating.poi">
                <title>Working with an Apache POI Workbook</title>

                <para>
                    If you have an Apache POI workbook created otherwise, you can wrap it
                    to <classname>Spreadsheet</classname> with the respective constructor.
                </para>

                <para>
                    You can access the underlying workbook with
                    <methodname>getWorkbook()</methodname>. However, if you make
                    modifications to the workbook, you must allow the spreadsheet update
                    itself by calling appropriate update methods for the modified element
                    or elements.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="spreadsheet.using.sheets">
            <title>Working with Sheets</title>

            <para>
                A "spreadsheet" in reality works on a <emphasis>workbook</emphasis>, which
                contains one or more <emphasis>worksheets</emphasis>. You can create new
                sheets and delete existing ones with
                <methodname>createNewSheet()</methodname> and
                <methodname>deleteSheet()</methodname>, respectively.
            </para>

            <programlisting lang="java"><![CDATA[// Recreate the initial sheet to configure it
Spreadsheet sheet = new Spreadsheet();
sheet.createNewSheet("New Sheet", 10, 5);
sheet.deleteSheet(0);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                When a sheet is deleted, the index of the sheets with a higher index is
                decremented by one.  When the active worksheet is deleted, the next one by
                index is set as active, or if there are none, the previous one.
            </para>

            <para>
                All operations on the spreadsheet content are done through the currently
                active worksheet. You can set an existing sheet as active with
                <methodname>setActiveSheetIndex()</methodname>.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="spreadsheet.components">
        <title>Components in Cells</title>

        <para>
            You can have Vaadin components in spreadsheet cells and bind field components
            to the cell data. The components can be shown all the time or work as editors
            that appear when a cell is activated for editing.
        </para>

        <para>
            Components in a spreadsheet must be generated by a
            <interfacename>SpreadsheetComponentFactory</interfacename>, which you need to
            implement.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="spreadsheet.table">
        <title>Tables Within Spreadsheets</title>

        <para>
            A worksheet may contain a number of <emphasis>tables</emphasis>, which provide
            features such as headers and filtering for a region in a spreadsheet. Such a
            table is a defined region of cells, managed through a
            <classname>SpreadsheetTable</classname> or
            <classname>SpreadsheetFilterTable</classname> added to the spreadsheet.
        </para>
    </section>

    <indexterm startref="term.spreadsheet" class="endofrange"/>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
