<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="gwt">
	<title>Integrating with the Server-Side</title>

    <indexterm xml:id="term.gwt" class="startofrange" significance="preferred">
        <primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary>
        <secondary>widgets</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>widgets</primary></indexterm>

	<para>
		This chapter describes how you can integrate client-side widgets or JavaScript
		components with a server-side component. The client-side implementations of all
		standard server-side components in Vaadin use the same client-side interfaces and
		patterns.
	</para>

    <section xml:id="gwt.overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            Vaadin components consist of two parts: a server-side and a client-side
            component. The latter are also called <emphasis>widgets</emphasis> in Google
            Web Toolkit (GWT) parlance. A Vaadin application uses the API of the
            server-side component, which is rendered as a client-side widget in the
            browser. As on the server-side, the client-side widgets form a hierarchy of
            layout widgets and regular widgets as the leaves.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.gwt.overview.widget-integration">
            <title>Integration of Client-Side Widgets</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/gwt/widget-integration-lo.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="80%" align="center" fileref="img/gwt/widget-integration-hi.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            The communication between a client-side widget and a server-side component is
            managed with a <emphasis>connector</emphasis> that handles syncronizing the
            widget state and events to and from the server-side.

            <indexterm><primary>connector</primary></indexterm>
        </para>

        <para>
            When rendering the user interface, a client-side connector and a widget are
            created for each server-side component. The mapping from a component to a
            connector is defined in the connector class with a <literal>@Connect</literal>
            annotation, and the widget is created by the connector class.

            <indexterm><primary>@Connect</primary></indexterm>
        </para>

        <para>
            The state of a server-side component is synchronized automatically to the
            client-side widget using a <emphasis>shared state</emphasis>
            object. A shared state object implements the
            <interfacename>ComponentState</interfacename> interface and it is used both in
            the server-side and the client-side component. On the client-side, a connector
            always has access to its state instance, as well to the state of its parent
            component state and the states of its children.

            <indexterm><primary>state object</primary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary><classname>ComponentState</classname></primary></indexterm>
        </para>

        <para>
            The state sharing assumes that state is defined with standard Java types, such
            as primitive and boxed primitive types, <classname>String</classname>, arrays,
            and certain collections (<classname>List</classname>,
            <classname>Set</classname>, and <classname>Map</classname>) of the supported
            types. Also the Vaadin <classname>Connector</classname> and some special
            internal types can be shared.
        </para>

        <para>
            In addition to state, both server- and client-side can make remote procedure
            calls (RPC) to the other side. RPC is used foremost for event
            notifications. For example, when a client-side connector of a button receives
            a click, it sends the event to the server-side using RPC.
        </para>

        <simplesect xml:id="gwt.overview.project">
            <title>Project Structure</title>

            <para>
                Widget set compilation, as described in <xref
                linkend="clientside.module"/>, requires using a special project structure,
                where the client-side classes are located under a
                <filename>client</filename> package under the package of the module
                descriptor. Any static resources, such as stylesheets and images, should
                be located under a <filename>public</filename> folder (not Java
                package). The source for the server-side component may be located
                anywhere, except not in the client-side package.
            </para>

            <para>
                The basic project structure is illustrated in <xref linkend="figure.gwt.overview.project"/>.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.gwt.overview.project">
                <title>Basic Widget Integration Project Structure</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/gwt/gwt-widget-files-lo.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/gwt/gwt-widget-files-hi.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                The Eclipse wizard, described in <xref linkend="gwt.eclipse"/>, creates a
                widget integration skeleton with the above structure.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="gwt.overview.javascript">
            <title>Integrating JavaScript Components</title>

            <para>
                In addition to the GWT widget integration, Vaadin offers a simplified way
                to integrate pure JavaScript components. The JavaScript connector code is
                published from the server-side. As the JavaScript integration does not
                involve GWT programming, no widget set compilation is needed.

                <indexterm><primary>JavaScript</primary></indexterm>
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.eclipse">
        <title>Starting It Simple With Eclipse</title>

        <indexterm xml:id="term.gwt.eclipse" class="startofrange">
            <primary>Eclipse</primary>
            <secondary>widget development</secondary>
        </indexterm>

		<para>
            Let us first take the easy way and create a simple component with Eclipse.
            While you can develop new widgets with any IDE or even without, you may find
            Eclipse and the Vaadin Plugin for it useful, as it automates all the basic
            routines of widget development, most importantly the creation of new widgets.
		</para>

		<section xml:id="gwt.eclipse.widget">
			<title>Creating a Widget</title>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Right-click the project in the Project Explorer and select
                        <menuchoice><guimenu>New</guimenu><guimenuitem>Other...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In the wizard selection, select
                        <menuchoice><guimenu>Vaadin</guimenu><guimenuitem>Vaadin
                        Widget</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and click
                        <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.
                    </para>

                    <screenshot condition="web">
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject role="html">
                                <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widget-new-select.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                            <imageobject role="fo">
                                <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widget-new-select.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </screenshot>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In the <guilabel>New Component Wizard</guilabel>, make the following
                        settings.
                    </para>

                    <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widget-new-settings.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </screenshot>
                    
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><guilabel>Source folder</guilabel></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    The root folder of the entire source tree. The default
                                    value is the default source tree of your project, and
                                    you should normally leave it unchanged unless you have
                                    a different project structure.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><guilabel>Package</guilabel></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    The parent package under which the new server-side
                                    component should be created. If the project does not
                                    already have a widget set, one is created under this
                                    package in the <package>widgetset</package>
                                    subpackage. The subpackage will contain the
                                    <filename>.gwt.xml</filename> descriptor that defines
                                    the widget set and the new widget stub under the
                                    <package>widgetset.client</package> subpackage.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term><guilabel>Name</guilabel></term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									The class name of the new <emphasis>server-side
									component</emphasis>. The name of the client-side
									widget stub will be the same but with
									"-<classname>Widget</classname>" suffix, for example,
									<classname>MyComponentWidget</classname>. You can
									rename the classes afterwards.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term><guilabel>Superclass</guilabel></term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									The superclass of the server-side component. It is
									<classname>AbstractComponent</classname> by default,
									but <classname>com.vaadin.ui.AbstractField</classname>
									or <classname>com.vaadin.ui.AbstractSelect</classname>
									are other commonly used superclasses. If you are
									extending an existing component, you should select it
									as the superclass. You can easily change the
									superclass later.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term><guilabel>Template</guilabel></term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Select which template to use. The default is
									<guilabel>Full fledged</guilabel>, which creates the
									server-side component, the client-side widget, the
									connector, a shared state object, and an RPC
									object. The <guilabel>Connector only</guilabel> leaves
									the shared state and RPC objects out.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>

					<para>
						Finally, click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> to create the new component.
					</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

			<para>
				The wizard will:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
                    <para>Create a server-side component stub in the base package</para>
                </listitem>

				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        If the project does not already have a widget set, the wizard
                        creates a GWT module descriptor file
                        (<filename>.gwt.xml</filename>) in the base package and modifies
                        the servlet class or the <filename>web.xml</filename> deployment
                        descriptor to specify the widget set class name parameter for the
                        application
                    </para>
                </listitem>

				<listitem>
                    <para>Create a client-side widget stub (along with the connector and
                    shared state and RPC stubs) in the
                    <filename>client.componentname</filename> package under the base
                    package</para>
                </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				The structure of the server-side component and the client-side widget, and
				the serialization of component state between them, is explained in the
				subsequent sections of this chapter.
			</para>

			<para>
				To compile the widget set, click the <guibutton>Compile widget
				set</guibutton> button in the Eclipse toolbar. See <xref
				linkend="gwt.eclipse.compiling"/> for details. After the compilation
				finishes, you should be able to run your application as before, but using
				the new widget set. The compilation result is written under the
				<filename>WebContent/VAADIN/widgetsets</filename> folder. When you need to
				recompile the widget set in Eclipse, see <xref
				linkend="gwt.eclipse.compiling"/>. For detailed information on compiling
				widget sets, see <xref linkend="clientside.compiling"/>.
			</para>

			<para>
				The following setting is inserted in the <filename>web.xml</filename>
				deployment descriptor to enable the widget set:
			</para>

			<programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?>&lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;Application widgetset&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;widgetset&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;<emphasis mode="bold">com.example.myproject.widgetset.MyprojectApplicationWidgetset</emphasis>&lt;/param-value&gt;
&lt;/init-param&gt;</programlisting>

			<para>
				You can refactor the package structure if you find need for it, but GWT
				compiler requires that the client-side code <emphasis>must</emphasis>
				always be stored under a package named "<filename>client</filename>" or a
				package defined with a <literal>source</literal> element in the widget set
				descriptor.
			</para>
        </section>

		<section xml:id="gwt.eclipse.compiling">
			<title>Compiling the Widget Set</title>

			<para>
				After you edit a widget, you need to compile the widget set. The Vaadin
				Plugin for Eclipse automatically suggests to compile the widget set in
				various situations, such as when you save a client-side source file. If
				this gets annoying, you can disable the automatic recompilation in the
				Vaadin category in project settings, by selecting the <guilabel>Suspend
				automatic widgetset builds</guilabel> option.
            </para>

            <para>
                You can compile the widget set manually by clicking the <guibutton>Compile
                widgetset</guibutton> button in the Eclipse toolbar, shown in <xref
                linkend="figure.gwt.eclipse.compiling.toolbar"/>, while the project is
                open and selected. If the project has multiple widget set definition
                files, you need to select the one to compile in the Project Explorer.
			</para>

            <!-- TODO: Better icon as requested in #3692. -->
            <figure xml:id="figure.gwt.eclipse.compiling.toolbar">
				<title>The <guibutton>Compile Widgetset</guibutton> Button in Eclipse Toolbar</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widgetset-compiling-toolbar-lo.png"/>
					</imageobject>
					<imageobject role="fo">
						<imagedata scale="100" smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widgetset-compiling-toolbar-hi.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

            <para>
                The compilation progress is shown in the <guilabel>Console</guilabel>
                panel in Eclipse, illustrated in <xref
                linkend="figure.gwt.eclipse.compiling"/>. You should note especially the
                list of widget sets found in the class path.
            </para>

			<figure xml:id="figure.gwt.eclipse.compiling" float="center" floatstyle="before">
				<title>Compiling a Widget Set</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widgetset-compiling.png"/>
					</imageobject>
					<imageobject role="fo">
						<imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/eclipse/widgetset-compiling.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
            
			<para>
				The compilation output is written under the
				<filename>WebContent/VAADIN/widgetsets</filename> folder, in a widget set
				specific folder.
			</para>

            <para>
                You can speed up the compilation significantly by compiling the widget set
                only for your browser during development. The generated
                <filename>.gwt.xml</filename> descriptor stub includes a disabled element
                that specifies the target browser. See <xref
                linkend="gwt.module.compilation-limiting"/> for more details on setting
                the <literal>user-agent</literal> property.
            </para>

			<para>
				For more information on compiling widget sets, see <xref
				linkend="clientside.compiling"/>. Should you compile a widget set
				outside Eclipse, you need to refresh the project by selecting it in
				<guilabel>Project Explorer</guilabel> and pressing <keycap>F5</keycap>.
			</para>
        </section>

        <indexterm startref="term.gwt.eclipse" class="endofrange"/>
    </section>


    <section xml:id="gwt.server-side">
        <title>Creating a Server-Side Component</title>

        <para>
            Typical server-side Vaadin applications use server-side components
            that are rendered on the client-side using their counterpart widgets. A
            server-side component must manage state synchronization between the widget on
            the client-side, in addition to any server-side logic.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.server-side.basic">
            <title>Basic Server-Side Component</title>

            <para>
                The component state is usually managed by a <emphasis>shared
                state</emphasis>, described later in <xref linkend="gwt.shared-state"/>.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponent extends AbstractComponent {
    public MyComponent() {
        getState().setText("This is MyComponent");
    }

    @Override
    protected MyComponentState getState() {
        return (MyComponentState) super.getState();
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <!-- Note: The getState() should be protected to avoid leaking implementation
            details. -->

        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.connector">
        <title>Integrating the Two Sides with a Connector</title>

        <para>
            A client-side widget is integrated with a server-side component with a
            <emphasis>connector</emphasis>. A connector is a client-side class that
            communicates changes to the widget state and events to the server-side.
        </para>

        <para>
            A connector normally gets the state of the server-side component by the
            <emphasis>shared state</emphasis>, described later in <xref
            linkend="gwt.shared-state"/>.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.connector.basic">
            <title>A Basic Connector</title>

            <para>
                The basic tasks of a connector is to hook up to the widget and handle
                events from user interaction and changes received from the server. A
                connector also has a number of routine infrastructure methods which need
                to be implemented.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[@Connect(MyComponent.class)
public class MyComponentConnector
        extends AbstractComponentConnector {

    @Override
    public MyComponentWidget getWidget() {
        return (MyComponentWidget) super.getWidget();
    }

    @Override
    public MyComponentState getState() {
        return (MyComponentState) super.getState();
    }

    @Override
    public void onStateChanged(StateChangeEvent stateChangeEvent)
    {
        super.onStateChanged(stateChangeEvent);
        
        // Do something useful
        final String text = getState().text;
        getWidget().setText(text);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Here, we handled state change with the crude
                <methodname>onStateChanged()</methodname> method that is called when any
                of the state properties is changed. A finer and simpler handling is
                achieved by using the <classname>@OnStateChange</classname> annotation on
                a handler method for each property, or by
                <classname>@DelegateToWidget</classname> on a shared state property, as
                described later in <xref linkend="gwt.shared-state"/>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.connector.communication">
            <title>Communication with the Server-Side</title>
            
            <para>
                The main task of a connector is to communicate user interaction with the
                widget to the server-side and receive state changes from the server-side
                and relay them to the widget.
            </para>

            <para>
                Server-to-client communication is normally done using a <emphasis>shared
                state</emphasis>, as described in <xref linkend="gwt.shared-state"/>, as
                well as RPC calls. The serialization of the state data is handled
                completely transparently. <phrase condition="web">Once the client-side
                engine receives the changes from the server, it reacts to them by creating
                and notifying connectors that in turn manage widgets. This is described in
                <xref linkend="gwt.advanced.phases"/> in more detail.</phrase>
            </para>

            <para>
                For client-to-server communication, a connector can make remote procedure
                calls (RPC) to the server-side. Also, the server-side component can make
                RPC calls to the connector. For a thorough description of the RPC
                mechanism, refer to <xref linkend="gwt.rpc"/>.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state">
        <title>Shared State</title>

        <para>
            The basic communication from a server-side component to its the client-side
            widget counterpart is handled using a <emphasis>shared state</emphasis>. The
            shared state is serialized transparently. It should be considered read-only on
            the client-side, as it is not serialized back to the server-side.
        </para>

        <para>
            A shared state object simply needs to extend the
            <classname>ComponentState</classname>. The member variables should normally be
            declared as public.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponentState extends ComponentState {
    public String text;
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            A shared state should never contain any logic. If the members have private
            visibility for some reason, you can also use public setters and getters, in
            which case the property must not be public.
        </para>

        <simplesect xml:id="gwt.shared-state.location">
            <title>Location of Shared-State Classes</title>

            <para>
                The shared-state classes are used by both server- and client-side classes,
                but widget set compilation requires that they must be located in a
                client-side source package. The default location is under a
                <filename>client</filename> package under the package of the
                <filename>.gwt.xml</filename> descriptor. If you wish to organize the
                shared classes separately from other client-side code, you can define
                separate client-side source packages for pure client-side classes and any
                shared classes. In addition to shared state classes, shared classes could
                include enumerations and other classes needed by shared-state or RPC
                communication.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, you could have the following definitions in the
                <filename>.gwt.xml</filename> descriptor:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[    <source path="client" />
    <source path="shared" />]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The paths are relative to the package containing the descriptor.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state.component">
            <title>Accessing Shared State on Server-Side</title>

            <para>
                A server-side component can access the shared state with the
                <methodname>getState()</methodname> method. It is required that you
                override the base implementation with one that returns the shared state
                object cast to the proper type, as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[@Override
public MyComponentState getState() {
    return (MyComponentState) super.getState();
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                You can then use the <methodname>getState()</methodname> to access the
                shared state object with the proper type.
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[public MyComponent() {
    getState().setText("This is the initial state");
    ....
}]]></programlisting>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state.connector">
            <title>Handing Shared State in a Connector</title>

            <para>
                A connector can access a shared state with the
                <methodname>getState()</methodname> method. The access should be
                read-only. It is required that you override the base implementation with
                one that returns the proper shared state type, as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[@Override
public MyComponentState getState() {
    return (MyComponentState) super.getState();
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                State changes made on the server-side are communicated transparently to
                the client-side. When a state change occurs, the
                <methodname>onStateChanged()</methodname> method in the connector is
                called. You should should always call the superclass method before
                anything else to handle changes to common component properties.
            </para>
                
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[@Override
public void onStateChanged(StateChangeEvent stateChangeEvent) {
    super.onStateChanged(stateChangeEvent);
		
    // Copy the state properties to the widget properties
    final String text = getState().getText();
    getWidget().setText(text);
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The crude <methodname>onStateChanged()</methodname> method is called when
                any of the state properties is changed, allowing you to have even complex
                logic in how you manipulate the widget according to the state changes. In
                most cases, however, you can handle the property changes more easily and
                also more efficiently by using instead the
                <classname>@OnStateChange</classname> annotation on the handler methods
                for each property, as described next in <xref
                linkend="gwt.shared-state.onstatechange"/>, or by delegating the property
                value directly to the widget, as described in <xref
                linkend="gwt.shared-state.delegatetowidget"/>.
            </para>

            <para condition="web">
                The processing phases of state changes are described in more detail in
                <xref linkend="gwt.advanced.phases"/>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state.onstatechange">
            <title>Handling Property State Changes with <classname>@OnStateChange</classname></title>

            <para>
                The <classname>@OnStateChange</classname> annotation can be used to mark a
                connector method that handles state change on a particular property, given
                as parameter for the annotation. In addition to higher clarity, this
                avoids handling all property changes if a state change occurs in only one
                or some of them. However, if a state change can occur in multiple
                properties, you can only use this technique if the properties do not have
                interaction that prevents handling them separately in arbitrary order.
            </para>

            <para>
                We can replace the <methodname>onStateChange()</methodname> method in the
                earlier connector example with the following:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[@OnStateChange("text")
void updateText() {
    getWidget().setText(getState().text);
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                If the shared state property and the widget property have same name and do
                not require any type conversion, as is the case in the above example, you
                could simplify this even further by using the
                <classname>@DelegateToWidget</classname> annotation for the shared state
                property, as described in <xref
                linkend="gwt.shared-state.delegatetowidget"/>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state.delegatetowidget">
            <title>Delegating State Properties to Widget</title>

            <para>
                The <classname>@DelegateToWidget</classname> annotation for a shared state
                property defines automatic delegation of the property value to the
                corresponding widget property of the same name and type, by calling the
                respective setter for the property in the widget.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponentState extends AbstractComponentState {
    @DelegateToWidget
    public String text;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                This is equivalent to handling the state change in the connector, as done
                in the example in <xref linkend="gwt.shared-state.onstatechange"/>.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you want to delegate a shared state property to a widget property of
                another name, you can give the property name as a string parameter for the
                annotation.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponentState extends AbstractComponentState {
    @DelegateToWidget("description")
    public String text;
}]]></programlisting>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state.referring">
            <title>Referring to Components in Shared State</title>

            <para>
                While you can pass any regular Java objects through a shared state,
                referring to another component requires special handling because on the
                server-side you can only refer to a server-side component, while on the
                client-side you only have widgets. References to components can be made by
                referring to their connectors (all server-side components implement the
                <interfacename>Connector</interfacename> interface).
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponentState extends ComponentState {
    public Connector otherComponent;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                You could then access the component on the server-side as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponent {
    public void MyComponent(Component otherComponent) {
        getState().otherComponent = otherComponent;
    }

    public Component getOtherComponent() {
        return (Component)getState().otherComponent;
    }

    // And the cast method
    @Override
    public MyComponentState getState() {
        return (MyComponentState) super.getState();
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                On the client-side, you should cast it in a similar fashion to a
                <classname>ComponentConnector</classname>, or possibly to the specific
                connector type if it is known.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.shared-state.resource">
            <title>Sharing Resources</title>

            <para>
                Resources, which commonly are references to icons or other images, are
                another case of objects that require special handling. A
                <interfacename>Resource</interfacename> object exists only on the
                server-side and on the client-side you have an URL to the resource. You
                need to use the <methodname>setResource()</methodname> and
                <methodname>getResource()</methodname> on the server-side to access a
                resource, which is serialized to the client-side separately.
            </para>

            <para>
                Let us begin with the server-side API:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[public class MyComponent extends AbstractComponent {
    ...

    public void setMyIcon(Resource myIcon) {
        setResource("myIcon", myIcon);
    }

    public Resource getMyIcon() {
        return getResource("myIcon");
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                On the client-side, you can then get the URL of the resource with
                <methodname>getResourceUrl()</methodname>.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[@Override
public void onStateChanged(StateChangeEvent stateChangeEvent) {
    super.onStateChanged(stateChangeEvent);
    ...
	
    // Get the resource URL for the icon
    getWidget().setMyIcon(getResourceUrl("myIcon"));
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The widget could then use the URL, for example, as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public class MyWidget extends Label {
    ...
    
    Element imgElement = null;
    
    public void setMyIcon(String url) {
        if (imgElement == null) {
            imgElement = DOM.createImg();
            getElement().appendChild(imgElement);
        }
        
        DOM.setElementAttribute(imgElement, "src", url);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.rpc">
        <title>RPC Calls Between Client- and Server-Side</title>

        <para>
            Vaadin supports making Remote Procedure Calls (RPC) between a server-side
            component and its client-side widget counterpart. RPC calls are normally used
            for communicating stateless events, such as button clicks or other user
            interaction, in contrast to changing the shared state. Either party can make
            an RPC call to the other side. When a client-side widget makes a call, a
            server request is made. Calls made from the server-side to the client-side are
            communicated in the response of the server request during which the call was
            made.
        </para>

        <para>
            If you use Eclipse and enable the "Full-Fledged" widget in the New Vaadin
            Widget wizard, it automatically creates a component with an RPC stub.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.rpc.server-side">
            <title>RPC Calls to the Server-Side</title>

            <para>
                RPC calls from the client-side to the server-side are made through an RPC
                interface that extends the <interfacename>ServerRpc</interfacename>
                interface. A server RPC interface simply defines any methods that can be
                called through the interface.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public interface MyComponentServerRpc extends ServerRpc {
    public void clicked(String buttonName);
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The above example defines a single <methodname>clicks()</methodname> RPC
                call, which takes a <classname>MouseEventDetails</classname> object as the
                parameter.
            </para>

            <para>
                You can pass the most common standard Java types, such as primitive and
                boxed primitive types, <classname>String</classname>, and arrays and some
                collections (<classname>List</classname>, <classname>Set</classname>, and
                <classname>Map</classname>) of the supported types. Also the Vaadin
                <classname>Connector</classname> and some special internal types can be
                passed.
            </para>

            <para>
                An RPC method must return void - the widget set compiler should complain
                if it doesn't.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="gwt.rpc.server-side.calling">
                <title>Making a Call</title>

                <para>
                    Before making a call, you need to instantiate the server RPC object
                    with <methodname>RpcProxy.create()</methodname>. After that, you can
                    make calls through the server RPC interface that you defined, for
                    example as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[@Connect(MyComponent.class)
public class MyComponentConnector
       extends AbstractComponentConnector {

    public MyComponentConnector() {
        getWidget().addClickHandler(new ClickHandler() {
            public void onClick(ClickEvent event) {
                final MouseEventDetails mouseDetails =
                     MouseEventDetailsBuilder
                         .buildMouseEventDetails(
                                 event.getNativeEvent(),
                                 getWidget().getElement());
                MyComponentServerRpc rpc =
                    getRpcProxy(MyComponentServerRpc.class);

                // Make the call
                rpc.clicked(mouseDetails.getButtonName());
            }
        });
    }
}]]></programlisting>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="gwt.rpc.server-side.handling">
                <title>Handling a Call</title>

                <para>
                    RPC calls are handled in a server-side implementation of the server
                    RPC interface. The call and its parameters are serialized and passed
                    to the server in an RPC request transparently.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponent extends AbstractComponent {
    private MyComponentServerRpc rpc =
    new MyComponentServerRpc() {
        private int clickCount = 0;
        
        public void clicked(String buttonName) {
            Notification.show("Clicked " + buttonName);
        }
    };

    public MyComponent() {
        ...
        registerRpc(rpc);
    }
}]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.extension">
        <title>Component and &uiclass; Extensions</title>

        <para>
            Adding features to existing components by extending them by inheritance
            creates a problem when you want to combine such features. For example, one
            add-on could add spell-check to a <classname>TextField</classname>, while
            another could add client-side validation. Combining such add-on features would
            be difficult if not impossible. You might also want to add a feature to
            several or even to all components, but extending all of them by inheritance is
            not really an option. Vaadin includes a component plug-in mechanism for these
            purposes. Such plug-ins are simply called <emphasis>extensions</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <para>
            Also a &ui; can be extended in a similar fashion. In fact, some Vaadin
            features such as the JavaScript execution are UI extensions.
        </para>

        <para>
            Implementing an extension requires defining a server-side extension class and
            a client-side connector. An extension can have a shared state with the
            connector and use RPC, just like a component could.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.extension.server-side">
            <title>Server-Side Extension API</title>

            <para>
                The server-side API for an extension consists of class that extends (in
                the Java sense) the <classname>AbstractExtension</classname> class. It
                typically has an <emphasis>extend()</emphasis> method, a constructor, or a
                static helper method that takes the extended component or &ui; as a
                parameter and passes it to <emphasis>super.extend()</emphasis>.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, let us have a trivial example with an extension that takes no
                special parameters, and illustrates the three alternative APIs:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public class CapsLockWarning extends AbstractExtension {
    // You could pass it in the constructor
    public CapsLockWarning(PasswordField field) {
        super.extend(field);
    }

    // Or in an extend() method
    public void extend(PasswordField field) {
        super.extend(field);
    }

    // Or with a static helper
    public static addTo(PasswordField field) {
        new CapsLockWarning().extend(field);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The extension could then be added to a component as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[PasswordField password = new PasswordField("Give it");

// Use the constructor
new CapsLockWarning(password);

// ... or with the extend() method
new CapsLockWarning().extend(password);

// ... or with the static helper
CapsLockWarning.addTo(password);

layout.addComponent(password);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Adding a feature in such a "reverse" way is a bit unusual in the Vaadin
                API, but allows type safety for extensions, as the method can limit the
                target type to which the extension can be applied, and whether it is a
                regular component or a &ui;.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.extension.connector">
            <title>Extension Connectors</title>

            <para>
                An extension does not have a corresponding widget on the client-side, but
                only an extension connector that extends the
                <classname>AbstractExtensionConnector</classname> class. The server-side
                extension class is specified with a <literal>@Connect</literal>
                annotation, just like in component connectors.
            </para>

            <para>
                An extension connector needs to implement the
                <methodname>extend()</methodname> method, which allows hooking to the
                extended component. The normal extension mechanism is to modify the
                extended component as needed and add event handlers to it to handle user
                interaction. An extension connector can share a state with the server-side
                extension as well as make RPC calls, just like with components.
            </para>

            <para>
                In the following example, we implement a "Caps Lock warning" extension. It
                listens for changes in Caps Lock state and displays a floating warning
                element over the extended component if the Caps Lock is on.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[@Connect(CapsLockWarning.class)
public class CapsLockWarningConnector
        extends AbstractExtensionConnector {

    @Override
    protected void extend(ServerConnector target) {
        // Get the extended widget
        final Widget pw =
                ((ComponentConnector) target).getWidget();

        // Preparations for the added feature
        final VOverlay warning = new VOverlay();
        warning.setOwner(pw);
        warning.add(new HTML("Caps Lock is enabled!"));

        // Add an event handler
        pw.addDomHandler(new KeyPressHandler() {
            public void onKeyPress(KeyPressEvent event) {
                if (isEnabled() && isCapsLockOn(event)) {
                    warning.showRelativeTo(passwordWidget);
                } else {
                    warning.hide();
                }
            }
        }, KeyPressEvent.getType());
    }

    private boolean isCapsLockOn(KeyPressEvent e) {
        return e.isShiftKeyDown() ^
               Character.isUpperCase(e.getCharCode());
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The <methodname>extend()</methodname> method gets the connector of the
                extended component as the parameter, in the above example a
                <classname>PasswordFieldConnector</classname>. It can access the widget
                with the <methodname>getWidget()</methodname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                An extension connector needs to be included in a widget set. The class
                must therefore be defined under the <filename>client</filename> package of
                a widget set, just like with component connectors.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.styling">
        <title>Styling a Widget</title>

        <para>
            To make your widget look stylish, you need to style it. There are two basic
            ways to define CSS styles for a component: in the widget sources and in a
            theme. A default style should be defined in the widget sources, and different
            themes can then modify the style.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.styling.class">
            <title>Determining the CSS Class</title>

            <para>
                The CSS class of a widget element is normally defined in the widget class
                and set with <methodname>setStyleName()</methodname>. A widget should set
                the styles for its sub-elements as it desires.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, you could style a composite widget with an overall style and
                with separate styles for the sub-widgets as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class MyPickerWidget extends ComplexPanel {
    public static final String CLASSNAME = "mypicker";

    private final TextBox textBox = new TextBox();
    private final PushButton button = new PushButton("...");

    public MyPickerWidget() {
        setElement(Document.get().createDivElement());
        setStylePrimaryName(CLASSNAME);

        textBox.setStylePrimaryName(CLASSNAME + "-field");
        button.setStylePrimaryName(CLASSNAME + "-button");

        add(textBox, getElement());
        add(button, getElement());

        button.addClickHandler(new ClickHandler() {
            public void onClick(ClickEvent event) {
              Window.alert("Calendar picker not yet supported!");
            }
        });
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                In addition, all Vaadin components get the <literal>v-widget</literal>
                class. If it extends an existing Vaadin or GWT widget, it will inherit
                CSS classes from that as well.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.styling.default">
            <title>Default Stylesheet</title>

            <para>
                A client-side module, which is normally a widget set, can include
                stylesheets. They must be placed under the <filename>public</filename>
                folder under the folder of the widget set, a described in <xref
                linkend="clientside.module.stylesheet"/>.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, you could style the widget described above as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[.mypicker {
	white-space: nowrap;
}

.mypicker-button {
	display: inline-block;
	border: 1px solid black;
	padding: 3px;
	width: 15px;
	text-align: center;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Notice that some size settings may require more complex handling and
                calculating the sizes dynamically.
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <!--
        <section xml:id="gwt.styling.sizing">
            <title>Considerations Regarding Sizing</title>

            <para>
                Determining the size of a widget requires some consideration. When Vaadin
                widgets are rendered as HTML, they all get the
                <literal>v-connector</literal> CSS class, which sets the CSS 3 property
                <literal>box-sizing: border-box</literal>. This causes the browser to
                consider borders and paddings when it calculates the size of the
                component. For example, if a component has <literal>5px</literal> padding
                and <literal>100%</literal> width, and is placed inside a slot... WHAT??
            </para>
        </section>
        -->

        <!-- TODO
        <section xml:id="gwt.styling.size-calculation">
            <title>Calculating the Widget Size</title>

            <para>
                While using CSS is the preferred way to size and position your widgets, it
                is not always possible.
            </para>
        </section>
        -->
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.componentcontainer">
        <title>Component Containers</title>

        <para>
            Component containers, such as layout components, are a special group of
            components that require some consideration. In addition to handling state,
            they need to manage communicating the hierarchy of their contained components
            to the other side.
        </para>

        <para>
            The easiest way to implement a component container is extend the
            <classname>AbstractComponentContainer</classname>, which handles the
            synchronization of the container server-side components to the client-side.
        </para>

        <!-- TODO Vaadin 7: https://vaadin.com/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Creating%20a%20simple%20component%20container -->

        <!-- TODO Vaadin 7
        <section xml:id="gwt.layout">
            <title>Handling Layouts</title>

            <section xml:id="gwt.sizes">
                <title>Handling Sizes</title>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="gwt.layout.managed">
                <title>Managed Layouts</title>
                
                <para>
                    A <classname>ManagedLayout</classname> is the most versatile, and at the
                    same time the heaviest, way to lay out widgets.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        -->
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.advanced" condition="web">
        <title>Advanced Client-Side Topics</title>

        <para>
            In the following, we mention some topics that you may encounter when
            integrating widgets.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.advanced.phases">
            <title>Client-Side Processing Phases</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin's client-side engine reacts to changes from the server in a number
                of phases, the order of which can be relevant for a connector. The
                processing occurs in the <methodname>handleUIDLMessage()</methodname>
                method in <classname>ApplicationConnection</classname>, but the logic can
                be quite overwhelming, so we describe the phases in the following summary.
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Any dependencies defined by using
                        <classname>@JavaScript</classname> or
                        <classname>@StyleSheet</classname> on the server-side class are
                        loaded. Processing does not continue until the browser confirms
                        that they have been loaded.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        New connectors are instantiated and
                        <methodname>init()</methodname> is run for each
                        <interfacename>Connector</interfacename>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        State objects are updated, but no state change event is fired yet.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The connector hierarchy is updated, but no hierarchy change event
                        is fired yet. <methodname>setParent()</methodname> and
                        <methodname>setChildren()</methodname> are run in this phase.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Hierarchy change events are fired. This means that all state
                        objects and the entire hierarchy are already up to date when this
                        happens. The DOM hierarchy should in theory be up to date after
                        all hierarchy events have been handled, although there are some
                        built-in components that for various reasons do not always live up
                        to this promise.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Captions are updated, causing
                        <methodname>updateCaption()</methodname> to be invoked on layouts
                        as needed.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>@DelegateToWidget</classname> is handled for all
                        changed state objects using the annotation.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        State change events are fired for all changed state objects.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <methodname>updateFromUIDL()</methodname> is called for legacy
                        connectors.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        All RPC methods received from the server are invoked.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Connectors that are no longer included in the hierarchy are
                        unregistered. This calls <methodname>onUnregister()</methodname>
                        on the <interfacename>Connector</interfacename>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The layout phase starts, first checking the sizes and positions of
                        all elements, and then notifying any
                        <interfacename>ElementResizeListener</interfacename>s, as well as
                        calling the appropriate layout method for the connectors that
                        implement either <classname>SimpleManagedLayout</classname> or
                        <classname>DirectionalManagedLayout</classname> interface.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.addons">
        <title>Creating Add-ons</title>

        <indexterm xml:id="term.gwt.addons" class="startofrange" significance="preferred">
            <primary>add-ons</primary>
            <secondary>creating</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>
            Add-ons are the most convenient way to reuse Vaadin code, either commercially
            or free. Vaadin Directory serves as the store for the add-ons. You can
            distribute add-ons both as JAR libraries and Zip packages.
        </para>

        <para>
            Creating a typical add-on package involves the following tasks:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Compile server-side classes</listitem>
            <listitem>Compile JavaDoc (optional)</listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Build the JAR</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Include Vaadin add-on manifest</listitem>
                    <listitem>Include the compiled server-side classes</listitem>
                    <listitem>Include the compiled JavaDoc (optional)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Include sources of client-side classes for widget set compilation (optional)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Include any JavaScript dependency libraries (optional)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Exclude any test or demo code in the project</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            The exact contents depend on the add-on type. Component add-ons often include
            a widget set, but not always, such as JavaScript components or pure
            server-side components. You can also have data container and theme add-ons, as
            well as various tools.
        </para>

        <para>
            It is common to distribute the JavaDoc in a separate JAR, but you can also
            include it in the same JAR.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.addons.export">
            <title>Exporting Add-on in Eclipse</title>

            <para>
                If you use the Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse for your add-on project, you can
                simply export the add-on from Eclipse.
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the project and then
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
                    from the menu</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the export wizard that opens, select
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>Vaadin</guimenu><guimenuitem>Vaadin Add-on
                    Package</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and click <guibutton>Next</guibutton></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In the <guilabel>Select the resources to export</guilabel> panel,
                        select the content that should be included in the add-on
                        package. In general, you should include sources in
                        <filename>src</filename> folder (at least for the client-side
                        package), compiled server-side classes, themes in
                        <filename>WebContent/VAADIN/themes</filename>. These are all
                        included automatically. You probably want to leave out any demo or
                        example code.
                    </para>
                    
                    <figure xml:id="figure.gwt.addons.export" float="center" floatstyle="before">
                        <title>Exporting a Vaadin Add-on</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/gwt/addon-export.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>

                    <para>
                        If you are submitting the add-on to Vaadin Directory, the
                        <guilabel>Implementation title</guilabel> should be exactly the
                        name of the add-on in Directory. The name may contain spaces and
                        most other letters. Notice that <emphasis>it is not possible to
                        change the name later</emphasis>.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        The <guilabel>Implementation version</guilabel> is the version of
                        your add-on. Typically experimental or beta releases start from
                        0.1.0, and stable releases from 1.0.0.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        The <guilabel>Widgetsets</guilabel> field should list the widget
                        sets included in the add-on, separated by commas. The widget sets
                        should be listed by their class name, that is, without the
                        <filename>.gwt.xml</filename> extension.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        The <guilabel>JAR file</guilabel> is the file name of the exported
                        JAR file. It should normally include the version number of the
                        add-on. You should follow the Maven format for the name, such as
                        <filename>myaddon-1.0.0.jar</filename>.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        Finally, click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.addons.ant" condition="web">
            <title>Building Add-on with Ant</title>

            <para>
                Building an add-on with Ant is similar to building Vaadin
                applications. Vaadin libraries and other dependencies are retrieved and
                included in the classpath using Apache Ivy.
            </para>

            <para>
                In the following, we assume the same structure as in the Eclipse project
                example. Let us put the build script in the <filename>build</filename>
                folder under the project.  We begin the Ant script as follows:
            </para>

			<programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;

&lt;project xmlns:ivy="antlib:org.apache.ivy.ant"
         name="<emphasis role="bold">My Own add-on</emphasis>"
         basedir=".."
         default="package-jar"&gt;
</programlisting>

            <para>
                The namespace declaration is all you need to do to enable Ivy in Ant 1.6
                and later. For earlier Ant versions, please see the Ivy documentation.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="gwt.addons.ant.configuration">
                <title>Configuration and Initialization</title>

                <para>
                    In the example script, we organize most settings in a
                    <literal>configure</literal> target and then initialize the build in
                    <literal>init</literal> target.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><!-- Update these settings for your project structure -->
&lt;target name="configure"&gt;
    &lt;!-- Where project source files are located --&gt;
    &lt;property name="src-location" value="<emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis>" /&gt;
        
    &lt;!-- Name of the widget set. --&gt;
    &lt;property name="widgetset" value="<emphasis role="bold">com.example.myaddon.widgetset.MyAddonWidgetset</emphasis>"/&gt;

    &lt;!-- Addon version --&gt;
    &lt;property name="version" value="<emphasis role="bold">0.1.0</emphasis>"/&gt;
    
    &lt;!-- Compilation result directory --&gt;
    &lt;property name="result-dir" value="build/result"/&gt;
    
    &lt;!-- The target name of the built add-on JAR --&gt;
    &lt;property name="target-jar"
        value="${result-dir}/<emphasis role="bold">myaddon</emphasis>-${version}.jar"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;

<!-- Initialize build -->
&lt;target name="init" depends="configure"&gt;
    &lt;!-- Construct and check classpath --&gt;
    &lt;path id="compile.classpath"&gt;
        &lt;pathelement path="build/classes" /&gt;
        &lt;pathelement path="${src-location}" /&gt;
        &lt;fileset dir="${result-dir}/lib"&gt;
            &lt;include name="*.jar"/&gt;
        &lt;/fileset&gt;
    &lt;/path&gt;

    &lt;mkdir dir="${result-dir}"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>

                <para>
                    You will need to make some configuration also in the
                    <literal>package-jar</literal> target in addition to the
                    <literal>configure</literal> target.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="gwt.addons.ant.compiling">
                <title>Compiling the Server-Side</title>

                <para>
                    Compiling the add-on requires the Vaadin libraries and any
                    dependencies. We use Apache Ivy for resolving the dependencies and
                    retrieving the library JARs.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?>&lt;!-- Retrieve dependencies with Ivy --&gt;
&lt;target name="resolve" depends="init"&gt;
    &lt;ivy:retrieve
        pattern="${result-dir}/lib/[artifact].[ext]"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;</programlisting>

                <para>
                    The <literal>pattern</literal> attribute for the
                    <literal>&lt;retrieve&gt;</literal> task specifies where the
                    dependencies are stored, in the above case in the
                    <filename>build/result/lib</filename> directory.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Compiling the server-side classes is then straight-forward:
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[<!-- Compile server-side -->
<target name="compile-server-side"
        depends="init, resolve">
    <delete dir="${result-dir}/classes"/>
    <mkdir dir="${result-dir}/classes"/>

    <javac srcdir="${src-location}"
           destdir="${result-dir}/classes">
        <classpath>
            <path refid="compile.classpath"/>
        </classpath>
    </javac>
</target>]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="gwt.addons.ant.javadoc">
                <title>Compiling the JavaDoc</title>

                <para>
                    You may want to include API documentation for the add-on in the same
                    or in a different JAR file. You can do it as follows, using the
                    configuration we defined earlier. You may want to exclude the
                    client-side classes and any test and demo classes from the JavaDoc, as
                    is done in this example, if they are in the same source tree.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?>&lt;!-- Compile JavaDoc --&gt;
&lt;target name="compile-javadoc" depends="init"&gt;
    &lt;delete dir="${result-dir}/javadoc"/&gt;
    &lt;mkdir dir="${result-dir}/javadoc"/&gt;

    &lt;javadoc destdir="${result-dir}/javadoc"&gt;
        &lt;sourcefiles&gt;
            &lt;fileset dir="${src-location}" id="src"&gt;
                &lt;include name="**/*.java"/&gt;
                
                &lt;!-- Excluded stuff from the package --&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/client/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/demo/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/MyDemoUI.java</emphasis>"/&gt;
            &lt;/fileset&gt;
        &lt;/sourcefiles&gt;
        &lt;classpath&gt;
            &lt;path refid="compile.classpath"/&gt;
        &lt;/classpath&gt;
    &lt;/javadoc&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;</programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="gwt.addons.ant.package">
                <title>Packaging the JAR</title>

                <para>
                    An add-on JAR typically includes the following:
                </para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Vaadin add-on manifest</listitem>
                    <listitem>The compiled server-side classes</listitem>
                    <listitem>The compiled JavaDoc (optional)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Sources of client-side classes (optional)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Any JavaScript dependency libraries (optional)</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>
                    Let us begin crafting the target. The JAR requires the compiled
                    server-side classes and the optional API documentation.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[<!-- Build the JAR -->
<target name="package-jar"
        depends="compile-server-side, compile-javadoc">
    <jar jarfile="${target-jar}" compress="true">]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    First, you need to include a manifest that defines basic information
                    about the add-on. The implementation title must be the exact title of
                    the add-on, as shown in the Vaadin Directory title. The vendor is
                    you. The manifest also includes the license title and file reference
                    for the add-on.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?>&lt;!-- Manifest required by Vaadin Directory --&gt;
&lt;manifest&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Vaadin-Package-Version"
               value="1" /&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Vaadin-Widgetsets"
               value="${widgetset}" /&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Implementation-Title"
               value="<emphasis role="bold">My Own Addon</emphasis>" /&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Implementation-Version"
               value="${version}" /&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Implementation-Vendor"
               value="<emphasis role="bold">Me Myself</emphasis>" /&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Vaadin-License-Title"
               value="<emphasis role="bold">Apache2</emphasis>" /&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="Vaadin-License-File"
        value="<emphasis role="bold">http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</emphasis>" /&gt;
&lt;/manifest&gt;</programlisting>

                <para>
                    The rest of the <literal>package-jar</literal> target goes as
                    follows. As was done in the JavaDoc compilation, you also need to
                    exclude any test or demo code in the project here. You need to modify
                    at least the emphasized parts for your project.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?>        &lt;!-- Include built server-side classes --&gt;
        &lt;fileset dir="build/result/classes"&gt;
            &lt;patternset&gt;
                &lt;include name="<emphasis role="bold">com/example/myaddon/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/client/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/demo/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/test/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
                &lt;exclude name="<emphasis role="bold">**/MyDemoUI*</emphasis>"/&gt;
            &lt;/patternset&gt;
        &lt;/fileset&gt;
    
        &lt;!-- Include widget set sources --&gt;
        &lt;fileset dir="src"&gt;
            &lt;patternset&gt;
                &lt;include name="<emphasis role="bold">com/exaple/myaddon/**/*</emphasis>"/&gt;
            &lt;/patternset&gt;
        &lt;/fileset&gt;
    
        &lt;!-- Include JavaDoc in the JAR --&gt;
        &lt;fileset dir="${result-dir}/javadoc"
                 includes="**/*"/&gt;
    &lt;/jar&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;</programlisting>

            </section>

            <para>
                You should now be ready to run the build script with Ant.
            </para>
        </section>
        <indexterm startref="term.gwt.addons" class="endofrange"/>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.vaadin-6-migration" condition="web">
        <title>Migrating from Vaadin 6</title>

        <indexterm xml:id="term.gwt.vaadin-6-migration" class="startofrange" significance="preferred">
            <primary>Vaadin 6 Migration</primary>
            <secondary>add-ons</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>
            The client-side architecture was redesigned almost entirely in Vaadin 7. In
            Vaadin 6, state synchronization was done explicitly by serializing and
            deserializing the state on the server- and client-side. In Vaadin 7, the
            serialization is handled automatically by the framework using state objects.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            In Vaadin 6, a server-side component serialized its state to the client-side
            using the <interfacename>Paintable</interfacename> interface in the
            client-side and deserialized the state through the
            <interfacename>VariableOwner</interfacename> interface. In Vaadin 7, these are
            done through the <interfacename>ClientConnector</interfacename> interface.
        </para>

        <para>
            On the client-side, a widget deserialized its state through the
            <interfacename>Paintable</interfacename> interface and sent state changes
            through the <interfacename>ApplicationConnection</interfacename> object. In
            Vaadin 7, these are replaced with the
            <interfacename>ServerConnector</interfacename>.
        </para>

        <para>
            In addition to state synchronization, Vaadin 7 has an RPC mechanism that can
            be used for communicating events. They are especially useful for events that
            are not associated with a state change, such as a button click.
        </para>

        <para>
            The framework ensures that the connector hierarchy and states are up-to-date
            when listeners are called.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.vaadin-6-migration.quick">
            <title>Quick (and Dirty) Migration</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin 7 has a compatibility layer that allows quick conversion of a widget.
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Create a connector class, such as
                        <classname>MyConnector</classname>, that extends
                        <classname>LegacyConnector</classname>. Implement the
                        <methodname>getWidget()</methodname> method.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Move the <literal>@ClientWidget(MyWidget.class)</literal> from the
                        server-side component, say <classname>MyComponent</classname>, to
                        the <classname>MyConnector</classname> class and make it
                        <literal>@Connect(MyComponent.class)</literal>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Have the server-side component implement the
                        <interface>LegacyComponent</interface> interface to enable
                        compatibility handling.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Remove any calls to <literal>super.paintContent()</literal>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Update any imports on the client-side
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>

        <indexterm startref="term.gwt.vaadin-6-migration" class="endofrange"/>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gwt.javascript">
        <title>Integrating JavaScript Components and Extensions</title>

        <indexterm xml:id="term.gwt.javascript" class="startofrange">
            <primary>JavaScript integration</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>
            Vaadin allows simplified integration of pure JavaScript components, as well as
            component and UI extensions. The JavaScript connector code is published from
            the server-side. As the JavaScript integration does not involve GWT
            programming, no widget set compilation is needed.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.example">
            <title>Example JavaScript Library</title>

            <para>
                There are many kinds of component libraries for JavaScript. In the
                following, we present a simple library that provides one object-oriented
                JavaScript component. We use this example later to show how to integrate
                it with a server-side Vaadin component.
            </para>

            <para>
                The example library includes a single <classname>MyComponent</classname>
                component, defined in <filename>mylibrary.js</filename>.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Define the namespace
var mylibrary = mylibrary || {};

mylibrary.MyComponent = function (element) {
	element.innerHTML =
		"<div class='caption'>Hello, world!</div>" +
		"<div class='textinput'>Enter a value: " +
		"<input type='text' name='value'/>" +
		"<input type='button' value='Click'/>" +
		"</div>";

	// Style it
	element.style.border = "thin solid red";
	element.style.display = "inline-block";

	// Getter and setter for the value property
	this.getValue = function () {
		return element.
		    getElementsByTagName("input")[0].value;
	};
	this.setValue = function (value) {
		element.getElementsByTagName("input")[0].value =
		    value;
	};

	// Default implementation of the click handler
	this.click = function () {
		alert("Error: Must implement click() method");
	};

	// Set up button click
	var button = element.getElementsByTagName("input")[1];
	var self = this; // Can't use this inside the function
	button.onclick = function () {
		self.click();
	};
};]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                When used in an HTML page, the library would be included with the
                following definition:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript"
        src="mylibrary.js"></script>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                You could then use it anywhere in the HTML document as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[<!-- Placeholder for the component -->    
<div id="foo"></div>
    
<!-- Create the component and bind it to the placeholder -->
<script type="text/javascript">
    window.foo = new mylibrary.MyComponent(
            document.getElementById("foo"));
    window.foo.click = function () {
        alert("Value is " + this.getValue());
    }
</script>]]></programlisting>

            <figure xml:id="figure.gwt.javascript.example">
                <title>A JavaScript Component Example</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/gwt/javascript-component.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                You could interact with the component with JavaScript for example as
                follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[<a href="javascript:foo.setValue('New value')">Click here</a>]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.server-side">
            <title>A Server-Side API for a JavaScript Component</title>

            <para>
                To begin integrating such a JavaScript component, you would need to sketch
                a bit how it would be used from a server-side Vaadin application. The
                component should support writing the value as well as listening for
                changes to it.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[final MyComponent mycomponent = new MyComponent();

// Set the value from server-side
mycomponent.setValue("Server-side value");

// Process a value input by the user from the client-side
mycomponent.addValueChangeListener(
        new MyComponent.ValueChangeListener() {
    @Override
    public void valueChange() {
        Notification.show("Value: " + mycomponent.getValue());
    }
});

layout.addComponent(mycomponent);]]></programlisting>

            <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.server-side.component">
                <title>Basic Server-Side Component</title>

                <para>
                    A JavaScript component extends the
                    <classname>AbstractJavaScriptComponent</classname>, which handles the
                    shared state and RPC for the component.
                </para>

                <!-- TODO: make addListener() public in original example, getState() protected. -->
                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[package com.vaadin.book.examples.client.js;

@JavaScript({"mylibrary.js", "mycomponent-connector.js"})
public class MyComponent extends AbstractJavaScriptComponent {
    public interface ValueChangeListener extends Serializable {
        void valueChange();
    }
    ArrayList<ValueChangeListener> listeners =
            new ArrayList<ValueChangeListener>();
    public void addValueChangeListener(
                   ValueChangeListener listener) {
        listeners.add(listener);
    }
    
    public void setValue(String value) {
        getState().value = value;
    }
    
    public String getValue() {
        return getState().value;
    }

    @Override
    protected MyComponentState getState() {
        return (MyComponentState) super.getState();
    }
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Notice later when creating the JavaScript connector that its name must
                    match the package name of this server-side class.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The shared state of the component is as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public class MyComponentState extends JavaScriptComponentState {
    public String value;
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    If the member variables are private, you need to have public setters
                    and getters for them, which you can use in the component.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.connector">
            <title>Defining a JavaScript Connector</title>

            <para>
                A JavaScript connector is a function that initializes the JavaScript
                component and handles communication between the server-side and the
                JavaScript code. <!-- TOD Clarify - code? -->
            </para>

            <para>
                A connector is defined as a connector initializer function that is added
                to the <literal>window</literal> object. The name of the function must
                match the server-side class name, with the full package path. Instead of
                the Java dot notation for the package name, underscores need to be used as
                separators.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Vaadin client-side framework adds a number of methods to the connector
                function. The <methodname>this.getElement()</methodname> method returns the
                HTML DOM element of the component. The
                <methodname>this.getState()</methodname> returns a shared state object
                with the current state as synchronized from the server-side.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[window.com_vaadin_book_examples_client_js_MyComponent =
function() {
    // Create the component
    var mycomponent =
        new mylibrary.MyComponent(this.getElement());
    
    // Handle changes from the server-side
    this.onStateChange = function() {
        mycomponent.setValue(this.getState().value);
    };

    // Pass user interaction to the server-side
    var self = this;
    mycomponent.click = function() {
        self.onClick(mycomponent.getValue());
    };
};]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                In the above example, we pass user interaction using the JavaScript RPC
                mechanism, as described in the next section.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.rpc">
            <title>RPC from JavaScript to Server-Side</title>

            <para>
                User interaction with the JavaScript component has to be passed to the
                server-side using an RPC (Remote Procedure Call) mechanism. The JavaScript
                RPC mechanism is almost equal to regular client-side widgets, as described
                in <xref linkend="gwt.rpc"/>.
            </para>


            <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.rpc.handling">
                <title>Handling RPC Calls on the Server-Side</title>

                <para>
                    Let us begin with the RPC function registration on the
                    server-side. RPC calls are handled on the server-side in function
                    handlers that implement the
                    <interfacename>JavaScriptFunction</interfacename> interface. A
                    server-side function handler is registered with the
                    <methodname>addFunction()</methodname> method in
                    <classname>AbstractJavaScriptComponent</classname>. The server-side
                    registration actually defines a JavaScript method that is available in
                    the client-side connector object.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Continuing from the server-side <classname>MyComponent</classname>
                    example we defined earlier, we add a constructor to it that registers
                    the function.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public MyComponent() {
    addFunction("onClick", new JavaScriptFunction() {
        @Override
        public void call(JSONArray arguments)
                throws JSONException {
            getState().setValue(arguments.getString(0));
            for (ValueChangeListener listener: listeners)
                listener.valueChange();
        }
    });
}]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="gwt.javascript.rpc.calling">
                <title>Making an RPC Call from JavaScript</title>

                <para>
                    An RPC call is made simply by calling the RPC method in the
                    connector. In the constructor function of the JavaScript connector,
                    you could write as follows (the complete connector code was given earlier):
                </para>

                <!-- TODO
                      Could also point out that the normal RPC mechanism can also be used, see
                      https://vaadin.com/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Using%20RPC%20from%20JavaScript
                      and
                      https://vaadin.com/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Simplified%20RPC%20using%20JavaScript
                -->

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[window.com_vaadin_book_examples_gwt_js_MyComponent =
    function() {
        ...
        var connector = this;
        mycomponent.click = function() {
            connector.onClick(mycomponent.getValue());
        };
    };]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Here, the <literal>mycomponent.click</literal> is a function in
                    the example JavaScript library, as described in <xref
                    linkend="gwt.javascript.example"/>. The
                    <methodname>onClick()</methodname> is the method we defined on the
                    server-side. We pass a simple string parameter in the call.
                </para>

                <para>
                    You can pass anything that is valid in JSON notation in the
                    parameters.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <indexterm startref="term.gwt.javascript" class="endofrange"/>
    </section>

    <indexterm startref="term.gwt" class="endofrange"/>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->

