<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
		This chapter gives a brief introduction to software development with Vaadin. We
		also try to give some insight about the design philosophy behind Vaadin and its
		history.
	</para>

	<section xml:id="intro.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>

		<para>
			Vaadin Framework is a Java web application development framework that is
			designed to make creation and maintenance of high quality web-based user
			interfaces easy. Vaadin supports two different programming models: server-side
			and client-side. The server-driven programming model is the more powerful one.
			It lets you forget the web and program user interfaces much like you would
			program a desktop application with conventional Java toolkits such as AWT,
			Swing, or SWT. But easier.
		</para>

		<para>
			While traditional web programming is a fun way to spend your time learning new
			web technologies, you probably want to be productive and concentrate on the
			application logic. The server-side Vaadin framework takes care of managing the
			user interface in the browser and the <firstterm>AJAX</firstterm>
			communications between the browser and the server. With the Vaadin approach,
			you do not need to learn and deal directly with browser technologies, such as
			HTML or JavaScript.
		</para>

		<figure xml:id="figure.intro.architecture">
			<title>Vaadin Application Architecture</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata scale="70" align="center" fileref="img/intro/architecture-vaadin7-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="50" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/intro/architecture-vaadin7-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>
			<xref linkend="figure.intro.architecture"/> illustrates the basic
			architectures of web applications made with Vaadin. The server-side
			application architecture consists of the <emphasis>server-side
			framework</emphasis> and a <emphasis>client-side engine</emphasis>. The engine
			runs in the browser as JavaScript code, rendering the user interface, and
			delivering user interaction to the server. The UI logic of an application runs
			as a Java Servlet in a Java application server.
		</para>

		<para>
            As the client-side engine is executed as JavaScript in the browser, no browser
            plugins are needed for using applications made with Vaadin. This gives it an
            edge over frameworks based on Flash, Java Applets, or other plugins. Vaadin
            relies on the support of Google Web Toolkit for a wide range of browsers, so
            that the developer does not need to worry about browser support.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Because HTML, JavaScript, and other browser technologies are essentially
			invisible to the application logic, you can think of the web browser as only a
			thin client platform. A thin client displays the user interface and
			communicates user events to the server at a low level. The control logic of
			the user interface runs on a Java-based web server, together with your
			business logic. By contrast, a normal client-server architecture with a
			dedicated client application would include a lot of application specific
			communications between the client and the server. Essentially removing the
			user interface tier from the application architecture makes our approach a
			very effective one.
		</para>

		<para>
			Behind the server-driven development model, Vaadin makes the best use of AJAX
			(<firstterm>Asynchronous JavaScript and XML</firstterm>, see <xref
			linkend="architecture.technology.ajax"/> for a description) techniques that
			make it possible to create Rich Internet Applications (RIA) that are as
			responsive and interactive as desktop applications.
		</para>

        <para>
            In addition to the server-side Java application development, you can develop
            on the client-side by making new widgets in Java, and even pure client-side
            applications that run solely in the browser.  The Vaadin client-side framework
            includes Google Web Toolkit (GWT), which provides a compiler from Java to the
            JavaScript that runs in the browser, as well a full-featured user interface
            framework. With this approach, Vaadin is pure Java on both sides.

            <indexterm><primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary></indexterm>
        </para>

		<para>
            Vaadin uses a client-side engine for rendering the user interface of a
            server-side application in the browser. All the client-server communications
            are hidden well under the hood.

            <indexterm><primary>JavaScript</primary></indexterm>

            Vaadin is designed to be extensible, and you can indeed use any 3rd-party
            widgets easily, in addition to the component repertoire offered in Vaadin. In
            fact, you can find hundreds of add-ons in the Vaadin Directory.
		</para>

		<para>
			Vaadin allows flexible separation between the appearance, structure, and
			interaction logic of the user interface. You can design the layouts either
			programmatically or declaratively, at the level of your choosing. The final
			appearance is defined in <firstterm>themes</firstterm> in CSS or Sass, as
			described in <xref linkend="themes"/>.
		</para>

		<para>
			We hope that this is enough about the basic architecture and features of
			Vaadin for now. You can read more about it later in <xref
			linkend="architecture"/>, or jump straight to more practical things in <xref
			linkend="application"/>.
        </para>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="intro.walkthrough">
		<title>Example Application Walkthrough</title>

		<para>
			Let us follow the long tradition of first saying "Hello World!" when learning
			a new programming framework. First, using the primary server-side API.
		</para>

        <programlisting language="java"><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[import com.vaadin.server.VaadinRequest;
import com.vaadin.ui.Label;
import com.vaadin.ui.UI;

@Title("My UI")
@Theme("valo")
public class HelloWorld extends UI {
    @Override
    protected void init(VaadinRequest request) {
        // Create the content root layout for the UI
        VerticalLayout content = new VerticalLayout();
        setContent(content);

        // Display the greeting
        content.addComponent(new Label("Hello World!"));

        // Have a clickable button        
        content.addComponent(new Button("Push Me!",
            new ClickListener() {
                @Override
                public void buttonClick(ClickEvent e) {
                    Notification.show("Pushed!");
                }
            }));
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		
		<para>
			A Vaadin application has one or more <emphasis>&ui;</emphasis>s that extend
			the <classname>com.vaadin.ui.&uiclass;</classname> class. A &ui; is a part of
			the web page in which the Vaadin application runs. An application can have
			multiple &ui;s in the same page, especially in portals, or in different
			windows or tabs. A UI is associated with a user session, and a session is
			created for each user who uses the application. In the context of our Hello
			World UI, it is sufficient to know that the underlying session is created when
			the user first accesses the application by opening the page, and the
			<methodname>init()</methodname> method is invoked at that time.
		</para>

		<para>
			The page title, which is shown in the caption of the browser window or tab, is
			defined with an annotation. The example uses a layout component as the root
			content of the UI, as that is the case with most Vaadin applications, which
			normally have more than one component. It then creates a new
			<classname>Label</classname> user interface component, which displays simple
			text, and sets the text to "Hello World!". The label is added to the layout.
		</para>

        <para>
            The example also shows how to create a button and handle button click
            events. Event handling is described in <xref linkend="architecture.events"/>
            and on the practical side in <xref linkend="application.events"/>. In addition
            to listeners, in Java 8 you can handle events with lambda expressions, which
            simplifies the handler code significantly.
        </para>

        <programlisting language="java"><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[content.addComponent(new Button("Push Me!",
    event -> Notification.show("Pushed!")));]]></programlisting>
		
		<para>
			The result of the Hello World application, when opened in a browser, is shown
			in <xref linkend="figure.intro.walkthrough"/>.
		</para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.intro.walkthrough">
            <title>Hello World Application</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="80%" align="center" fileref="img/intro/HelloWorld.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

		<para>
			To run a program, you need to package it as a web application WAR package and
			deploy it to a server, as explained in <xref
			linkend="application.environment"/>. During development, you typically deploy
			to an application server integrated with the IDE.
		</para>

        <para>
            Developing a pure client-side application, you could write a Hello World just
            as easily, and also in Java:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="java"><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public class HelloWorld implements EntryPoint {
    @Override
    public void onModuleLoad() {
        RootPanel.get().add(new Label("Hello, world!"));
    }
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            We do not set the title here, because it is usually defined in the HTML page in
            which the code is executed. The application would be compiled into JavaScript
            with the Vaadin Client Compiler (or GWT Compiler). It is more typical,
            however, to write client-side widgets, which you can then use from a
            server-side Vaadin application. For more information regarding client-side
            development, see <xref linkend="clientside"/>.
        </para>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="intro.eclipse">
		<title>Support for the Eclipse IDE</title>

		<para>
			While Vaadin is not bound to any specific IDE, and you can in fact easily use
			it without any IDE altogether, we provide special support for the Eclipse IDE,
			which has become the most used environment for Java development. The support
			is provided in the Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse, which helps you in:
		</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Creating new Vaadin projects</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Creating custom themes</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Creating custom client-side widgets</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Easily upgrading to a newer version of the Vaadin library</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

		<para>
			Using the Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse is the recommended way of installing
			Vaadin for development. Downloading the installation package that contains the
			JARs or defining Vaadin as a Maven dependency is also possible.
		</para>

		<para>
			Installing and updating the Eclipse plugin is covered in <xref
			linkend="getting-started.eclipse"/> and the creation of a new Vaadin project
			using the plugin in <xref
			linkend="getting-started.first-project.creation"/>. See <xref
			linkend="themes.eclipse"/> and <xref linkend="gwt.eclipse"/> for instructions
			on using the different features of the plugin.
		</para>
	</section>

    <section xml:id="intro.goals">
        <title>Goals and Philosophy</title>

        <para>
            Simply put, Vaadin's ambition is to be the best possible tool when it comes to
            creating web user interfaces for business applications. It is easy to adopt,
            as it is designed to support both entry-level and advanced programmers, as
            well as usability experts and graphic designers.
        </para>

        <para>
            When designing Vaadin, we have followed the philosophy inscribed in
            the following rules.
        </para>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Right tool for the right purpose</title>

            <para>
                Because our goals are high, the focus must be clear. Vaadin is designed
                for creating web applications. It is not designed for creating websites or
                advertisement demos. You may find, for example, JSP/JSF or Flash more
                suitable for such purposes.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Simplicity and maintainability</title>

            <para>
                We have chosen to emphasize robustness, simplicity, and
                maintainability. This involves following the well-established best
                practices in user interface frameworks and ensuring that our
                implementation represents an ideal solution for its purpose without
                clutter or bloat.
			</para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>XML is not designed for programming</title>
            <para>
                The Web is inherently document-centered and very much bound to the
                declarative presentation of user interfaces. While Vaadin allows for
                declarative designs of views, layouts, and even entire UIs, the
                programmatic approach by building the UIs from Java components frees the
                programmer from these limitations. To create highly dynamic views, it is
                more natural to create them by programming.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Tools should not limit your work</title>
            <para>
                There should not be any limits on what you can do with the framework:
                if for some reason the user interface components do not support what
                you need to achieve, it must be easy to add new ones to your
                application. When you need to create new components, the role of the
                framework is critical: it makes it easy to create re-usable components
                that are easy to maintain.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="intro.background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>
            The Vaadin Framework was not written overnight. After working with web user
            interfaces since the beginning of the Web, a group of developers got together
            in 2000 to form IT Mill. The team had a desire to develop a new programming
            paradigm that would support the creation of real user interfaces for real
            applications using a real programming language.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The library was originally called Millstone Library. The first version was
            used in a large production application that IT Mill designed and
            implemented for an international pharmaceutical company. IT Mill made the
            application already in the year 2001 and it is still in use. Since then,
            the company has produced dozens of large business applications with the
            library and it has proven its ability to solve hard problems easily.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The next generation of the library, IT Mill Toolkit Release 4, was
            released in 2006. It introduced an entirely new AJAX-based presentation
            engine. This allowed the development of AJAX applications without the need
            to worry about communications between the client and the server.
        </para>
        
        <simplesect xml:id="intro.background.toolkit-5">
            <title>Release 5 Into the Open</title>

            <para>
                <indexterm><primary>IT Mill Toolkit</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>AJAX</primary></indexterm>

                IT Mill Toolkit 5, released initially at the end of 2007, took a
                significant step further into AJAX. The client-side rendering of the user
                interface was completely rewritten using GWT, the Google Web Toolkit.

                <indexterm><primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary></indexterm>
            </para>

            <para>
                IT Mill Toolkit 5 introduced many significant improvements both in the
                server-side API and in the functionality. Rewriting the Client-Side Engine
                with GWT allowed the use of Java both on the client and the
                server-side. The transition from JavaScript to GWT made the development
                and integration of custom components and customization of existing
                components much easier than before, and it also allows easy integration of
                existing GWT components. The adoption of GWT on the client-side did not,
                by itself, cause any changes in the server-side API, because GWT is a
                browser technology that is hidden well behind the API. Also theming was
                completely revised in IT Mill Toolkit 5.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Release 5 was published under the Apache License 2, an unrestrictive
                open source license, to create faster expansion of the user base and to make
                the formation of a developer community possible.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

		<simplesect xml:id="intro.background.vaadin6">
			<title>Birth of Vaadin Release 6</title>

			<para>
				IT Mill Toolkit was renamed as <emphasis>Vaadin Framework</emphasis>, or
				Vaadin in short, in spring 2009. Later IT Mill, the company, was also
				renamed as Vaadin Ltd. Vaadin means an adult female semi-domesticated
				mountain reindeer in Finnish.
			</para>

            <para>
                With Vaadin 6, the number of developers using the framework
                exploded. Together with the release, the Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse was
                released, helping the creation of Vaadin projects. The introduction of
                Vaadin Directory in early 2010 gave it a further boost, as the number of
                available components multiplied almost overnight. Many of the originally
                experimental components have since then matured and are now used by
                thousands of developers. In 2013, we are seeing tremendous growth in the
                ecosystem around Vaadin. The size of the user community, at least if
                measured by forum activity, has already gone past the competing
                server-side frameworks and even GWT.
            </para>
		</simplesect>

		<simplesect xml:id="intro.background.vaadin7">
			<title>The Major Revision with Vaadin 7</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin 7 was a major revision that changed the Vaadin API much more than
                Vaadin 6 did. It is certainly more web-oriented than Vaadin 6 was.

                We are doing everything we can to help Vaadin rise high in the web
                universe. Some of this work is easy and almost routine - fixing bugs and
                implementing features. But going higher also requires standing
                firmer. That was one of the aims of Vaadin 7 - redesigning the product so that
                the new architecture enables Vaadin to reach over many long-standing
                challenges.

                Many of the changes required breaking API compatibility with Vaadin 6,
                especially in the client-side, but they are made with a strong desire to
                avoid carrying unnecessary legacy burden far into the future.
            </para>

            <para>
                Inclusion of the Google Web Toolkit in Vaadin 7 was a significant
                development, as it meant that Vaadin now provides support for GWT as
                well. When Google opened the GWT development in summer 2012, Vaadin (the
                company) joined the new GWT steering committee. As a member of the
                committee, Vaadin can work towards the success of GWT as a foundation of
                the Java web development community.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
