<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="layout">
	<title>Managing Layout</title>

		<para>
			Ever since the ancient xeroxians invented graphical user interfaces,
			programmers have wanted to make GUI programming ever easier for
			themselves. Solutions started simple. When GUIs appeared on PC
			desktops, practically all screens were of the VGA type and fixed into
			640x480 size. Mac or X Window System on UNIX were not much
			different. Everyone was so happy with such awesome graphics
			resolutions that they never thought that an application would have to
			work on a radically different screen size. At worst, screens could
			only grow, they thought, giving more space for more windows. In the
			80s, the idea of having a computer screen in your pocket was simply
			not realistic. Hence, the GUI APIs allowed placing UI components
			using screen coordinates. Visual Basic and some other systems
			provided an easy way for the designer to drag and drop components on
			a fixed-sized window. One would have thought that at least
			translators would have complained about the awkwardness of such a solution,
			but apparently they were not, as non-engineers, heard or at least
			cared about. At best, engineers could throw at them a resource editor
			that would allow them to resize the UI components by hand. Such was
			the spirit back then.
		</para>
			
		<para>
			After the web was born, layout design was doomed to change for ever.
			At first, layout didn't matter much, as everyone was happy with plain
			headings, paragraphs, and a few hyperlinks here and there.  Designers
			of HTML wanted the pages to run on any screen size. The screen size
			was actually not pixels but rows and columns of characters, as the
			baby web was really just hyper<emphasis>text</emphasis>, not
			graphics. That was soon to be changed. The first GUI-based browser,
			NCSA Mosaic, launched a revolution that culminated in Netscape
			Navigator. Suddenly, people who had previously been doing
			advertisement brochures started writing HTML. This meant that layout
			design had to be easy not just for programmers, but also allow the
			graphics designer to do his or her job without having to know a thing
			about programming. The W3C committee designing web standards came up
			with the CSS (Cascading Style Sheet) specification, which allowed trivial separation of
			appearance from content. Later versions of HTML followed, XHTML and HTML 5
			appeared, as did countless other standards.
		</para>
			
		<para>
			Page description and markup languages are a wonderful solution for static
			presentations, such as books and most web pages. Real applications, however,
			need to have more control. They need to be able to change the state of user
			interface components and even their layout on the run. This creates a need to
			separate the presentation from content on exactly the right level. <!-- Vaadin
			provides a solution for this, using themes and CSS, but let us first look at
			what Java did for UI programming. -->

			<!-- Changing the layout steps right on the feet of the graphics
			designers, so we have a conflict. We will discuss this conflict
			later, but let us first look at what Java did for UI programming. -->
		</para>
			
		<para>
			Thanks to the attack of graphics designers, desktop applications were, when it
			comes to appearance, far behind web design. Sun Microsystems had come in 1995
			with a new programming language, Java, for writing cross-platform desktop
			applications. Java's original graphical user interface toolkit, AWT (Abstract
			Windowing Toolkit), was designed to work on multiple operating systems as well
			as embedded in web browsers. One of the special aspects of AWT was the layout
			manager, which allowed user interface components to be flexible, growing and
			shrinking as needed. This made it possible for the user to resize the
			windows of an application flexibly and also served the needs of localization,
			as text strings were not limited to some fixed size in pixels. It became even
			possible to resize the pixel size of fonts, and the rest of the layout
			adapted to the new size.
		</para>

		<para>
			Layout management of Vaadin is a direct successor of the web-based concept for
			separation of content and appearance and of the Java AWT solution for binding
			the layout and user interface components into objects in programs. Vaadin
			layout components allow you to position your UI components on the screen in a
			hierarchical fashion, much like in conventional Java UI toolkits such as AWT,
			Swing, or SWT. In addition, you can approach the layout from the direction of
			the web with the <classname>CustomLayout</classname> component, which you can
			use to write your layout as a template in HTML that provides locations of any
			contained components. The <classname>AbsoluteLayout</classname> allows the
			old-style pixel-position based layouting, but it also supports percentual
			values, which makes it usable for scalable layouts. It is also useful as an
			area on which the user can position items with drag and drop.
		</para>

		<para>
			The moral of the story is that, because Vaadin is intended
			for web applications, appearance is of high importance. The solutions
			have to be the best of both worlds and satisfy artists of both
			kind: code and graphics. On the API side, the layout is controlled by UI
			components, particularly the layout components. On the visual side, it is controlled by themes. Themes
			can contain any HTML, Sass, CSS, and JavaScript that you or your web
			artists create to make people feel good about your software.
		</para>
			
	<section xml:id="layout.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            The user interface components in Vaadin can roughly be divided in two groups:
            components that the user can interact with and layout components for placing
            the other components to specific places in the user interface. The layout
            components are identical in their purpose to layout managers in regular
            desktop frameworks for Java and you can use plain Java to accomplish
            sophisticated component layouting.
        </para>

		<para>
			You start by creating a content layout for the UI and then add other layout
			components hierarchically, and finally the interaction components as the
			leaves of the component tree.
		</para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// Set the root layout for the UI
VerticalLayout content = new VerticalLayout();
setContent(content);

// Add the topmost component.
content.addComponent(new Label("The Ultimate Cat Finder"));

// Add a horizontal layout for the bottom part.
HorizontalLayout bottom = new HorizontalLayout();
content.addComponent(bottom);

bottom.addComponent(new Tree("Major Planets and Their Moons"));
bottom.addComponent(new Panel());
...]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Or in the declarative format:
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[<v-vertical-layout>
  <v-label>The Ultimate Cat Finder</v-label>

  <v-horizontal-layout>
    <v-tree caption="Major Planets and Their Moons"/>
    <v-panel/>
  </v-horizontal-layout>
</v-vertical-layout>]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			You will usually need to tune the layout components a bit by setting sizes,
			expansion ratios, alignments, spacings, and so on. The general settings are
			described in <xref linkend="layout.settings"/>.
		</para>

		<para>
			Layouts are coupled with themes that specify various layout features, such as
			backgrounds, borders, text alignment, and so on. Definition and use of themes
			is described in <xref linkend="themes"/>.
		</para>

		<para>
			You can see a finished version of the above example in <xref
			linkend="figure.layout.intro.simple"/>.
		</para>

		<figure xml:id="figure.layout.intro.simple">
			<title>Layout Example</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout-intro-example-1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout-intro-example-1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="layout.root-layout">
        <title>UI, Window, and Panel Content</title>

        <para>
            The <classname>UI</classname>, <classname>Window</classname>, and
            <classname>Panel</classname> all have a single content component, which you
            need to set with <methodname>setContent()</methodname>. The content is usually
            a layout component, although any component is allowed.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[Panel panel = new Panel("This is a Panel");
VerticalLayout panelContent = new VerticalLayout();
panelContent.addComponent(new Label("Hello!"));
panel.setContent(panelContent);

// Set the panel as the content of the UI
setContent(panel);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The size of the content is the default size of the particular layout
            component, for example, a <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> has 100% width
            and undefined height by default (this coincides with the defaults for
            <classname>Panel</classname> and <classname>Label</classname>). If such a
            layout with undefined height grows higher than the browser window, it will
            flow out of the view and scrollbars will appear. In many applications, you
            want to use the full area of the browser view. Setting the components
            contained inside the content layout to full size is not enough, and would
            actually lead to an invalid state if the height of the content layout is
            undefined.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// First set the root content for the UI
VerticalLayout content = new VerticalLayout();
setContent(content);

// Set the content size to full width and height
content.setSizeFull();

// Add a title area on top of the screen. This takes
// just the vertical space it needs.
content.addComponent(new Label("My Application"));

// Add a menu-view area that takes rest of vertical space
HorizontalLayout menuview = new HorizontalLayout();
menuview.setSizeFull();
content.addComponent(menuview);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            See <xref linkend="layout.settings.size"/> for more
            information about setting layout sizes.
        </para>

    </section>
		
    <section xml:id="layout.orderedlayout">
        <title><classname>VerticalLayout</classname> and <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname></title>
        
        <para>
            <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> and
            <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> are ordered layouts for laying
            components out either vertically or horizontally, respectively. They both
            extend from <classname>AbstractOrderedLayout</classname>, together with the
            <classname>FormLayout</classname>. These are the two most important layout
            components in Vaadin, and typically you have a
            <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> as the root content of a UI.
        </para>

        <para>
            <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> has 100% default width and undefined
            height, so it fills the containing layout (or UI) horizontally, and fits its
            content vertically. <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> has undefined size
            in both dimensions.
        </para>

        <para>
            Typical use of the layouts goes as follows:
        </para>

        <book-example eid="layout.orderedlayout.basic" style="float: right"></book-example>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[VerticalLayout vertical = new VerticalLayout ();
vertical.addComponent(new TextField("Name"));
vertical.addComponent(new TextField("Street address"));
vertical.addComponent(new TextField("Postal code"));
layout.addComponent(vertical);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The component captions are placed above the component, so the layout will look
            as follows:
        </para>

        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/orderedlayout_vertical.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        
        <para>
            Using <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> gives the following layout:
        </para>
        
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/orderedlayout_horizontal.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata scale="60" align="center" fileref="img/layout/orderedlayout_horizontal.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <section xml:id="layout.orderedlayout.properties">
            <title>Properties or Attributes</title>

            <para>
                Ordered layouts have the following properties:
            </para>

			<table xml:id="layout.orderedlayout.properties.table">
				<title>Properties and Declarative Attributes</title>

				<tgroup cols="2" align="left">
					<tbody>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry>Property</entry>
							<entry>Declarative Attribute</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
					<tbody>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>componentAlignment</parameter></entry>
							<entry>In child components: <literal>:left</literal> (default), <literal>:center</literal>, <literal>:right</literal>, <literal>:top</literal> (default), <literal>:middle</literal>, <literal>:bottom</literal></entry>
						</row>

						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>spacing</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>spacing</parameter><replaceable>[=&lt;boolean&gt;]</replaceable></entry>
						</row>

						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>margin</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>margin</parameter><replaceable>[=&lt;boolean&gt;]</replaceable></entry>
						</row>

						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>expandRatio</parameter></entry>
							<entry>In child components: <parameter>:expand</parameter>=<replaceable>&lt;integer&gt;</replaceable> or <parameter>:expand</parameter> (implies ratio 1)</entry>
						</row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.orderedlayout.spacing">
            <title>Spacing in Ordered Layouts</title>

            <para>
                The ordered layouts can have spacing between the horizontal or vertical
                cells. The spacing can be enabled with
                <methodname>setSpacing(true)</methodname> or declaratively with the
                <literal>spacing</literal> attribute.
            </para>

            <para>
                The spacing as a default height or width, which can be customized in
                CSS. You need to set the height or width for spacing elements with
                <literal>v-spacing</literal> style. You also need to specify an enclosing
                rule element in a CSS selector, such as
                <literal>v-verticallayout</literal> for a
                <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> or
                <literal>v-horizontallayout</literal> for a
                <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname>. You can also use
                <literal>v-vertical</literal> and <literal>v-horizontal</literal> for all
                vertically or horizontally ordered layouts, such as
                <classname>FormLayout</classname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, the following sets the amount of spacing for all
                <classname>VerticalLayout</classname>s, as well as
                <classname>FormLayout</classname>, in the UI:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[.v-vertical > .v-spacing {
    height: 30px;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Or for <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname>:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[.v-horizontal > .v-spacing {
    width: 50px;
}]]></programlisting>
       </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.orderedlayout.sizing">
            <title>Sizing Contained Components</title>

            <para>
                The components contained within an ordered layout can be laid out in a
                number of different ways depending on how you specify their height or
                width in the primary direction of the layout component.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.layout.orderedlayout.size.summary">
                <title>Component Widths in <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname></title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_sizing.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                <xref linkend="figure.layout.orderedlayout.size.summary"/> above gives a
                summary of the sizing options for a
                <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname>. The figure is broken down in the
                following subsections.
            </para>

            <simplesect xml:id="layout.orderedlayout.sizing.undefined">
                <title>Layout with Undefined Size</title>

                <para>
                    If a <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> has undefined height or
                    <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> undefined width, the layout
                    will shrink to fit the contained components so that there is no extra
                    space between them.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[HorizontalLayout fittingLayout = new HorizontalLayout();
fittingLayout.setWidth(Sizeable.SIZE_UNDEFINED, 0); // Default
fittingLayout.addComponent(new Button("Small"));
fittingLayout.addComponent(new Button("Medium-sized"));
fittingLayout.addComponent(new Button("Quite a big component"));
parentLayout.addComponent(fittingLayout);]]></programlisting>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_undefined.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>

                <para>
                    The both layouts actually have undefined height by default and
                    <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> has also undefined width,
                    while <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> has 100% relative width.
                </para>

                <para>
                    If such a vertical layout with undefined height continues below the
                    bottom of a window (a <classname>Window</classname> object), the
                    window will pop up a vertical scroll bar on the right side of the
                    window area. This way, you get a "web page". The same applies to
                    <classname>Panel</classname>.
                </para>

                <warning>
                    <title>A layout that contains components with percentual size must have a
                        defined size!</title>
                    
                    <para>
                        If a layout has undefined size and a contained component has, say,
                        100% size, the component would fill the space given by the layout,
                        while the layout would shrink to fit the space taken by the
                        component, which would be a paradox. This requirement holds for
                        height and width separately. The debug window allows detecting
                        such invalid cases; see <xref
                        linkend="advanced.debug.hierarchy"/>.
                    </para>
                </warning>

                <para>
                    An exception to the above rule is a case where you have a layout with
                    undefined size that contains a component with a fixed or undefined
                    size together with one or more components with relative size. In this
                    case, the contained component with fixed (or undefined) size in a
                    sense defines the size of the containing layout, removing the
                    paradox. That size is then used for the relatively sized components.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The technique can be used to define the width of a
                    <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> or the height of a
                    <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname>.
                </para>

                <book-example eid="layout.orderedlayout.sizing.sizing-undefined-defining" style="float: right"></book-example>
<programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Vertical layout would normally have 100% width
VerticalLayout vertical = new VerticalLayout();
        
// Shrink to fit the width of contained components
vertical.setWidth(Sizeable.SIZE_UNDEFINED, 0);
        
// Label has normally 100% width, but we set it as
// undefined so that it will take only the needed space
Label label =
    new Label("\u2190 The VerticalLayout shrinks to fit "+
              "the width of this Label \u2192");
label.setWidth(Sizeable.SIZE_UNDEFINED, 0);
vertical.addComponent(label);
        
// Button has undefined width by default
Button butt = new Button("\u2190 This Button takes 100% "+
                         "of the width \u2192");
butt.setWidth("100%");
vertical.addComponent(butt);]]></programlisting>

                <figure xml:id="figure.layout.orderedlayout.sizing.undefined.defining">
                    <title>Defining the Size with a Component</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/orderedlayout-sizing-undefined.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/orderedlayout-sizing-undefined.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </simplesect>

            <simplesect>
                <title>Layout with Defined Size</title>

                <para>
                    If you set a <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> to a defined size
                    horizontally or a <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> vertically,
                    and there is space left over from the contained components, the extra
                    space is distributed equally between the component cells. The
                    components are aligned within these cells according to their
                    alignment setting, top left by default, as in the example below.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[fixedLayout.setWidth("400px");]]></programlisting>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_defined.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>

                <para>
                    Using percentual sizes for components contained in a layout requires
                    answering the question, "Percentage of what?" There is no sensible
                    default answer for this question in the current implementation of the
                    layouts, so in practice, you may not define "100%" size alone.
                </para>
            </simplesect>

            <simplesect>
                <title>Expanding Components</title>

                <para>
                    Often, you want to have one component that takes all the available
                    space left over from other components. You need to set its size as
                    100% and set it as <emphasis>expanding</emphasis> with
                    <methodname>setExpandRatio()</methodname>. The second parameter for
                    the method is an expansion ratio, which is relevant if there are more
                    than one expanding component, but its value is irrelevant for a single
                    expanding component.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[HorizontalLayout layout = new HorizontalLayout();
layout.setWidth("400px");

// These buttons take the minimum size.
layout.addComponent(new Button("Small"));
layout.addComponent(new Button("Medium-sized"));

// This button will expand.
Button expandButton = new Button("Expanding component");

// Use 100% of the expansion cell's width.
expandButton.setWidth("100%");

// The component must be added to layout before setting the ratio.
layout.addComponent(expandButton);

// Set the component's cell to expand.
layout.setExpandRatio(expandButton, 1.0f);

parentLayout.addComponent(layout);]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    In the declarative format, you need to specify the
                    <literal>:expand</literal> attribute in the child components. The
                    attribute defaults to expand ratio 1.
                </para>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expanding.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                
                <para>
                    Notice that you can not call <methodname>setExpandRatio()</methodname>
                    before you have added the component to the layout, because it can not
                    operate on an component that it doesn't yet have.
                </para>
            </simplesect>

            <simplesect>
                <title>Expand Ratios</title>

                <para>
                    If you specify an expand ratio for multiple components, they will all
                    try to use the available space according to the ratio.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[HorizontalLayout layout = new HorizontalLayout();
layout.setWidth("400px");

// Create three equally expanding components.
String[] captions = { "Small", "Medium-sized",
                      "Quite a big component" };
for (int i = 1; i <= 3; i++) {
    Button button = new Button(captions[i-1]);
    button.setWidth("100%");
    layout.addComponent(button);

    // Have uniform 1:1:1 expand ratio.
    layout.setExpandRatio(button, 1.0f);
}]]></programlisting>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expand_uniform.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>

                <para>
                    As the example used the same ratio for all components, the ones with more
                    content may have the content cut. Below, we use differing ratios:
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[// Expand ratios for the components are 1:2:3.
layout.setExpandRatio(button, i * 1.0f);]]></programlisting>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expand_ratios.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>

                <para>
                    If the size of the expanding components is defined as a percentage
                    (typically "100%"), the ratio is calculated from the
                    <emphasis>overall</emphasis> space available for the relatively sized
                    components. For example, if you have a 100 pixels wide layout with two
                    cells with 1.0 and 4.0 respective expansion ratios, and both the
                    components in the layout are set as
                    <methodname>setWidth("100%")</methodname>, the cells will have
                    respective widths of 20 and 80 pixels, regardless of the minimum size
                    of the components.
                </para>

                <para>
                    However, if the size of the contained components is undefined or
                    fixed, the expansion ratio is of the <emphasis>excess</emphasis>
                    available space. In this case, it is the excess space that expands, not
                    the components.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[for (int i = 1; i <= 3; i++) {
    // Button with undefined size.
    Button button = new Button(captions[i - 1]);
    
    layout4.addComponent(button);

    // Expand ratios are 1:2:3.
    layout4.setExpandRatio(button, i * 1.0f);
}]]></programlisting>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expand_ratios-2.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>

                <para>
                    It is not meaningful to combine expanding components with percentually
                    defined size and components with fixed or undefined size. Such
                    combination can lead to a very unexpected size for the percentually
                    sized components.
                </para>
            </simplesect>

            <simplesect>
                <title>Percentage of Cells</title>

                <para>
                    A percentual size of a component defines the size of the component
                    <emphasis>within its cell</emphasis>. Usually, you use "100%", but a
                    smaller percentage or a fixed size (smaller than the cell size) will
                    leave an empty space in the cell and align the component within the
                    cell according to its alignment setting, top left by default.
                </para>

                <programlisting><![CDATA[HorizontalLayout layout50 = new HorizontalLayout();
layout50.setWidth("400px");

String[] captions1 = { "Small 50%", "Medium 50%",
                       "Quite a big 50%" };
for (int i = 1; i <= 3; i++) {
    Button button = new Button(captions1[i-1]);
    button.setWidth("50%");
    layout50.addComponent(button);

    // Expand ratios for the components are 1:2:3.
    layout50.setExpandRatio(button, i * 1.0f);
}
parentLayout.addComponent(layout50);]]></programlisting>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expand_percentage.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="layout.gridlayout">
        <title><classname>GridLayout</classname></title>
        
        <para>
            <classname>GridLayout</classname> container lays components out on a grid,
            defined by the number of columns and rows. The columns and rows of the grid
            serve as coordinates that are used for laying out components on the grid. Each
            component can use multiple cells from the grid, defined as an area
            (x1,y1,x2,y2), although they typically take up only a single grid cell.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The grid layout maintains a cursor for adding components in left-to-right,
            top-to-bottom order. If the cursor goes past the bottom-right corner, it
            will automatically extend the grid downwards by adding a new row.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The following example demonstrates the use of
            <classname>GridLayout</classname>. The
            <methodname>addComponent</methodname> takes a component and optional
            coordinates. The coordinates can be given for a single cell or for an area
            in x,y (column,row) order. The coordinate values have a base value of
            0. If coordinates are not given, the cursor will be used.
        </para>
        
        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Create a 4 by 4 grid layout.
GridLayout grid = new GridLayout(4, 4);
grid.addStyleName("example-gridlayout");

// Fill out the first row using the cursor.
grid.addComponent(new Button("R/C 1"));
for (int i = 0; i < 3; i++) {
    grid.addComponent(new Button("Col " + (grid.getCursorX() + 1)));
}

// Fill out the first column using coordinates.
for (int i = 1; i < 4; i++) {
    grid.addComponent(new Button("Row " + i), 0, i);
}

// Add some components of various shapes.
grid.addComponent(new Button("3x1 button"), 1, 1, 3, 1);
grid.addComponent(new Label("1x2 cell"), 1, 2, 1, 3);
InlineDateField date = new InlineDateField("A 2x2 date field");
date.setResolution(DateField.RESOLUTION_DAY);
grid.addComponent(date, 2, 2, 3, 3);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The resulting layout will look as follows. The borders have been
            made visible to illustrate the layout cells.
        </para>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure.ui.gridlayout">
            <title>The Grid Layout Component</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="130" align="center" fileref="img/layout/gridlayout.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            A component to be placed on the grid must not overlap with existing
            components. A conflict causes throwing a
            <classname>GridLayout.OverlapsException</classname>.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Sizing Grid Cells</title>
            
            <para>
                You can define the size of both a grid layout and its components in
                either fixed or percentual units, or leave the size undefined
                altogether, as described in <xref
					linkend="components.features.sizeable"/>. <xref
					linkend="layout.settings.size"/> gives an introduction to sizing of
                layouts.
            </para>

            <para>
                The size of the <classname>GridLayout</classname> component is
                undefined by default, so it will shrink to fit the size of the
                components placed inside it. In most cases, especially if you set a
                defined size for the layout but do not set the contained components to
                full size, there will be some unused space. The position of the
                non-full components within the grid cells will be determined by their
                <emphasis>alignment</emphasis>. See <xref
					linkend="layout.settings.alignment"/> for details on how to align the
                components inside the cells.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The components contained within a <classname>GridLayout</classname>
                layout can be laid out in a number of different ways depending on how
                you specify their height or width. The layout options are similar to
                <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> and
                <classname>VerticalLayout</classname>, as described in <xref
					linkend="layout.orderedlayout"/>.
            </para>
            
			<warning>
				<title>A layout that contains components with percentual size must have a
				defined size!</title>
				<para>
					If a layout has undefined size and a contained component has, say,
					100% size, the component would fill the space given by the layout,
					while the layout would shrink to fit the space taken by the component,
					which is a paradox. This requirement holds for height and width
					separately. The debug mode allows detecting such invalid cases; see
					<xref linkend="advanced.debug.mode"/>.
				</para>
            </warning>

            <para>
                Often, you want to have one or more rows or columns that take all the
                available space left over from non-expanding rows or columns. You need
                to set the rows or columns as <emphasis>expanding</emphasis> with
                <methodname>setRowExpandRatio()</methodname> and
                <methodname>setColumnExpandRatio()</methodname>. The first parameter
                for these methods is the index of the row or column to set as
                expanding. The second parameter for the methods is an expansion ratio,
                which is relevant if there are more than one expanding row or column,
                but its value is irrelevant if there is only one. With multiple
                expanding rows or columns, the ratio parameter sets the relative
                portion how much a specific row/column will take in relation with the
                other expanding rows/columns.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[GridLayout grid = new GridLayout(3,2);

// Layout containing relatively sized components must have
// a defined size, here is fixed size.
grid.setWidth("600px");
grid.setHeight("200px");

// Add some content
String labels [] = {
        "Shrinking column<br/>Shrinking row",
        "Expanding column (1:)<br/>Shrinking row",
        "Expanding column (5:)<br/>Shrinking row",
        "Shrinking column<br/>Expanding row",
        "Expanding column (1:)<br/>Expanding row",
        "Expanding column (5:)<br/>Expanding row"
};
for (int i=0; i<labels.length; i++) {
    Label label = new Label(labels[i], ContentMode.HTML);
    label.setWidth(null); // Set width as undefined
    grid.addComponent(label);
}

// Set different expansion ratios for the two columns
grid.setColumnExpandRatio(1, 1);
grid.setColumnExpandRatio(2, 5);

// Set the bottom row to expand
grid.setRowExpandRatio(1, 1);

// Align and size the labels.
for (int col=0; col<grid.getColumns(); col++) {
    for (int row=0; row<grid.getRows(); row++) {
        Component c = grid.getComponent(col, row);
        grid.setComponentAlignment(c, Alignment.TOP_CENTER);
        
        // Make the labels high to illustrate the empty
        // horizontal space.
        if (col != 0 || row != 0)
            c.setHeight("100%");
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <figure xml:id="figure.ui.gridlayout.sizing.expanding">
                <title>Expanding Rows and Columns in <classname>GridLayout</classname></title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/gridlayout_sizing_expanding.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                If the size of the contained components is undefined or fixed, the
                expansion ratio is of the <emphasis>excess</emphasis> space, as in
                <xref linkend="figure.ui.gridlayout.sizing.expanding"/> (excess
                horizontal space is shown in white). However, if the size of the all the
                contained components in the expanding rows or columns is defined as a
                percentage, the ratio is calculated from the
                <emphasis>overall</emphasis> space available for the percentually
                sized components. For example, if we had a 100 pixels wide grid layout
                with two columns with 1.0 and 4.0 respective expansion ratios, and all
                the components in the grid were set as
                <methodname>setWidth("100%")</methodname>, the columns would have
                respective widths of 20 and 80 pixels, regardless of the minimum size
                of their contained components.
            </para>
            
        </section>
        
        <simplesect>
            <title>CSS Style Rules</title>
            
            <programlisting><![CDATA[.v-gridlayout {}
.v-gridlayout-margin {}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The <markup>v-gridlayout</markup> is the root element of the
                <classname>GridLayout</classname> component. The
                <markup>v-gridlayout-margin</markup> is a simple element inside it
                that allows setting a padding between the outer element and the cells.
            </para>

            <para>
                For styling the individual grid cells, you should style the components
                inserted in the cells. The implementation structure of the grid can
                change, so depending on it, as is done in the example below, is not
                generally recommended. Normally, if you want to have, for example, a
                different color for a certain cell, just make set the component inside
                it <methodname>setSizeFull()</methodname>, and add a style name for
                it. Sometimes you may need to use a layout component between a cell
                and its actual component just for styling.
            </para>

            <para>
                The following example shows how to make the grid borders visible, as
                in <xref linkend="figure.ui.gridlayout.sizing.expanding"/>.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[.v-gridlayout-gridexpandratio {
    background: blue; /* Creates a "border" around the grid. */
    margin:     10px; /* Empty space around the layout. */
}

/* Add padding through which the background color shows. */
.v-gridlayout-gridexpandratio .v-gridlayout-margin {
    padding: 2px;     
}

/* Add cell borders and make the cell backgrounds white.
 * Warning: This depends heavily on the HTML structure. */
.v-gridlayout-gridexpandratio > div > div > div {
    padding:    2px;   /* Layout background will show through. */
    background: white; /* The cells will be colored white. */
}

/* Components inside the layout are a safe way to style cells. */
.v-gridlayout-gridexpandratio .v-label {
    text-align: left;
    background: #ffffc0; /* Pale yellow */
}]]></programlisting>
            
            <para>
                You should beware of <literal>margin</literal>,
                <literal>padding</literal>, and <literal>border</literal> settings in
                CSS as they can mess up the layout. The dimensions of layouts are
                calculated in the Client-Side Engine of Vaadin and some
                settings can interfere with these calculations. For more information,
                on margins and spacing, see <xref linkend="layout.settings.spacing"/>
                and <xref linkend="layout.settings.margins"/>
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="layout.formlayout">
        <title><classname>FormLayout</classname></title>
        
        <para>
            <classname>FormLayout</classname> lays the components and their captions out
            in two columns, with optional indicators for required fields and errors that
            can be shown for each field. The field captions can have an icon in addition
            to the text. <classname>FormLayout</classname> is an ordered layout and much
            like <classname>VerticalLayout</classname>. For description of margins,
            spacing, and other features in ordered layouts, see <xref
            linkend="layout.orderedlayout"/>.
        </para>

        <para>
            The following example shows typical use of <classname>FormLayout</classname>
            in a form:
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// A FormLayout used outside the context of a Form
FormLayout fl = new FormLayout();

// Make the FormLayout shrink to its contents 
fl.setSizeUndefined();

TextField tf = new TextField("A Field");
fl.addComponent(tf);

// Mark the first field as required
tf.setRequired(true);
tf.setRequiredError("The Field may not be empty.");

TextField tf2 = new TextField("Another Field");
fl.addComponent(tf2);

// Set the second field straing to error state with a message.
tf2.setComponentError(
    new UserError("This is the error indicator of a Field."));]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The resulting layout will look as follows. The error message shows in a
            tooptip when you hover the mouse pointer over the error indicator.
        </para>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.formlayout">
            <title>A <classname>FormLayout</classname> Layout for Forms</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="110" align="center" fileref="img/layout/formlayout-example1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>	

        <simplesect>
            <title>CSS Style Rules</title>

            <!-- TODO contains some rather specific examples -->            
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[.v-formlayout {}
.v-formlayout .v-caption {}

/* Columns in a field row. */
.v-formlayout-contentcell {} /* Field content. */
.v-formlayout-captioncell {} /* Field caption. */
.v-formlayout-errorcell {}   /* Field error indicator. */

/* Overall style of field rows. */
.v-formlayout-row {}
.v-formlayout-firstrow {}
.v-formlayout-lastrow {}

/* Required field indicator. */
.v-formlayout .v-required-field-indicator {}
.v-formlayout-captioncell .v-caption
        .v-required-field-indicator {}

/* Error indicator. */
.v-formlayout-cell .v-errorindicator {}
.v-formlayout-error-indicator .v-errorindicator {}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The top-level element of <classname>FormLayout</classname> has the
                <literal>v-formlayout</literal> style. The layout is tabular with three
                columns: the caption column, the error indicator column, and the field
                column. These can be styled with
                <literal>v-formlayout-captioncell</literal>,
                <literal>v-formlayout-errorcell</literal>, and
                <literal>v-formlayout-contentcell</literal>, respectively. While the
                error indicator is shown as a dedicated column, the indicator for required
                fields is currently shown as a part of the caption column.
            </para>

            <para>
                For information on setting margins and spacing, see also <xref
                linkend="layout.orderedlayout.spacing"/> and <xref
                linkend="layout.settings.margins"/>.
            </para>
            
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="layout.panel">
        <title><classname>Panel</classname></title>

        <para>
            <classname>Panel</classname> is a single-component container with a frame
            around the content. It has an optional caption and an icon which are handled
            by the panel itself, not its containing layout. The panel itself does not
            manage the caption of its contained component. You need to set the content
            with <methodname>setContent()</methodname>.
        </para>

        <para>
            <classname>Panel</classname> has 100% width and undefined height by
            default. This corresponds with the default sizing of
            <classname>VerticalLayout</classname>, which is perhaps most commonly used as
            the content of a <classname>Panel</classname>. If the width or height of a
            panel is undefined, the content must have a corresponding undefined or fixed
            size in the same direction to avoid a sizing paradox.
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[Panel panel = new Panel("Astronomy Panel");
panel.addStyleName("mypanelexample");
panel.setSizeUndefined(); // Shrink to fit content
layout.addComponent(panel);
        
// Create the content
FormLayout content = new FormLayout();
content.addStyleName("mypanelcontent");
content.addComponent(new TextField("Participant"));
content.addComponent(new TextField("Organization"));
content.setSizeUndefined(); // Shrink to fit
content.setMargin(true);
panel.setContent(content);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The resulting layout is shown in <xref linkend="figure.layout.panel"/>.
        </para>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.panel">
            <title>A <classname>Panel</classname></title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/panel.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>	

        <section xml:id="layout.panel.scrolling">
            <title>Scrolling the Panel Content</title>

            <indexterm xml:id="term.layout.panel.scrolling.scrollbars" class="startofrange">
                <primary>scroll bars</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>
                Normally, if a panel has undefined size in a direction, as it has by
                default vertically, it will fit the size of the content and grow as the
                content grows. However, if it has a fixed or percentual size and its
                content becomes too big to fit in the content area, a scroll bar will
                appear for the particular direction. Scroll bars in a
                <classname>Panel</classname> are handled natively by the browser with the
                <literal>overflow: auto</literal> property in CSS.

                <indexterm>overflow CSS property</indexterm>
            </para>

            <para>
                In the following example, we have a 300 pixels wide and very high
                <classname>Image</classname> component as the panel content.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Display an image stored in theme
Image image = new Image(null,
    new ThemeResource("img/Ripley_Scroll-300px.jpg"));
        
// To enable scrollbars, the size of the panel content
// must not be relative to the panel size
image.setSizeUndefined(); // Actually the default

// The panel will give it scrollbars.
Panel panel = new Panel("Scroll");
panel.setWidth("300px");
panel.setHeight("300px");
panel.setContent(image);

layout.addComponent(panel);]]></programlisting>

            <!-- Copyright Notice: The Ripley Scroll is out of copyright. -->

            <para>
                The result is shown in <xref
                linkend="figure.layout.panel.scrolling"/>. Notice that also the horizontal
                scrollbar has appeared even though the panel has the same width as the
                content (300 pixels) - the 300px width for the panel includes the panel
                border and vertical scrollbar.
            </para>

			<figure xml:id="figure.layout.panel.scrolling">
				<title>Panel with Scroll Bars</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata smallscale="75%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/panel-scrolling.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>	

            <indexterm xml:id="term.layout.panel.scrolling.scrollable" class="startofrange">
                <primary><interfacename>Scrollable</interfacename></primary>
            </indexterm>

            <simplesect xml:id="layout.panel.scrolling.programmatic">
                <title>Programmatic Scrolling</title>

                <para>
                    <classname>Panel</classname> implements the
                    <interfacename>Scrollable</interfacename> interface to allow
                    programmatic scrolling. You can set the scroll position in pixels with
                    <methodname>setScrollTop()</methodname> and
                    <methodname>setScrollLeft()</methodname>. You can also get the scroll
                    position set previously, but scrolling the panel in the browser does
                    not update the scroll position to the server-side.
                </para>

                <indexterm startref="term.layout.panel.scrolling.scrollable" class="endofrange"/>
                <indexterm startref="term.layout.panel.scrolling.scrollbars" class="endofrange"/>
            </simplesect>
        </section>

        <simplesect xml:id="layout.panel.css">
            <title>CSS Style Rules</title>
            
            <programlisting><![CDATA[.v-panel {}
.v-panel-caption {}
.v-panel-nocaption {}
.v-panel-content {}
.v-panel-deco {}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The entire panel has <literal>v-panel</literal> style. A panel
                consists of three parts: the caption, content, and bottom decorations
                (shadow). These can be styled with <literal>v-panel-caption</literal>,
                <literal>v-panel-content</literal>, and
                <literal>v-panel-deco</literal>, respectively. If the panel has no
                caption, the caption element will have the style
                <literal>v-panel-nocaption</literal>.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The built-in <literal>light</literal> style in the Reindeer and Runo
                themes has no borders or border decorations for the
                <classname>Panel</classname>. You can use the
                <parameter>Reindeer.PANEL_LIGHT</parameter> and
                <parameter>Runo.PANEL_LIGHT</parameter> constants to add the style to a
                panel. Other themes may also provide the light and other styles for
                <classname>Panel</classname> as well.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="layout.sub-window">
		<title>Sub-Windows</title>

		<para>
            <emphasis>Sub-windows</emphasis> are floating panels within a native browser
            window. Unlike native browser windows, sub-windows are managed by the
            client-side runtime of Vaadin using HTML features. Vaadin allows opening,
            closing, resizing, maximizing and restoring sub-windows, as well as scrolling
            the window content.
		</para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.sub-window.basic">
            <title>A Sub-Window</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/subwindow-basic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/subwindow-basic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Sub-windows are typically used for <firstterm>Dialog Windows</firstterm> and
            <firstterm>Multiple Document Interface</firstterm> applications. Sub-windows
            are by default not modal; you can set them modal as described in <xref
            linkend="layout.sub-window.modal"/>.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="layout.sub-window.openclose">
            <title>Opening and Closing Sub-Windows</title>

            <para>
                You can open a new sub-window by creating a new
                <classname>Window</classname> object and adding it to the UI with
                <methodname>addWindow()</methodname>, typically in some event listener. A
                sub-window needs a content component, which is typically a layout.
            </para>

            <para>
                In the following, we display a sub-window immediately when a UI opens:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[public static class SubWindowUI extends UI {
    @Override
    protected void init(VaadinRequest request) {
        // Some other UI content
        setContent(new Label("Here's my UI"));
        
        // Create a sub-window and set the content
        Window subWindow = new Window("Sub-window");
        VerticalLayout subContent = new VerticalLayout();
        subContent.setMargin(true);
        subWindow.setContent(subContent);
        
        // Put some components in it
        subContent.addComponent(new Label("Meatball sub"));
        subContent.addComponent(new Button("Awlright"));
        
        // Center it in the browser window
        subWindow.center();
        
        // Open it in the UI
        addWindow(subWindow);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The result was shown in <xref
                linkend="figure.layout.sub-window.basic"/>. Sub-windows by default have
                undefined size in both dimensions, so they will shrink to fit the content.
            </para>
            
			<para>
				The user can close a sub-window by clicking the close button in the
				upper-right corner of the window. The button is controlled by the
				<emphasis>closable</emphasis> property, so you can disable it with
				<methodname>setClosable(false)</methodname>.
			</para>
	
			<para>
				You close a sub-window also programmatically by calling the
				<methodname>close()</methodname> for the sub-window, typically in a click
				listener for an <guibutton>OK</guibutton> or <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>
				button. You can also call <methodname>removeWindow()</methodname> for the
				current <classname>UI</classname>.
			</para>

            <section xml:id="layout.sub-window.openclose.example" condition="web">
                <title>Sub-Window Management</title>

                <para>
                    Usually, you would extend the <classname>Window</classname> class for
                    your specific sub-window as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Define a sub-window by inheritance
class MySub extends Window {
    public MySub() {
        super("Subs on Sale"); // Set window caption
        center();

        // Some basic content for the window
        VerticalLayout content = new VerticalLayout();
        content.addComponent(new Label("Just say it's OK!"));
        content.setMargin(true);
        setContent(content);
        
        // Disable the close button
        setClosable(false);

        // Trivial logic for closing the sub-window
        Button ok = new Button("OK");
        ok.addClickListener(new ClickListener() {
            public void buttonClick(ClickEvent event) {
                close(); // Close the sub-window
            }
        });
        content.addComponent(ok);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    You could open the window as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[// Some UI logic to open the sub-window
final Button open = new Button("Open Sub-Window");
open.addClickListener(new ClickListener() {
    public void buttonClick(ClickEvent event) {
        MySub sub = new MySub();
        
        // Add it to the root component
        UI.getCurrent().addWindow(sub);
    }
});]]></programlisting>
            </section>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="layout.sub-window.position">
			<title>Window Positioning</title>

			<para>
				When created, a sub-window will have an undefined default size and
				position. You can specify the size of a window with
				<methodname>setHeight()</methodname> and
				<methodname>setWidth()</methodname> methods. You can set the position of
				the window with <methodname>setPositionX()</methodname> and
				<methodname>setPositionY()</methodname> methods.
			</para>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[// Create a new sub-window
mywindow = new Window("My Dialog");

// Set window size.
mywindow.setHeight("200px");
mywindow.setWidth("400px");

// Set window position.
mywindow.setPositionX(200);
mywindow.setPositionY(50);

UI.getCurrent().addWindow(mywindow);]]></programlisting>

		</section>

		<section xml:id="layout.sub-window.scrolling">
			<title>Scrolling Sub-Window Content</title>

            <indexterm xml:id="term.layout.sub-window.scrolling.scrollbars" class="startofrange">
                <primary>scroll bars</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>
                If a sub-window has a fixed or percentual size and its content becomes too
                big to fit in the content area, a scroll bar will appear for the
                particular direction. On the other hand, if the sub-window has undefined
                size in the direction, it will fit the size of the content and never get a
                scroll bar. Scroll bars in sub-windows are handled with regular HTML
                features, namely <literal>overflow: auto</literal> property in CSS.
                <indexterm><primary>overflow</primary></indexterm>
            </para>


            <para>
                <indexterm><primary><interfacename>Scrollable</interfacename></primary></indexterm>

                As <classname>Window</classname> extends <classname>Panel</classname>,
                windows are also <interfacename>Scrollable</interfacename>. Note that the
                interface defines <emphasis>programmatic scrolling</emphasis>, not
                scrolling by the user. Please see <xref linkend="layout.panel"/>.
            </para>

            <indexterm startref="term.layout.sub-window.scrolling.scrollbars" class="endofrange"/>
        </section>

		<section xml:id="layout.sub-window.modal">
			<title>Modal Sub-Windows</title>

			<para>
				A modal window is a sub-window that prevents interaction with the other
				UI. Dialog windows, as illustrated in <xref
				linkend="figure.layout.sub-window.modal"/>, are typical cases of modal
				windows. The advantage of modal windows is limiting the scope of user
				interaction to a sub-task, so changes in application state are more
				limited. The disadvantage of modal windows is that they can restrict
				workflow too much.
			</para>

            <para>
                You can make a sub-window modal with
                <methodname>setModal(true)</methodname>.
            </para>

			<figure xml:id="figure.layout.sub-window.modal">
				<title>Modal Sub-Window</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/subwindow-modal.png"/>
					</imageobject>
					<imageobject role="fo">
						<imagedata scale="90" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/subwindow-modal.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para>
				Depending on the theme, the parent window may be grayed when the modal
				window is open.
			</para>

			<warning>
				<title>Security Warning</title>
				<para>
					Modality of child windows is purely a client-side feature and can be
					circumvented with client-side attack code. You should not trust in the
					modality of child windows in security-critical situations such as
					login windows.
				</para>
			</warning>
		</section>
	</section> <!-- layout.sub-window -->

	<section xml:id="layout.splitpanel">
        <title><classname>HorizontalSplitPanel</classname> and <classname>VerticalSplitPanel</classname></title>
        
        <indexterm xml:id="term.layout.splitpanel.horizontal" class="startofrange">
            <primary><classname>HorizontalSplitPanel</classname></primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm xml:id="term.layout.splitpanel.vertical" class="startofrange">
            <primary><classname>VerticalSplitPanel</classname></primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>
            <classname>HorizontalSplitPanel</classname> and
            <classname>VerticalSplitPanel</classname> are a two-component containers that
            divide the available space into two areas to accomodate the two
            components. <classname>HorizontalSplitPanel</classname> makes the split
            horizontally with a vertical splitter bar, and
            <classname>VerticalSplitPanel</classname> vertically with a horizontal
            splitter bar. The user can drag the bar to adjust its position.
        </para>

        <para>
            You can set the two components with the
            <methodname>setFirstComponent()</methodname> and
            <methodname>setSecondComponent()</methodname> methods, or with the regular
            <methodname>addComponent()</methodname> method.
        </para>

        <book-example eid="layout.splitpanel.basic" style="float: right"></book-example>
        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have a panel to put stuff in
Panel panel = new Panel("Split Panels Inside This Panel");

// Have a horizontal split panel as its content
HorizontalSplitPanel hsplit = new HorizontalSplitPanel();
panel.setContent(hsplit);

// Put a component in the left panel
Tree tree = new Tree("Menu", TreeExample.createTreeContent());
hsplit.setFirstComponent(tree);

// Put a vertical split panel in the right panel
VerticalSplitPanel vsplit = new VerticalSplitPanel();
hsplit.setSecondComponent(vsplit);

// Put other components in the right panel
vsplit.addComponent(new Label("Here's the upper panel"));
vsplit.addComponent(new Label("Here's the lower panel"));]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The result is shown in <xref linkend="figure.splitpanel.basic"/>. Observe that
            the tree is cut horizontally as it can not fit in the layout. If its height
            exceeds the height of the panel, a vertical scroll bar will appear
            automatically. If horizontal scroll bar is necessary, you could put the
            content in a <classname>Panel</classname>, which can have scroll bars in both
            directions.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.splitpanel.basic">
            <title><classname>HorizontalSplitPanel</classname> and <classname>VerticalSplitPanel</classname></title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/splitpanel-example1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            You can set the split position with
            <methodname>setSplitPosition()</methodname>. It accepts any units defined in
            the <classname>Sizeable</classname> interface, with percentual size relative
            to the size of the component.
        </para>

        <book-example eid="layout.splitpanel.splitposition" style="float: right"></book-example>
        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Have a horizontal split panel
HorizontalSplitPanel hsplit = new HorizontalSplitPanel();
hsplit.setFirstComponent(new Label("75% wide panel"));
hsplit.setSecondComponent(new Label("25% wide panel"));

// Set the position of the splitter as percentage
hsplit.setSplitPosition(75, Sizeable.UNITS_PERCENTAGE);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Another version of the <methodname>setSplitPosition()</methodname> method
            allows leaving out the unit, using the same unit as previously. The method
            also has versions take take a boolean parameter,
            <parameter>reverse</parameter>, which allows defining the size of the right or
            bottom panel instead of the left or top panel.
        </para>

        <para>
            The split bar allows the user to adjust the split position by dragging the bar
            with mouse. To lock the split bar, use
            <methodname>setLocked(true)</methodname>. When locked, the move handle in the
            middle of the bar is disabled.
        </para>
        
        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Lock the splitter
hsplit.setLocked(true);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Setting the split position programmatically and locking the split bar is
            illustrated in <xref linkend="figure.component.splitpanel.splitposition"/>.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.component.splitpanel.splitposition">
            <title>A Layout With Nested SplitPanels</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/splitpanel-splitposition.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Notice that the size of a split panel must not be undefined in the split
            direction.
        </para>

		<simplesect condition="web">
			<title>CSS Style Rules</title>

			<programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?>/* For a horizontal SplitPanel. */
.v-splitpanel-horizontal {}
.v-splitpanel-hsplitter {}
.v-splitpanel-hsplitter-locked {}

/* For a vertical SplitPanel. */
.v-splitpanel-vertical {}
.v-splitpanel-vsplitter {}
.v-splitpanel-vsplitter-locked {}

/* The two container panels. */
.v-splitpanel-first-container {}  /* Top or left panel. */
.v-splitpanel-second-container {} /* Bottom or right panel. */</programlisting>

            <para>
                The entire split panel has the style
                <literal>v-splitpanel-horizontal</literal> or
                <literal>v-splitpanel-vertical</literal>, depending on the panel direction. The
                split bar or <emphasis>splitter</emphasis> between the two content panels
                has either the <literal>...-splitter</literal> or
                <literal>...-splitter-locked</literal> style, depending on whether its
                position is locked or not.
            </para>
            
		</simplesect>

        <indexterm startref="term.layout.splitpanel.horizontal" class="endofrange"/>
        <indexterm startref="term.layout.splitpanel.vertical" class="endofrange"/>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet">
        <title><classname>TabSheet</classname></title>
        
        <para>
            The <classname>TabSheet</classname> is a multicomponent container that allows
            switching between the components with "tabs". The tabs are organized as a tab
            bar at the top of the tab sheet. Clicking on a tab opens its contained
            component in the main display area of the layout. If there are more tabs than
            fit in the tab bar, navigation buttons will appear.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.tabsheet.example1">
            <title>A Simple TabSheet Layout</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                   <imagedata smallscale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/tabsheet-example1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.adding">
            <title>Adding Tabs</title>

            <para>
                You add new tabs to a tab sheet with the <methodname>addTab()</methodname>
                method. The simple version of the method takes as its parameter the root
                component of the tab. You can use the root component to retrieve its
                corresponding <classname>Tab</classname> object. Typically, you put a
                layout component as the root component.
            </para>

            <para>
                You can also give the caption and the icon as parameters for the
                <methodname>addTab()</methodname> method. The following example
                demonstrates the creation of a simple tab sheet, where each tab shows a
                different <classname>Label</classname> component. The tabs have an icon,
                which are (in this example) loaded as Java class loader resources from the
                application.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[TabSheet tabsheet = new TabSheet();
layout.addComponent(tabsheet);

// Create the first tab
VerticalLayout tab1 = new VerticalLayout();
tab1.addComponent(new Embedded(null,
        new ThemeResource("img/planets/Mercury.jpg")));
tabsheet.addTab(tab1, "Mercury",
        new ThemeResource("img/planets/Mercury_symbol.png"));

// This tab gets its caption from the component caption
VerticalLayout tab2 = new VerticalLayout();
tab2.addComponent(new Embedded(null,
        new ThemeResource("img/planets/Venus.jpg")));
tab2.setCaption("Venus");
tabsheet.addTab(tab2).setIcon(
        new ThemeResource("img/planets/Venus_symbol.png"));
...]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.tab">
            <title>Tab Objects</title>
        
            <para>
                Each tab in a tab sheet is represented as a <classname>Tab</classname>
                object, which manages the tab caption, icon, and attributes such as hidden
                and visible. You can set the caption with
                <methodname>setCaption()</methodname> and the icon with
                <methodname>setIcon()</methodname>. If the component added with
                <methodname>addTab()</methodname> has a caption or icon, it is used as the
                default for the <classname>Tab</classname> object. However, changing the
                attributes of the root component later does not affect the tab, but you
                must make the setting through the <classname>Tab</classname> object. The
                <methodname>addTab()</methodname> returns the new
                <classname>Tab</classname> object, so you can easily set an attribute
                using the reference.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// Set an attribute using the returned reference
tabsheet.addTab(myTab).setCaption("My Tab");]]></programlisting>

            <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.tab.disabling">
                <title>Disabling and Hiding Tabs</title>

                <para>
                    A tab can be disabled by setting
                    <methodname>setEnabled(false)</methodname> for the
                    <classname>Tab</classname> object, thereby disallowing selecting it.
                </para>

                <para>
                    A tab can be made invisible by setting
                    <methodname>setVisible(false)</methodname> for the
                    <classname>Tab</classname> object. The
                    <methodname>hideTabs()</methodname> method allows hiding the tab bar
                    entirely. This can be useful in tabbed document interfaces (TDI) when
                    there is only one tab.
                </para>

                <figure xml:id="figure.tabsheet.example2" condition="web">
                    <title>A TabSheet with Hidden and Disabled Tabs</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata smallscale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/tabsheet-example2.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.events">
            <title>Tab Change Events</title>

            <para>
                Clicking on a tab selects it. This fires a
                <classname>TabSheet.SelectedTabChangeEvent</classname>, which you can
                handle by implementing the
                <classname>TabSheet.SelectedTabChangeListener</classname> interface. You
                can access the tabsheet of the event with
                <methodname>getTabSheet()</methodname>, and find the new selected tab with
                <methodname>getSelectedTab()</methodname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                You can programmatically select a tab with
                <methodname>setSelectedTab()</methodname>, which also fires the
                <classname>SelectedTabChangeEvent</classname> (beware of recursive
                events). Reselecting the currently selected tab does not fire the event.
            </para>

            <para>
                Notice that when the first tab is added, it is selected and the change
                event is fired, so if you want to catch that, you need to add your
                listener before adding any tabs.
            </para>

            <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.events.dynamic" condition="web">
                <title>Creating Tab Content Dynamically</title>

                <para>
                    In the following example, we create the tabs as empty content layouts, and
                    add the tab content dynamically when a tab is selected:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[TabSheet tabsheet = new TabSheet();

// Create tab content dynamically when tab is selected
tabsheet.addSelectedTabChangeListener(
        new TabSheet.SelectedTabChangeListener() {
    public void selectedTabChange(SelectedTabChangeEvent event) {
        // Find the tabsheet
        TabSheet tabsheet = event.getTabSheet();
        
        // Find the tab (here we know it's a layout)
        Layout tab = (Layout) tabsheet.getSelectedTab();

        // Get the tab caption from the tab object
        String caption = tabsheet.getTab(tab).getCaption();
        
        // Fill the tab content
        tab.removeAllComponents();
        tab.addComponent(new Image(null,
            new ThemeResource("img/planets/"+caption+".jpg")));
    }
});
        
// Have some tabs
String[] tabs = {"Mercury", "Venus", "Earth", "Mars"};
for (String caption: tabs)
    tabsheet.addTab(new VerticalLayout(), caption,
        new ThemeResource("img/planets/"+caption+"_symbol.png"));]]></programlisting>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.closing">
            <title>Enabling and Handling Closing Tabs</title>

            <para>
                You can enable a close button for individual tabs with the
                <literal>closable</literal> property in the
                <classname>TabSheet.Tab</classname> objects.
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[// Enable closing the tab
tabsheet.getTab(tabComponent).setClosable(true);]]></programlisting>

            <figure xml:id="figure.layout.tabsheet.closing">
                <title>TabSheet with Closable Tabs</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/tabsheet-tabclose.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section xml:id="layout.tabsheet.closing.handling">
                <title>Handling Tab Close Events</title>

                <para>
                    You can handle closing tabs by implementing a custom
                    <classname>TabSheet.CloseHandler</classname>. The default
                    implementation simply calls <methodname>removeTab()</methodname> for
                    the tab to be closed, but you can prevent the close by not calling
                    it. This allows, for example, opening a dialog window to confirm the
                    close.
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[tabsheet.setCloseHandler(new CloseHandler() {
    @Override
    public void onTabClose(TabSheet tabsheet,
                           Component tabContent) {
        Tab tab = tabsheet.getTab(tabContent);
        Notification.show("Closing " + tab.getCaption());
        
        // We need to close it explicitly in the handler
        tabsheet.removeTab(tab);
    }
});]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>

		<simplesect condition="web">
			<title>CSS Style Rules</title>

			<programlisting>.v-tabsheet {}
.v-tabsheet-tabs {}
.v-tabsheet-content {}
.v-tabsheet-deco {}
.v-tabsheet-tabcontainer {}
.v-tabsheet-tabsheetpanel {}
.v-tabsheet-hidetabs {}

.v-tabsheet-scroller {}
.v-tabsheet-scrollerPrev {}
.v-tabsheet-scrollerNext {}
.v-tabsheet-scrollerPrev-disabled{}
.v-tabsheet-scrollerNext-disabled{}

.v-tabsheet-tabitem {}
.v-tabsheet-tabitem-selected {}
.v-tabsheet-tabitemcell {}
.v-tabsheet-tabitemcell-first {}

.v-tabsheet-tabs td {}
.v-tabsheet-spacertd {}</programlisting>

            <para>
                The entire tabsheet has the <literal>v-tabsheet</literal> style.
                A tabsheet consists of three main parts: the tabs on the top, the
                main content pane, and decorations around the tabsheet.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The tabs area at the top can be styled with
                <literal>v-tabsheet-tabs</literal>,
                <literal>v-tabsheet-tabcontainer</literal> and
                <literal>v-tabsheet-tabitem*</literal>.
            </para>
            
            <para>
             	The style <literal>v-tabsheet-spacertd</literal> is used for any
             	empty space after the tabs. If the tabsheet has too little space to
             	show all tabs, scroller buttons enable browsing the full tab list.
             	These use the styles <literal>v-tabsheet-scroller*</literal>.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The content area where the tab contents are shown can be styled with
                <literal>v-tabsheet-content</literal>, and the surrounding decoration
                with <literal>v-tabsheet-deco</literal>.
            </para>
		</simplesect>
    </section>
    
	<section xml:id="layout.accordion">
        <title><classname>Accordion</classname></title>

        <para>
            <classname>Accordion</classname> is a multicomponent container similar to
            <classname>TabSheet</classname>, except that the "tabs" are arranged
            vertically. Clicking on a tab opens its contained component in the space
            between the tab and the next one. You can use an
            <classname>Accordion</classname> identically to a
            <classname>TabSheet</classname>, which it actually inherits. See <xref
            linkend="layout.tabsheet"/> for more information.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The following example shows how you can create a simple accordion. As the
            <classname>Accordion</classname> is rather naked alone, we put it inside a
            Panel that acts as its caption and provides it a border.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// Create the Accordion.
Accordion accordion = new Accordion();

// Have it take all space available in the layout.
accordion.setSizeFull();

// Some components to put in the Accordion.
Label l1 = new Label("There are no previously saved actions.");
Label l2 = new Label("There are no saved notes.");
Label l3 = new Label("There are currently no issues.");

// Add the components as tabs in the Accordion.
accordion.addTab(l1, "Saved actions", null);
accordion.addTab(l2, "Notes", null);
accordion.addTab(l3, "Issues", null);

// A container for the Accordion.
Panel panel = new Panel("Tasks");
panel.setWidth("300px");
panel.setHeight("300px");
panel.setContent(accordion);

// Trim its layout to allow the Accordion take all space.
panel.getLayout().setSizeFull();
panel.getLayout().setMargin(false);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            <xref linkend="figure.accordion.example1"/> shows what the example would look
            like with the default theme.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.accordion.example1">
            <title>An Accordion</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/accordion-example1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

		<simplesect condition="web">
			<title>CSS Style Rules</title>

			<programlisting>.v-accordion {}
.v-accordion-item {}
.v-accordion-item-open {}
.v-accordion-item-first {}
.v-accordion-item-caption {}
.v-accordion-item-caption .v-caption {}
.v-accordion-item-content {}</programlisting>

            <para>
                The top-level element of <classname>Accordion</classname> has the
                <literal>v-accordion</literal> style. An <classname>Accordion</classname>
                consists of a sequence of item elements, each of which has a caption
                element (the tab) and a content area element.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The selected item (tab) has also the <literal>v-accordion-open</literal>
                style. The content area is not shown for the closed items.
            </para>
		</simplesect>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="layout.absolutelayout">
		<title><classname>AbsoluteLayout</classname></title>

        <para>
            <classname>AbsoluteLayout</classname> allows placing components in arbitrary
            positions in the layout area. The positions are specified in the
            <methodname>addComponent()</methodname> method with horizontal and vertical
            coordinates relative to an edge of the layout area. The positions can include
            a third depth dimension, the <emphasis>z-index</emphasis>, which specifies
            which components are displayed in front and which behind other components.
        </para>

        <para>
            The positions are specified by a CSS absolute position string, using the
            <literal>left</literal>, <literal>right</literal>, <literal>top</literal>,
            <literal>bottom</literal>, and <literal>z-index</literal> properties known
            from CSS. In the following example, we have a 300 by 150 pixels large layout
            and position a text field 50 pixels from both the left and the top edge:
        </para>

<programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// A 400x250 pixels size layout
AbsoluteLayout layout = new AbsoluteLayout();
layout.setWidth("400px");
layout.setHeight("250px");
        
// A component with coordinates for its top-left corner
TextField text = new TextField("Somewhere someplace");
layout.addComponent(text, "left: 50px; top: 50px;");]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The <literal>left</literal> and <literal>top</literal> specify the distance
            from the left and top edge, respectively. The <literal>right</literal> and
            <literal>bottom</literal> specify the distances from the right and top edge.
        </para>

<programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// At the top-left corner
Button button = new Button( "left: 0px; top: 0px;");
layout.addComponent(button, "left: 0px; top: 0px;");

// At the bottom-right corner
Button buttCorner = new Button( "right: 0px; bottom: 0px;");
layout.addComponent(buttCorner, "right: 0px; bottom: 0px;");

// Relative to the bottom-right corner
Button buttBrRelative = new Button( "right: 50px; bottom: 50px;");
layout.addComponent(buttBrRelative, "right: 50px; bottom: 50px;");

// On the bottom, relative to the left side
Button buttBottom = new Button( "left: 50px; bottom: 0px;");
layout.addComponent(buttBottom, "left: 50px; bottom: 0px;");

// On the right side, up from the bottom
Button buttRight = new Button( "right: 0px; bottom: 100px;");
layout.addComponent(buttRight, "right: 0px; bottom: 100px;");]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The result of the above code examples is shown in <xref linkend="figure.layout.absolutelayout.bottomright"/>.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.absolutelayout.bottomright">
            <title>Components Positioned Relative to Various Edges</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/absolutelayout-bottomright.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            In the above examples, we had components of undefined size and specified the
            positions of components by a single pair of coordinates. The other possibility
            is to specify an area and let the component fill the area by specifying a
            proportinal size for the component, such as
            "<literal>100%</literal>". Normally, you use
            <methodname>setSizeFull()</methodname> to take the entire area given by the
            layout.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Specify an area that a component should fill
Panel panel = new Panel("A Panel filling an area");
panel.setSizeFull(); // Fill the entire given area
layout.addComponent(panel, "left: 25px; right: 50px; "+
                           "top: 100px; bottom: 50px;");]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The result is shown in <xref linkend="figure.layout.absolutelayout.area"/>
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.absolutelayout.area">
            <title>Component Filling an Area Specified by Coordinates</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/absolutelayout-area.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            You can also use proportional coordinates to specify the coordinates:
        </para>

<programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// A panel that takes 30% to 90% horizontally and
// 20% to 80% vertically
Panel panel = new Panel("A Panel");
panel.setSizeFull(); // Fill the specified area
layout.addComponent(panel, "left: 30%; right: 10%;" +
                           "top: 20%; bottom: 20%;");]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The result is shown in <xref linkend="figure.layout.absolutelayout.proportional"/>
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.absolutelayout.proportional">
            <title>Specifying an Area by Proportional Coordinates</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/absolutelayout-proportional.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Drag and drop is very useful for moving the components contained in an
            <classname>AbsoluteLayout</classname>. Check out the example in <xref
            linkend="advanced.dragndrop.drop-on-component"/>.
        </para>

        <simplesect condition="web">
            <title>Styling with CSS</title>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[.v-absolutelayout {}
.v-absolutelayout-wrapper {}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The <classname>AbsoluteLayout</classname> component has
                <literal>v-absolutelayout</literal> root style. Each component in the
                layout is contained within an element that has the
                <literal>v-absolutelayout-wrapper</literal>. The component captions are
                outside the wrapper elements, in a separate element with the usual
                <literal>v-caption</literal> style.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="layout.csslayout">
		<title><classname>CssLayout</classname></title>

        <para>
            <classname>CssLayout</classname> allows strong control over styling of the
            components contained inside the layout. The components are contained in a
            simple DOM structure consisting of <literal>&lt;div&gt;</literal> elements. By
            default, the contained components are laid out horizontally and wrap naturally
            when they reach the width of the layout, but you can control this and most
            other behaviour with CSS. You can also inject custom CSS for each contained
            component. As <classname>CssLayout</classname> has a very simple DOM structure
            and no dynamic rendering logic, relying purely on the built-in rendering logic
            of the browsers, it is the fastest of the layout components.
        </para>

        <para>
            The basic use of <classname>CssLayout</classname> is just like with any other
            layout component:
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[CssLayout layout = new CssLayout();
        
// Component with a layout-managed caption and icon
TextField tf = new TextField("A TextField");
tf.setIcon(new ThemeResource("icons/user.png"));
layout.addComponent(tf);

// Labels are 100% wide by default so must unset width
Label label = new Label("A Label");
label.setWidth(Sizeable.SIZE_UNDEFINED, 0);
layout.addComponent(label);
        
layout.addComponent(new Button("A Button"));]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The result is shown in <xref linkend="figure.layout.csslayout.basic"/>. Notice
            that the default spacing and alignment of the layout is quite crude and CSS
            styling is nearly always needed.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.layout.csslayout.basic">
            <title>Basic Use of <classname>CssLayout</classname></title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/csslayout-basic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            The <literal>display</literal> attribute of <classname>CssLayout</classname>
            is <literal>inline-block</literal> by default, so the components are laid out
            horizontally following another. <classname>CssLayout</classname> has 100%
            width by default. If the components reach the width of the layout, they are
            wrapped to the next "line" just as text would be. If you add a component with
            100% width, it will take an entire line by wrapping before and after the
            component.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="layout.csslayout.injection">
            <title>CSS Injection</title>

            <para>
                Overriding the <methodname>getCss()</methodname> method allows injecting
                custom CSS for each component. The CSS returned by the method is inserted in
                the <parameter>style</parameter> attribute of the
                <literal>&lt;div&gt;</literal> element of the component, so it will override
                any style definitions made in CSS files.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[CssLayout layout = new CssLayout() {
    @Override
    protected String getCss(Component c) {
        if (c instanceof Label) {
            // Color the boxes with random colors
            int rgb = (int) (Math.random()*(1<<24));
            return "background: #" + Integer.toHexString(rgb);
        }
        return null;
    }
};
layout.setWidth("400px"); // Causes to wrap the contents

// Add boxes of various sizes
for (int i=0; i<40; i++) {
    Label box = new Label("&nbsp;", ContentMode.HTML);
    box.addStyleName("flowbox");
    box.setWidth((float) Math.random()*50,
                 Sizeable.UNITS_PIXELS);
    box.setHeight((float) Math.random()*50,
                  Sizeable.UNITS_PIXELS);
    layout.addComponent(box);
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The style name added to the components allows making common styling in a CSS
                file:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[.v-label-flowbox {
  border: thin black solid;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                <xref linkend="figure.layout.csslayout.getcss"/> shows the rendered result.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.layout.csslayout.getcss">
                <title>Use of <methodname>getCss()</methodname> and line wrap</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/csslayout-getcss.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.csslayout.compatibility">
            <title>Browser Compatibility</title>

            <para>
                The stregth of the <classname>CssLayout</classname> is also its
                weakness. Much of the logic behind the other layout components is there to
                give nice default behaviour and to handle the differences in different
                browsers. Some browsers, no need to say which, are notoriously
                incompatible with the CSS standards, so they require a lot of custom
                CSS. You may need to make use of the browser-specific style classes in the
                root element of the application. <!-- TODO: described in <xref
                linkend="advanced.browserinfo"/> --> Some features in the other layouts
                are not even solvable in pure CSS, at least in all browsers.
            </para>
        </section>

        <simplesect xml:id="layout.csslayout.css"> <!-- It is relevant to keep this in the print edition -->
            <title>Styling with CSS</title>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[.v-csslayout {}
.v-csslayout-margin {}
.v-csslayout-container {}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The <classname>CssLayout</classname> component has
                <literal>v-csslayout</literal> root style. The margin element with
                <literal>v-csslayout-margin</literal> style is always enabled. The
                components are contained in an element with
                <literal>v-csslayout-container</literal> style.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, we could style the basic <classname>CssLayout</classname>
                example shown earlier as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[/* Have the caption right of the text box, bottom-aligned */
.csslayoutexample .mylayout .v-csslayout-container {
    direction: rtl;
    line-height: 24px;
    vertical-align: bottom;
}

/* Have some space before and after the caption */
.csslayoutexample .mylayout .v-csslayout-container .v-caption {
    padding-left:  3px;
    padding-right: 10px;
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The example would now be rendered as shown in <xref
                linkend="figure.layout.csslayout.styling"/>.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.layout.csslayout.styling">
                <title>Styling <classname>CssLayout</classname></title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata smallscale="70%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/csslayout-styling.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                Captions and icons that are managed by the layout are contained in an
                element with <literal>v-caption</literal> style. These caption elements
                are contained flat at the same level as the actual component
                elements. This may cause problems with wrapping in
                <literal>inline-block</literal> mode, as wrapping can occur between the
                caption and its corresponding component element just as well as between
                components. Such use case is therefore not feasible.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="layout.settings">
		<title>Layout Formatting</title>

		<para>
			While the formatting of layouts is mainly done with style sheets, just as with
			other components, style sheets are not ideal or even possible to use in some
			situations. For example, CSS does not allow defining the spacing of table
			cells, which is done with the <parameter>cellspacing</parameter> attribute in
			HTML.
		</para>

		<para>
			Moreover, as many layout sizes are calculated dynamically in the Client-Side
			Engine of Vaadin, some CSS settings can fail altogether.
		</para>

		<section xml:id="layout.settings.size">
			<title>Layout Size</title>

			<para>
				The size of a layout component can be specified with the
				<methodname>setWidth()</methodname> and
				<methodname>setHeight()</methodname> methods defined in the
				<classname>Sizeable</classname> interface, just like for any component. It
				can also be undefined, in which case the layout shrinks to fit the
				component(s) inside it. <xref linkend="components.features.sizeable"/>
				gives details on the interface.
			</para>

			<figure xml:id="figure.layout.settings.size.undefined">
				<title><classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> with Undefined vs Defined size</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_size_undefined_vs_defined.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

			<para>
				Many layout components take 100% width by default, while they have the
				height undefined.
			</para>

			<para>
				The sizes of components inside a layout can also be defined as a
				percentage of the space available in the layout, for example with
				<methodname>setWidth("100%");</methodname> or with the (most commonly used
				method) <methodname>setFullSize()</methodname> that sets 100% size in both
				directions. If you use a percentage in a
				<classname>HorizontalLayout</classname>,
				<classname>VerticalLayout</classname>, or
				<classname>GridLayout</classname>, you will also have to set the component
				as <emphasis>expanding</emphasis>, as noted below.
			</para>

			<warning>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>A layout that contains components with percentual size must
                    have a defined size</emphasis>!
                </para>

                <para>
                    If a layout has undefined size and a contained component has, say,
                    100% size, the component will try to fill the space given by the
                    layout, while the layout will shrink to fit the space taken by the
                    component, which is a paradox. This requirement holds for height and
                    width separately. The debug mode allows detecting such invalid cases;
                    see <xref linkend="advanced.debug.hierarchy"/>.
                </para>
			</warning>

			<para>
				For example:
			</para>

			<programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// This takes 100% width but has undefined height.
VerticalLayout layout = new VerticalLayout();

// A button that takes all the space available in the layout.
Button button = new Button("100%x100% button");
button.setSizeFull();
layout.addComponent(button);

// We must set the layout to a defined height vertically, in
// this case 100% of its parent layout, which also must
// not have undefined size.
layout.setHeight("100%");]]></programlisting>

			<para>
				If you have a layout with undefined height, such as
				<classname>VerticalLayout</classname>, in a <classname>UI</classname>,
				<classname>Window</classname>, or <classname>Panel</classname>, and put
				enough content in it so that it extends outside the bottom of the view
				area, scrollbars will appear. If you want your application to use all the
				browser view, nothing more or less, you should use
				<methodname>setFullSize()</methodname> for the root layout.
			</para>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[// Create the UI content
VerticalLayout content = new VerticalLayout();

// Use entire view area
content.setSizeFull();

setContent(content);]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="layout.settings.size.expanding">
            <title>Expanding Components</title>

            <para>
                If you set a <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> to a defined size
                horizontally or a <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> vertically, and
                there is space left over from the contained components, the extra space is
                distributed equally between the component cells. The components are
                aligned within these cells, according to their alignment setting, top left
                by default, as in the example below.
            </para>

            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_defined.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>

            <para>
                Often, you don't want such empty space, but want one or more
                components to take all the leftover space. You need to set such a
                component to 100% size and use
                <methodname>setExpandRatio()</methodname>. If there is just one
                such expanding component in the layout, the ratio parameter is irrelevant.
            </para>
				
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expanding.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>

            <para>
                If you set multiple components as expanding, the expand ratio dictates how
                large proportion of the available space (overall or excess depending on
                whether the components are sized as a percentage or not) each component
                takes. In the example below, the buttons have 1:2:3 ratio for the
                expansion.
            </para>

            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/horizontallayout_width_expand_ratios.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>

            <para>
                <classname>GridLayout</classname> has corresponding method for both of
                its directions, <methodname>setRowExpandRatio()</methodname> and
                <methodname>setColumnExpandRatio()</methodname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                Expansion is dealt in detail in the documentation of the layout
                components that support it. See <xref
					linkend="layout.orderedlayout"/> and <xref
					linkend="layout.gridlayout"/> for details on components
                with relative sizes.
            </para>
        </section>

		<section xml:id="layout.settings.alignment">
			<title>Layout Cell Alignment</title>

            <indexterm xml:id="term.alignment" class="startofrange">
                <primary>Alignment</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm xml:id="term.setcomponentalignment" class="startofrange">
                <primary><methodname>setComponentAlignment()</methodname></primary>
            </indexterm>

			<para>
                When a component in a layout cell has size (width or height) smaller than
                the size of the cell, it will by default be aligned in the top-left corner
                of the cell.

				You can set the alignment with the
				<methodname>setComponentAlignment()</methodname> method. The method takes
				as its parameters the component contained in the cell to be formatted, and
				the horizontal and vertical alignment. The component must have been added
				to the layout before setting the alignment.
			</para>

			<para>
				<xref linkend="figure.layout.settings.alignment"/> illustrates the
				alignment of components within a <classname>GridLayout</classname>.
			</para>

			<figure xml:id="figure.layout.settings.alignment">
				<title>Cell Alignments</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_alignment.png"/>
					</imageobject>
					<imageobject role="fo">
						<imagedata scale="80" smallscale="120" align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_alignment.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

			<para>
                Note that <emphasis>a component with 100% relative size can not be
                aligned</emphasis>, as it will take the entire width or height of the
                cell, in which case alignment is meaningless. This should especially be
                noted with the <classname>Label</classname> component, which has 100%
                default width, and the text alignment <emphasis>within</emphasis> the
                component is separate, defined by the CSS <literal>text-align</literal>
                property.
            </para>

			<para>
				The easiest way to set alignments is to use the constants defined in the
				<classname>Alignment</classname> class. Let us look how the buttons in the
				top row of the above <classname>GridLayout</classname> are aligned with
				constants:
			</para>

			<programlisting language="java"><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[// Create a grid layout
GridLayout grid = new GridLayout(3, 3);

grid.setWidth(400, Sizeable.UNITS_PIXELS);
grid.setHeight(200, Sizeable.UNITS_PIXELS);

Button topleft = new Button("Top Left");
grid.addComponent(topleft, 0, 0);
grid.setComponentAlignment(topleft, Alignment.TOP_LEFT);

Button topcenter = new Button("Top Center");
grid.addComponent(topcenter, 1, 0);
grid.setComponentAlignment(topcenter, Alignment.TOP_CENTER);

Button topright = new Button("Top Right");
grid.addComponent(topright, 2, 0);
grid.setComponentAlignment(topright, Alignment.TOP_RIGHT);
...]]></programlisting>

			<para>
				The following table lists all the <classname>Alignment</classname>
				constants by their respective locations:
			</para>

			<table>
				<title>Alignment Constants</title>
				<tgroup cols="3" align="left">
					<tbody>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>TOP_LEFT</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>TOP_CENTER</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>TOP_RIGHT</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>MIDDLE_LEFT</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>MIDDLE_CENTER</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>MIDDLE_RIGHT</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>BOTTOM_LEFT</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>BOTTOM_CENTER</parameter></entry>
							<entry><parameter>BOTTOM_RIGHT</parameter></entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<para>
				Another way to specify the alignments is to create an
				<classname>Alignment</classname> object and specify the horizontal and
				vertical alignment with separate constants. You can specify either of the
				directions, in which case the other alignment direction is not modified,
				or both with a bitmask operation between the two directions.
			</para>

			<programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[Button middleleft = new Button("Middle Left");
grid.addComponent(middleleft, 0, 1);
grid.setComponentAlignment(middleleft,
          new Alignment(Bits.ALIGNMENT_VERTICAL_CENTER | 
                        Bits.ALIGNMENT_LEFT));

Button middlecenter = new Button("Middle Center");
grid.addComponent(middlecenter, 1, 1);
grid.setComponentAlignment(middlecenter,
          new Alignment(Bits.ALIGNMENT_VERTICAL_CENTER |
                        Bits.ALIGNMENT_HORIZONTAL_CENTER));

Button middleright = new Button("Middle Right");
grid.addComponent(middleright, 2, 1);
grid.setComponentAlignment(middleright,
          new Alignment(Bits.ALIGNMENT_VERTICAL_CENTER |
                        Bits.ALIGNMENT_RIGHT));]]></programlisting>

			<para>
				Obviously, you may combine only one vertical bitmask with one horizontal
				bitmask, though you may leave either one out. The following table lists
				the available alignment bitmask constants:
			</para>

			<table>
				<title>Alignment Bitmasks</title>
				<tgroup cols="2" align="left">
					<tbody>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry morerows="2">Horizontal</entry>
							<entry><parameter>Bits.ALIGNMENT_LEFT</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>Bits.ALIGNMENT_HORIZONTAL_CENTER</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>Bits.ALIGNMENT_RIGHT</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry morerows="2">Vertical</entry>
							<entry><parameter>Bits.ALIGNMENT_TOP</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>Bits.ALIGNMENT_VERTICAL_CENTER</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row valign="top">
							<entry><parameter>Bits.ALIGNMENT_BOTTOM</parameter></entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<para>
				You can determine the current alignment of a component with
				<methodname>getComponentAlignment()</methodname>, which returns an
				<classname>Alignment</classname> object. The class provides a number of
				getter methods for decoding the alignment, which you can also get as a
				bitmask value.
			</para>

            <section xml:id="layout.settings.alignment.size">
                <title>Size of Aligned Components</title>

                <para>
                    You can only align a component that is smaller than its containing
                    cell in the direction of alignment. If a component has 100% width, as
                    many components have by default, horizontal alignment does not have
                    any effect. For example, <classname>Label</classname> is 100% wide by
                    default and can not therefore be horizontally aligned as such. The
                    problem can be hard to notice, as the text inside a
                    <classname>Label</classname> is left-aligned.
                </para>

                <para>
                    You usually need to set either a fixed size, undefined size, or less
                    than a 100% relative size for the component to be aligned - a size
                    that is smaller than the containing layout has.
                </para>

                <para>
                    For example, assuming that a <classname>Label</classname> has short
                    content that is less wide than the containing
                    <classname>VerticalLayout</classname>, you could center it as follows:
                </para>

                <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[VerticalLayout layout = new VerticalLayout(); // 100% default width
Label label = new Label("Hello"); // 100% default width
label.setSizeUndefined();
layout.addComponent(label);
layout.setComponentAlignment(label, Alignment.MIDDLE_CENTER);]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    If you set the size as undefined and the component itself contains
                    components, make sure that the contained components also have either
                    undefined or fixed size. For example, if you set the size of a
                    <classname>Form</classname> as undefined, its containing layout
                    <classname>FormLayout</classname> has 100% default width, which you
                    also need to set as undefined. But then, any components inside the
                    <classname>FormLayout</classname> must have either undefined or fixed
                    size.
                </para>
            </section>

            <indexterm startref="term.alignment" class="endofrange"/>
            <indexterm startref="term.setcomponentalignment" class="endofrange"/>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="layout.settings.spacing">
			<title>Layout Cell Spacing</title>
			
			<para>
				The <classname>VerticalLayout</classname>,
				<classname>HorizontalLayout</classname>, and
				<classname>GridLayout</classname> layouts offer a
				<methodname>setSpacing()</methodname> method to enable spacing between
				the cells of the layout.
			</para>

			<para>
				For example:
			</para>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[VerticalLayout layout = new VerticalLayout();
layout.setSpacing(true);
layout.addComponent(new Button("Component 1"));
layout.addComponent(new Button("Component 2"));
layout.addComponent(new Button("Component 3"));]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The effect of spacing in <classname>VerticalLayout</classname> and
                <classname>HorizontalLayout</classname> is illustrated in <xref
                linkend="figure.layout.spacing"/>.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.layout.spacing">
                <title>Layout Spacings</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_spacing.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata scale="80" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_spacing.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

			<para>
                The exact amount of spacing is defined in CSS. If the default is not
                suitable, you can customize it in a custom theme.
            </para>

            <para>
                In the Valo theme, you can specify the spacing with the
                <varname>$v-layout-spacing-vertical</varname> and
                <varname>$v-layout-spacing-horizontal</varname> parameters, as described
                in <xref linkend="themes.valo.variables"/>. The spacing defaults to the
                <varname>$v-unit-size</varname> measure.
            </para>

            <para>
                When adjusting spacing in other themes, you should note that it is
                implemented in a bit different ways in different layouts. In the ordered
                layouts, it is done with spacer elements, while in the
                <classname>GridLayout</classname> it has special handling. Please see the
                sections on the individual components for more details.
            </para>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="layout.settings.margins">
			<title>Layout Margins</title>

			<para>
				Most layout components do not have any margin around them by default. The
				ordered layouts, as well as <classname>GridLayout</classname>, support
				enabling a margin with <methodname>setMargin()</methodname>. This enables
				CSS classes for each margin in the HTML element of the layout
				component. 
            </para>

            <para>
                In the Valo theme, the margin sizes default to
                <varname>$v-unit-size</varname>. You can customize them with
                <varname>$v-layout-margin-top</varname>, <varname>right</varname>,
                <varname>bottom</varname>, and <varname>left</varname>. See <xref
                linkend="themes.valo.variables"/> for a description of the parameters.
            </para>

            <para>
                To customize the default margins in other themes, you can define each
                margin with the <literal>padding</literal> property in CSS.  You may want
                to have a custom CSS class for the layout component to enable specific
                customization of the margins, as is done in the following with the
                <literal>mymargins</literal> class:
            </para>

			<programlisting>
.<emphasis role="bold">mymargins</emphasis>.v-margin-left   {padding-left:   <emphasis role="bold">10</emphasis>px;}
.<emphasis role="bold">mymargins</emphasis>.v-margin-right  {padding-right:  <emphasis role="bold">20</emphasis>px;}
.<emphasis role="bold">mymargins</emphasis>.v-margin-top    {padding-top:    <emphasis role="bold">40</emphasis>px;}
.<emphasis role="bold">mymargins</emphasis>.v-margin-bottom {padding-bottom: <emphasis role="bold">80</emphasis>px;}</programlisting>

			<para>
				You can enable only specific margins by passing a
				<classname>MarginInfo</classname> to the
				<methodname>setMargin()</methodname>. The margins are specified in
				clockwise order for top, right, bottom, and left margin. The following
				would enable the left and right margins:
			</para>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[layout.setMargin(new MarginInfo(false, true, false, true));]]></programlisting>

			<para>
				The resulting margins are shown in <xref linkend="figure.layout.margin"/>
				below. The two ways produce identical margins.
			</para>

			<figure xml:id="figure.layout.margin">
				<title>Layout Margins</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_margin.png"/>
					</imageobject>
					<imageobject role="fo">
						<imagedata scale="80" smallscale="110" align="center" fileref="img/layout/layout_margin.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</section>
	</section>
		
	<section xml:id="layout.customlayout">
		<title>Custom Layouts</title>
		
		<para>
			While it is possible to create almost any typical layout with the standard layout
			components, it is sometimes best to separate the layout completely from
			code. With the <classname>CustomLayout</classname> component, you can write
			your layout as a template in HTML that provides locations of any contained
			components. The layout template is included in a theme. This separation allows
			the layout to be designed separately from code, for example using WYSIWYG web
			designer tools such as Adobe Dreamweaver.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			A template is a HTML file located under <filename>layouts</filename> folder
			under a theme folder under the <filename>WebContent/VAADIN/themes/</filename>
			folder, for example,
			<filename>WebContent/VAADIN/themes/<emphasis>themename/layouts/mylayout.html</emphasis></filename>. (Notice
			that the root path <filename>WebContent/VAADIN/themes/</filename> for themes
			is fixed.) A template can also be provided dynamically from an
			<classname>InputStream</classname>, as explained below.  A template includes
			<literal>&lt;div&gt;</literal> elements with a <parameter>location</parameter>
			attribute that defines the location identifier. All custom layout HTML-files
			must be saved using UTF-8 character encoding.
		</para>

		<programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?>&lt;table width="100%" height="100%"&gt;
  &lt;tr height="100%"&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      &lt;table align="center"&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td align="right"&gt;User&amp;nbsp;name:&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;<emphasis role="strong">&lt;div location="username"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td align="right"&gt;Password:&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;<emphasis role="strong">&lt;div location="password"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td align="right" colspan="2"&gt;
      <emphasis role="strong">&lt;div location="okbutton"&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</programlisting>

		<para>
			The client-side engine of Vaadin will replace contents of the
			location elements with the components. The components are bound to the
			location elements by the location identifier given to
			<methodname>addComponent()</methodname>, as shown in the example below.
		</para>

		<programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[// Have a Panel where to put the custom layout.
Panel panel = new Panel("Login");
panel.setSizeUndefined();
main.addComponent(panel);

// Create custom layout from "layoutname.html" template.
CustomLayout custom = new CustomLayout("layoutname");
custom.addStyleName("customlayoutexample");

// Use it as the layout of the Panel.
panel.setContent(custom);

// Create a few components and bind them to the location tags
// in the custom layout.
TextField username = new TextField();
custom.addComponent(username, "username");

TextField password = new TextField();
custom.addComponent(password, "password");

Button ok = new Button("Login");
custom.addComponent(ok, "okbutton");]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			The resulting layout is shown below in <xref linkend="figure.layout.customlayout"/>.
		</para>

		<figure xml:id="figure.layout.customlayout">
			<title>Example of a Custom Layout Component</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/layout/customlayout-example1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="100" smallscale="130" align="center" fileref="img/layout/customlayout-example1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>
			You can use <methodname>addComponent()</methodname> also to replace an
			existing component in the location given in the second parameter.
		</para>

		<para>
			In addition to a static template file, you can provide a template dynamically
			with the <classname>CustomLayout</classname> constructor that accepts an
			<classname>InputStream</classname> as the template source. For example:
		</para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[new CustomLayout(new ByteArrayInputStream("<b>Template</b>".getBytes()));]]></programlisting>

		<para>or</para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[new CustomLayout(new FileInputStream(file));]]></programlisting>
	</section>
</chapter>


<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->

