<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="clientside">
	<title>Client-Side Vaadin Development</title>

    <para>
        This chapter gives an overview of the Vaadin client-side framework, its
        architecture, and development tools.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="clientside.overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            As noted in the introduction, Vaadin supports two development models:
            server-side and client-side. Client-side Vaadin code is executed in the web
            browser as JavaScript code. The code is written in Java, like all Vaadin code,
            and then compiled to JavaScript with the <emphasis>Vaadin Client
            Compiler</emphasis>. You can create pure client-side applications and widgets,
            which you can simply load in the browser and use even without a server-side
            application. Going further, you can integrate the client-side widgets with
            their server-side counterpart components using connectors, and hence enable
            using them in server-side Vaadin applications. That is actually how most
            Vaadin add-on components are done.
        </para>

        <para>
            The client-side framework is based on the Google Web Toolkit (GWT), with added
            features and bug fixes. For example, in addition to the basic GWT widgets,
            Vaadin provides the Vaadin-specific implementations of most of the common user
            interface widgets. Vaadin is compatible with GWT to the extent of the basic
            GWT feature set. Vaadin Ltd is a member of the GWT Steering Committee, working
            on the future direction of GWT together with Google and other supporters of
            GWT.
        </para>

        <note>
            <title>Widgets and Components</title>
            <para>
                <indexterm><primary>widget, definition</primary></indexterm>
                
                Google Web Toolkit uses the term <emphasis>widget</emphasis> for user
                interface components. In this book, we use the term widget to refer to
                client-side components, while using the term <emphasis>component</emphasis> in
                a general sense and also in the special sense for server-side components.
            </para>
        </note>

        <para>
            The main idea in server-side Vaadin development is to render the server-side
            components in the browser with the Client-Side Engine. The engine is
            essentially a set of widgets paired with <emphasis>connectors</emphasis> that
            serialize their state and events with the server-side counterpart
            components. The client-side engine is technically called a <emphasis>widget
            set</emphasis>, to describe the fact that it mostly consists of widgets and
            that widget sets can be combined, as described later.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="clientside.installing">
        <title>Installing the Client-Side Development Environment</title>

        <para>
            The installation of the client-side development libraries is described in
            <xref linkend="getting-started"/>. You especially need the
            <filename>vaadin-client</filename> library, which contains the client-side
            Java API, and <filename>vaadin-client-compiler</filename>, which contains the
            Vaadin Client Compiler for compiling Java to JavaScript.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="clientside.module">
        <title>Client-Side Module Descriptor</title>

        <para>
            Client-side Vaadin modules, such as the Vaadin Client-Side Engine (widget set)
            or pure client-side applications, that are to be compiled to JavaScript, are
            defined in a <emphasis>module descriptor</emphasis>
            (<filename>.gwt.xml</filename>) file.
        </para>

        <para>
            When defining a widget set to build the Vaadin client-side engine, the only
            necessary task is to inherit a base widget set. If you are developing a
            regular widget set, you should normally inherit the
            <classname>DefaultWidgetSet</classname>.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE module PUBLIC
  "-//Google Inc.//DTD Google Web Toolkit 1.7.0//EN"
  "http://google-web-toolkit.googlecode.com/svn/tags/1.7.0/distro-source/core/src/gwt-module.dtd">

<module>
    <!-- Inherit the default widget set -->
    <inherits name="com.vaadin.DefaultWidgetSet" />
</module>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            If you are developing a pure client-side application, you should instead
            inherit <classname>com.vaadin.Vaadin</classname>, as described in <xref
            linkend="clientsideapp"/>. In that case, the module descriptor also needs an
            entry-point.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            If you are using the Eclipse IDE, the New Vaadin Widget wizard will
            automatically create the GWT module descriptor. See <xref
                linkend="gwt.eclipse.widget"/> for detailed instructions.
        </para>
        
        <section xml:id="clientside.module.stylesheet">
            <title>Specifying a Stylesheet</title>

            <para>
                A client-side module can include CSS stylesheets. When the module is
                compiled, these stylesheets are copied to the output target. In the module
                descriptor, define a <literal>stylesheet</literal> element.
            </para>


            <para>
                For example, if you are developing a custom widget and want to have a
                default stylesheet for it, you could define it as follows:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[<stylesheet src="mywidget/styles.css"/>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The specified path is relative to the <emphasis>public</emphasis>
                folder under the folder of the module descriptor.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="gwt.module.compilation-limiting">
            <title>Limiting Compilation Targets</title>
                
            <para>
                Compiling widget sets takes considerable time. You can reduce the
                compilation time significantly by compiling the widget sets only for
                your browser, which is useful during development. You can do this by
                setting the <parameter>user.agent</parameter> property in the module
                descriptor.
            </para>
                
            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[<set-property name="user.agent" value="gecko1_8"/>]]></programlisting>
            
            <para>
                The <parameter>value</parameter> attribute should match your browser. The
                browsers supported by GWT depend on the GWT version, below is a list of
                browser identifiers supported by GWT.
            </para>
            
            <table>
                <title>GWT User Agents</title>
                <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                    <thead>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>Identifier</entry>
                            <entry>Name</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>ie6</entry>
                            <entry>Internet Explorer 6</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>ie8</entry>
                            <entry>Internet Explorer 8</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>gecko1_8</entry>
                            <entry>Mozilla Firefox 1.5 and later</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>safari</entry>
                            <entry>Apple Safari and other Webkit-based browsers including Google Chrome</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>opera</entry>
                            <entry>Opera</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row valign="top">
                            <entry>ie9</entry>
                            <entry>Internet Explorer 9</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        
        <para>
            For more information about the GWT Module XML Format, please see Google Web
            Toolkit Developer Guide.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="clientside.compiling">
        <title>Compiling a Client-Side Module</title>

        <para>
            A client-side module, either a widget set or a pure client-side module, must
            be compiled to JavaScript using the Vaadin Client Compiler.
        </para>

        <para>
            As most Vaadin add-ons include widgets, widget set compilation is usually
            needed when using add-ons. In that case, the widget sets from different
            add-ons are compiled into a <emphasis>project widget set</emphasis>, as
            described in <xref linkend="addons"/>. <!-- TODO Provide a link to a proper
            add-on compilation section when one is available. -->
        </para>

        <section xml:id="clientside.compiling.overview">
            <title>Vaadin Compiler Overview</title>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Client Compiler compiles Java to JavaScript. It is provided as
                the <filename>vaadin-client-compiler</filename> JAR, which you can execute
                with the <literal>-jar</literal> parameter for the Java runtime. It
                requires the <filename>vaadin-client</filename> JAR, which contains the
                Vaadin client-side framework.
            </para>

            <para>
                The compiler compiles a <emphasis>client module</emphasis>, which can be
                either a pure client-side module or a Vaadin widget set, that is, the
                Vaadin Client-Side Engine that includes the widgets used in the
                application. The client module is defined with a module descriptor, which
                was described in <xref linkend="clientside.module"/>.
            </para>

            <para>
                The compiler writes the compilation result to a target folder that will
                include the compiled JavaScript with any static resources included in the
                module.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="clientside.compiling.eclipse">
            <title>Compiling in Eclipse</title>

            <para>
                When the Vaadin Plugin is installed in Eclipse, you can simply click the
                <guibutton>Compile Vaadin widgets</guibutton> button in the toolbar. It
                will compile the widget set it finds from the project. If the project has
                multiple widget sets, such as one for custom widgets and another one for
                the project, you need to select the module descriptor of the widget set to
                compile before clicking the button.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="clientside.compiling.ant">
            <title>Compiling with Ant</title>

            <para>
                You can find a script template for compiling widget sets with Ant and Ivy
                at the <link xlink:href="http://vaadin.com/download/">Vaadin download
                page</link>. You can copy the build script to your project and, once
                configured, run it with Ant.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="clientside.compiling.maven">
            <title>Compiling with Maven</title>

            <para>
                You can compile the widget set with the <literal>vaadin:compile</literal>
                goal as follows:
            </para>

            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>mvn</command> <parameter>vaadin:compile</parameter></screen>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="clientside.widget">
        <title>Creating a Custom Widget</title>

        <para>
            Creating a new Vaadin component begins from a client-side widget, which is
            later integrated with a server-side counterpart to enable server-side
            development. In addition, you can also choose to make pure client-side
            widgets, a possibility which we also describe later in this section.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="clientside.widget.simple">
            <title>A Basic Widget</title>

            <para>
                All widgets extend the <classname>Widget</classname> class or some of its
                subclasses. You can extend any core GWT or supplementary Vaadin
                widgets. The basic GWT widget component hierarchy is illustrated in <xref
                linkend="figure.clientside.widgets"/> .
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.clientside.widgets">
                <title>GWT Widget Base Class Hierarchy</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/gwt/gwt-widgets-lo.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata scale="60" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/gwt/gwt-widgets-hi.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                For example, we could extend the <classname>Label</classname> widget to
                display some custom text.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[package com.example.myapp.client;

import com.google.gwt.user.client.ui.Label;

public class MyWidget extends Label {
    public static final String CLASSNAME = "mywidget";

    public MyWidget() {
        setStyleName(CLASSNAME);
        setText("This is MyWidget");
    }
}]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The above example is largely what the Eclipse plugin generates as a widget
                stub. It is a good practice to set a style class for the widget, to allow
                styling it with CSS.
            </para>

            <para>
                The client-side source code <emphasis>must</emphasis> be contained in a
                <filename>client</filename> package under the package of the descriptor
                file, which is covered later.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="clientside.widget.using">
            <title>Using the Widget</title>

            <para>
                You can use a custom widget just like you would use any widget.
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[public class MyEntryPoint implements EntryPoint {
    @Override
    public void onModuleLoad() {
        // Use the custom widget
        final MyWidget mywidget = new MyWidget();
        RootPanel.get().add(mywidget);
    }
}]]></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="clientside.debugging">
        <title>Debugging Client-Side Code</title>
        
        <para>
            Vaadin includes two application execution modes for debugging client-side
            code. The Development Mode compiles the client-side module and runs it in the
            browser, using a browser plugin to communicate with the debugger. The
            "SuperDevMode" allows debugging the code right in the browser, without even
            need to install a plugin.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="clientside.debugging.devmode">
            <title>Launching Development Mode</title>

            <para>
                The Development Mode compiles the client-side module (or widget set),
                launches the application in the browser, and allows debugging the
                client-side code in Eclipse. You can launch the Development Mode by
                running the <classname>com.google.gwt.dev.DevMode</classname> class. It
                requires some parameters, as described later.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse can create a launch configuration for the
                Development Mode. In the Vaadin section of project properties, click the
                <guibutton>Create development mode launch</guibutton> button. This creates
                a new launch configuration in the project. You can edit the launch
                configuration in <menuchoice><guimenu>Run</guimenu><guimenuitem>Run
                Configurations</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. 
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[-noserver -war WebContent/VAADIN/widgetsets com.example.myproject.widgetset.MyWidgetSet -startupUrl http://localhost:8080/myproject -bindAddress 127.0.0.1]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The parameters are as follows:
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><parameter>-noserver</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        Normally, the Development Mode launches its own server for hosting
                        the content. As we are developing the application under an IDE
                        that deploys it to a server, we can disable the Development Mode
                        server with this option.
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><parameter>-war</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        Specifies path to the location where the JavaScript is to be
                        compiled. When developing pure client-side widgets, this could be
                        the <filename>WebContent</filename> folder, or some other
                        folder. When compiling widget sets, it must be
                        <filename>WebContent/VAADIN/widgetsets</filename>.
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><parameter>-startupUrl</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        Specifies the address of the loader page for the application. For
                        server-side Vaadin applications, this should be the path to the
                        Vaadin application servlet, as defined in the deployment. For pure
                        client-side widgets, it should be the page where the application is
                        included.
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><parameter>-bindAddress</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        This is the IP address of the host in which the Development Mode
                        runs. Normally it is the local host, that is,
                        <literal>127.0.0.1</literal>.
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="clientside.debugging.superdevmode">
            <title>Launching SuperDevMode</title>

            <para>
                The SuperDevMode is much like the regular Development Mode, except that it
                does not require a browser plugin. Compilation from Java to JavaScript is
                done incrementally, reducing the compilation time significantly. It also
                allows debugging JavaScript and even Java right in the browser (currently
                only supported in Chrome).
            </para>

            <para>
                You can enable SuperDevMode as follows:
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        You need to set a redirect property in the
                        <filename>.gwt.xml</filename> module descriptor as follows:
                    </para>

                    <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[<set-configuration-property name="devModeRedirectEnabled" value="true" />]]></programlisting>

                    <para>
                        In addition, you need the <literal>xsiframe</literal> linker. It
                        is included in the
                        <classname>com.vaadin.DefaultWidgetSet</classname> as
                        well as in the <classname>com.vaadin.Vaadin</classname>
                        module. Otherwise, you need to include it with:
                    </para>

                    <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[<add-linker name="xsiframe" />]]></programlisting>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    Compile the module (that is, the widget set), for example by clicking
                    the button in Eclipse.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If you are using Eclipse, create a launch configuration for the
                        SuperDevMode by clicking the <guibutton>Create SuperDevMode
                        launch</guibutton> in the <guilabel>Vaadin</guilabel> section of
                        the project properties.
                    </para>

                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            The main class to execute should be
                            <classname>com.google.gwt.dev.codeserver.CodeServer</classname>.
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            The application takes the fully-qualified class name of the
                            module (or widget set) as parameter, for example,
                            <classname>com.example.myproject.widgetset.MyprojectWidgetset</classname>.
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            Add project sources to the class path of the launch if they
                            are not in the project class path.
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>
                The above configuration only needs to be done once to enable the
                SuperDevMode. After that, you can launch the mode as follows:
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    Run the SuperDevMode Code Server with the launch configuration that
                    you created above. This perfoms the initial compilation of your module
                    or widget set.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Launch the servlet container for your application, for example, Tomcat.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Open your browser with the application URL and add
                    <literal>?superdevmode</literal> parameter to the URL (see the notice
                    below if you are not extending
                    <classname>DefaultWidgetSet</classname>). This recompiles the code,
                    after which the page is reloaded with the SuperDevMode. You can also
                    use the <literal>?debug</literal> parameter and then click the
                    <guibutton>SDev</guibutton> button in the debug console.
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>
                If you make changes to the client-side code and refresh the page in the
                browser, the client-side is recompiled and you see the results
                immediately.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Step 3 above assumes that you extend
                <classname>DefaultWidgetSet</classname> in your module. If that is not the
                case, you need to add the following at the start of the
                <methodname>onModuleLoad()</methodname> method of the module:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[if (SuperDevMode.enableBasedOnParameter()) { return; }]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Alternatively, you can use the bookmarklets provided by the code
                server. Go to <uri>http://localhost:9876/</uri> and drag the bookmarklets
                "<guilabel>Dev Mode On</guilabel>" and "<guilabel>Dev Mode Off</guilabel>"
                to the bookmarks bar
            </para>

            <section xml:id="clientside.debugging.superdevmode.java">
                <title>Debugging Java Code in Chrome</title>

                <para>
                    Chrome supports source maps, which allow debugging Java source code
                    from which the JavaScript was compiled.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Open the Chrome Inspector by right-clicking and selecting
                    <guilabel>Inspect Element</guilabel>. Click the settings icon in the
                    lower corner of the window and check the
                    <menuchoice><guimenu>Scripts</guimenu><guimenuitem>Enable source
                    maps</guimenuitem></menuchoice> option. Refresh the page with the
                    Inspector open, and you will see Java code instead of JavaScript in
                    the scripts tab.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->

