<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="sqlcontainer">
    <title>Vaadin SQLContainer</title>

    <para>
        Vaadin SQLContainer is a container implementation that allows easy and
        customizable access to data stored in various SQL-speaking databases.
    </para>

    <para>
        SQLContainer supports two types of database access. Using
        <classname>TableQuery</classname>, the pre-made query generators will enable
        fetching, updating, and inserting data directly from the container into a database
        table - automatically, whereas <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> allows the
        developer to use their own, probably more complex query for fetching data and
        their own optional implementations for writing, filtering and sorting support -
        item and property handling as well as lazy loading will still be handled
        automatically.
    </para>

    <para>
        In addition to the customizable database connection options, SQLContainer also
        extends the Vaadin <classname>Container</classname> interface to implement more
        advanced and more database-oriented filtering rules. Finally, the add-on also
        offers connection pool implementations for JDBC connection pooling and JEE
        connection pooling, as well as integrated transaction support; auto-commit mode is
        also provided.
    </para>

    <para>
        The purpose of this section is to briefly explain the architecture and some of the
        inner workings of SQLContainer. It will also give the readers some examples on how
        to use SQLContainer in their own applications. The requirements, limitations and
        further development ideas are also discussed.
    </para>

    <para>
        SQLContainer is available from the Vaadin Directory under the same unrestrictive
        Apache License 2.0 as the Vaadin Framework itself.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.architecture">
        <title>Architecture</title>

        <para>
            The architecture of SQLContainer is relatively
            simple. <classname>SQLContainer</classname> is the class implementing the
            Vaadin <classname>Container</classname> interfaces and providing access to
            most of the functionality of this add-on. The standard Vaadin
            <classname>Property</classname> and <classname>Item</classname> interfaces
            have been implementd as the <classname>ColumnProperty</classname> and
            <classname>RowItem</classname> classes. Item IDs are represented by
            <classname>RowId</classname> and <classname>TemporaryRowId</classname>
            classes. The <classname>RowId</classname> class is built based on the primary
            key columns of the connected database table or query result.
        </para>

        <para>
            In the <package>connection</package> package, the
            <classname>JDBCConnectionPool</classname> interface defines the requirements
            for a connection pool implementation. Two implementations of this interface
            are provided: <classname>SimpleJDBCConnectionPool</classname> provides a
            simple yet very usable implementation to pool and access JDBC
            connections. <classname>J2EEConnectionPool</classname> provides means to
            access J2EE DataSources.
        </para>

        <para>
            The <package>query</package> package contains the
            <classname>QueryDelegate</classname> interface, which defines everything the
            SQLContainer needs to enable reading and writing data to and from a
            database. As discussed earlier, two implementations of this interface are
            provided: <classname>TableQuery</classname> for automatic read-write support
            for a database table, and <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> for customizing
            the query, sorting, filtering and writing; this is done by implementing
            relevant methods of the <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname>
            interface.
        </para>

        <para>
            The <package>query</package> package also contains
            <classname>Filter</classname> and <classname>OrderBy</classname> classes which
            have been written to provide an alternative to the standard Vaadin container
            filtering and make sorting non-String properties a bit more user friendly.
        </para>

        <para>
            Finally, the <package>generator</package> package contains a
            <classname>SQLGenerator</classname> interface, which defines the kind of
            queries that are required by the <classname>TableQuery</classname> class. The
            provided implementations include support for HSQLDB, MySQL, PostgreSQL
            (<classname>DefaultSQLGenerator</classname>), Oracle
            (<classname>OracleGenerator</classname>) and Microsoft SQL Server
            (<classname>MSSQLGenerator</classname>). A new or modified implementations may
            be provided to gain compatibility with older versions or other database
            servers.
        </para>

            <!-- para>
                A class diagram of SQLContainer and its supporting classes as well as
                connections to Vaadin interfaces is provided in Figure 1 TODO
                . Note that not every method is shown in the diagram due to space
                constraints.
            </para -->

            <!-- TODO FIGURE! -->
        
        <para>
            For further details, please refer to the SQLContainer API documentation.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.getting-started">
        <title>Getting Started with SQLContainer</title>

        <para>
            Getting development going with the SQLContainer is easy and quite
            straight-forward. The purpose of this section is to describe how to create the
            required resources and how to fetch data from and write data to a database
            table attached to the container.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.getting-started.connection-pool">
            <title>Creating a connection pool</title>

            <para>
                First, we need to create a connection pool to allow the SQLContainer to
                connect to a database. Here we will use the
                <classname>SimpleJDBCConnectionPool</classname>, which is a basic
                implementation of connection pooling with JDBC data sources. In the
                following code, we create a connection pool that uses the HSQLDB driver
                together with an in-memory database. The initial amount of connections is
                2 and the maximum amount is set at 5. Note that the database driver,
                connection url, username, and password parameters will vary depending on
                the database you are using.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[JDBCConnectionPool pool = new SimpleJDBCConnectionPool(
        "org.hsqldb.jdbc.JDBCDriver",
        "jdbc:hsqldb:mem:sqlcontainer", "SA", "", 2, 5);]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.getting-started.query-delegate">
            <title>Creating the <classname>TableQuery</classname> Query Delegate</title>

            <para>
                After the connection pool is created, we'll need a query delegate for the
                SQLContainer. The simplest way to create one is by using the built-in
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> class. The
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> delegate provides access to a defined
                database table and supports reading and writing data out-of-the-box. The
                primary key(s) of the table may be anything that the database engine
                supports, and are found automatically by querying the database when a new
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> is instantiated. We create the
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> with the following statement:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[TableQuery tq = new TableQuery("tablename", connectionPool);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                In order to allow writes from several user sessions concurrently, we must
                set a version column to the <classname>TableQuery</classname> as well. The
                version column is an integer- or timestamp-typed column which will either
                be incremented or set to the current time on each modification of the
                row. <classname>TableQuery</classname> assumes that the database will take
                care of updating the version column; it just makes sure the column value
                is correct before updating a row. If another user has changed the row and
                the version number in the database does not match the version number in
                memory, an <classname>OptimisticLockException</classname> is thrown and
                you can recover by refreshing the container and allow the user to merge
                the data. The following code will set the version column:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[tq.setVersionColumn("OPTLOCK");]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.getting-started.container-creation">
            <title>Creating the Container</title>
            
            <para>
                Finally, we may create the container itself. This is as simple as stating:
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[SQLContainer container = new SQLContainer(tq);]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                After this statement, the <classname>SQLContainer</classname> is connected
                to the table tablename and is ready to use for example as a data source
                for a Vaadin <classname>Table</classname> or a Vaadin
                <classname>Form</classname>.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.filteringsorting">
        <title>Filtering and Sorting</title>

        <para>
            Filtering and sorting the items contained in an SQLContainer is, by design,
            always performed in the database. In practice this means that whenever the
            filtering or sorting rules are modified, at least some amount of database
            communication will take place (the minimum is to fetch the updated row count
            using the new filtering/sorting rules).
        </para>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.filteringsorting.filtering">
            <title>Filtering</title>

            <para>
                Filtering is performed using the filtering API in Vaadin, which allows for
                very complex filtering to be easily applied. More information about the
                filtering API can be found in <xref
                linkend="datamodel.container.filtered"/>.
            </para>

            <para>
                In addition to the filters provided by Vaadin, SQLContainer also
                implements the <classname>Like</classname> filter as well as the
                <classname>Between</classname> filter. Both of these map to the equally
                named WHERE-operators in SQL. The filters can also be applied on items
                that reside in memory, for example, new items that have not yet been
                stored in the database or rows that have been loaded and updated, but not
                yet stored.
            </para>

            <para>
                The following is an example of the types of complex filtering that are
                possible with the new filtering API. We want to find all people named Paul
                Johnson that are either younger than 18 years or older than 65 years and
                all Johnsons whose first name starts with the letter "A":
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[mySQLContainer.addContainerFilter(
    new Or(new And(new Equal("NAME", "Paul"),
                   new Or(new Less("AGE", 18),
                          new Greater("AGE", 65))),
           new Like("NAME", "A%")));
mySQLContainer.addContainerFilter(
    new Equal("LASTNAME", "Johnson"));]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                This will produce the following WHERE clause:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[WHERE (("NAME" = "Paul" AND ("AGE" < 18 OR "AGE" > 65)) OR "NAME" LIKE "A%") AND "LASTNAME" = "Johnson"]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.filteringsorting.sorting">
            <title>Sorting</title>

            <para>
                Sorting can be performed using standard Vaadin, that is, using the sort
                method from the <classname>Container.Sortable</classname> interface. The
                <parameter>propertyId</parameter> parameter refers to column names.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[public void sort(Object[] propertyId, boolean[] ascending)]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                In addition to the standard method, it is also possible to directly add an
                <classname>OrderBy</classname> to the container via the
                <methodname>addOrderBy()</methodname> method. This enables the developer
                to insert sorters one by one without providing the whole array of them at
                once.
            </para>

            <para>
                All sorting rules can be cleared by calling the sort method with null or
                an empty array as the first argument.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.editing">
        <title>Editing</title>

        <para>
            Editing the items (<classname>RowItem</classname>s) of SQLContainer can be
            done similarly to editing the items of any Vaadin
            container. <classname>ColumnProperties</classname> of a
            <classname>RowItem</classname> will automatically notify SQLContainer to make
            sure that changes to the items are recorded and will be applied to the
            database immediately or on commit, depending on the state of the auto-commit
            mode.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.editing.adding">
            <title>Adding items</title>

            <para>
                Adding items to an <classname>SQLContainer</classname> object can only be
                done via the <methodname>addItem()</methodname> method. This method will
                create a new <classname>Item</classname> based on the connected database
                table column properties. The new item will either be buffered by the
                container or committed to the database through the query delegate
                depending on whether the auto commit mode (see the next section) has been
                enabled.
            </para>

            <para>
                When an item is added to the container it is impossible to precisely know
                what the primary keys of the row will be, or will the row insertion
                succeed at all. This is why the SQLContainer will assign an instance of
                <classname>TemporaryRowId</classname> as a <classname>RowId</classname>
                for the new item. We will later describe how to fetch the actual key after
                the row insertion has succeeded.
            </para>

            <para>
                If auto-commit mode is enabled in the <classname>SQLContainer</classname>,
                the <methodname>addItem()</methodname> methot will return the final
                <classname>RowId</classname> of the new item.
                </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.editing.fetching">
            <title>Fetching generated row keys</title>

            <para>
                Since it is a common need to fetch the generated key of a row right after
                insertion, a listener/notifier has been added into the
                <classname>QueryDelegate</classname> interface. Currently only the
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> class implements the
                <classname>RowIdChangeNotifier</classname> interface, and thus can notify
                interested objects of changed row IDs. The events fill be fired after
                <methodname>commit()</methodname> in <classname>TableQuery</classname> has
                finished; this method is called by <classname>SQLContainer</classname>
                when necessary.
            </para>

            <para>
                To receive updates on the row IDs, you might use the following code
                (assuming container is an instance of
                <classname>SQLContainer</classname>). Note that these events are not fired
                if auto commit mode is enabled.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[app.getDbHelp().getCityContainer().addListener(
    new QueryDelegate.RowIdChangeListener() {
        public void rowIdChange(RowIdChangeEvent event) {
            System.err.println("Old ID: " + event.getOldRowId());
            System.err.println("New ID: " + event.getNewRowId());
        }
    });]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.editing.version-column">
            <title>Version column requirement</title>

            <para>
                If you are using the <classname>TableQuery</classname> class as the query
                delegate to the <classname>SQLContainer</classname> and need to enable
                write support, there is an enforced requirement of specifying a version
                column name to the <classname>TableQuery</classname> instance. The column
                name can be set to the <classname>TableQuery</classname> using the
                following statement:
            </para>
                        
            <programlisting><![CDATA[tq.setVersionColumn("OPTLOCK");]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The version column is preferrably an integer or timestamp typed column in
                the table that is attached to the <classname>TableQuery</classname>. This
                column will be used for optimistic locking; before a row modification the
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> will check before that the version
                column value is the same as it was when the data was read into the
                container. This should ensure that no one has modified the row inbetween
                the current user's reads and writes.
            </para>

            <para>
                Note! <classname>TableQuery</classname> assumes that the database will
                take care of updating the version column by either using an actual
                <literal>VERSION</literal> column (if supported by the database in
                question) or by a trigger or a similar mechanism.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you are certain that you do not need optimistic locking, but do want to
                enable write support, you may point the version column to, for example, a
                primary key column of the table.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.editing.autocommit">
            <title>Auto-commit mode</title>

            <para>
                <classname>SQLContainer</classname> is by default in transaction mode,
                which means that actions that edit, add or remove items are recorded
                internally by the container. These actions can be either committed to the
                database by calling <methodname>commit()</methodname> or discarded by
                calling <methodname>rollback()</methodname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                The container can also be set to auto-commit mode. When this mode is
                enabled, all changes will be committed to the database immediately. To
                enable or disable the auto-commit mode, call the following method:
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public void setAutoCommit(boolean autoCommitEnabled)]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                It is recommended to leave the auto-commit mode disabled, as it ensures
                that the changes can be rolled back if any problems are noticed within the
                container items. Using the auto-commit mode will also lead to failure in
                item addition if the database table contains non-nullable columns.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.editing.modified-state">
            <title>Modified state</title>

            <para>
                When used in the transaction mode it may be useful to determine whether
                the contents of the <classname>SQLContainer</classname> have been modified
                or not. For this purpose the container provides an
                <methodname>isModified()</methodname> method, which will tell the state of
                the container to the developer. This method will return true if any items
                have been added to or removed from the container, as well as if any value
                of an existing item has been modified.
            </para>

            <para>
                Additionally, each <classname>RowItem</classname> and each
                <classname>ColumnProperty</classname> have
                <methodname>isModified()</methodname> methods to allow for a more detailed
                view over the modification status. Do note that the modification statuses
                of <classname>RowItem</classname> and
                <classname>ColumnProperty</classname> objects only depend on whether or
                not the actual <classname>Property</classname> values have been
                modified. That is, they do not reflect situations where the whole
                <classname>RowItem</classname> has been marked for removal or has just
                been added to the container.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.caching">
        <title>Caching, Paging and Refreshing</title>

        <para>
            To decrease the amount of queries made to the database, SQLContainer uses
            internal caching for database contents. The caching is implemented with a
            size-limited <classname>LinkedHashMap</classname> containing a mapping from
            <classname>RowId</classname>s to <classname>RowItem</classname>s. Typically
            developers do not need to modify caching options, although some fine-tuning
            can be done if required.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.caching.container-size">
            <title>Container Size</title>

            <para>
                The <classname>SQLContainer</classname> keeps continuously checking the
                amount of rows in the connected database table in order to detect external
                addition or removal of rows. By default, the table row count is assumed to
                remain valid for 10 seconds. This value can be altered from code; with
                <methodname>setSizeValidMilliSeconds()</methodname> in
                <classname>SQLContainer</classname>.
            </para>

            <para>
                If the size validity time has expired, the row count will be automatically
                updated on:
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>A call to <methodname>getItemIds()</methodname> method</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>A call to <methodname>size()</methodname> method</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Some calls to <methodname>indexOfId(Object itemId)</methodname> method</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>A call to <methodname>firstItemId()</methodname> method</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>When the container is fetching a set of rows to the item cache (lazy loading)</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.caching.page-length">
            <title>Page Length and Cache Size</title>

            <para>
                The page length of the <classname>SQLContainer</classname> dictates the
                amount of rows fetched from the database in one query. The default value
                is 100, and it can be modified with the
                <methodname>setPageLength()</methodname> method. To avoid constant queries
                it is recommended to set the page length value to at least 5 times the
                amount of rows displayed in a Vaadin <classname>Table</classname>;
                obviously, this is also dependent on the cache ratio set for the
                <classname>Table</classname> component.
            </para>

            <para>
                The size of the internal item cache of the
                <classname>SQLContainer</classname> is calculated by multiplying the page
                lenght with the cache ratio set for the container. The cache ratio can
                only be set from the code, and the default value for it is 2. Hence with
                the default page length of 100 the internal cache size becomes 200
                items. This should be enough even for larger <classname>Table</classname>s
                while ensuring that no huge amounts of memory will be used on the cache.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.caching.refreshing">
            <title>Refreshing the Container</title>

            <para>
                Normally, the <classname>SQLContainer</classname> will handle refreshing
                automatically when required. However, there may be situations where an
                implicit refresh is needed, for example, to make sure that the version
                column is up-to-date prior to opening the item for editing in a form. For
                this purpose a <methodname>refresh()</methodname> method is provided. This
                method simply clears all caches, resets the current item fetching offset
                and sets the container size dirty. Any item-related call after this will
                inevitably result into row count and item cache update.
            </para>

            <para>
                <emphasis>Note that a call to the refresh method will not affect or reset
                the following properties of the container:</emphasis>
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>The <classname>QueryDelegate</classname> of the container</listitem>
                <listitem>Auto-commit mode</listitem>
                <listitem>Page length</listitem>
                <listitem>Filters</listitem>
                <listitem>Sorting</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.caching.flush-notification">
            <title>Cache Flush Notification Mechanism</title>

            <para>
                Cache usage with databases in multiuser applications always results in
                some kind of a compromise between the amount of queries we want to execute
                on the database and the amount of memory we want to use on caching the
                data; and most importantly, risking the cached data becoming stale.
            </para>

            <para>
                SQLContainer provides an experimental remedy to this problem by
                implementing a simple cache flush notification mechanism. Due to its
                nature these notifications are disabled by default but can be easily
                enabled for a container instance by calling
                <methodname>enableCacheFlushNotifications()</methodname> at any time
                during the lifetime of the container.
            </para>

            <para>
                The notification mechanism functions by storing a weak reference to all
                registered containers in a static list structure. To minimize the risk of
                memory leaks and to avoid unlimited growing of the reference list, dead
                weak references are collected to a reference queue and removed from the
                list every time a <classname>SQLContainer</classname> is added to the
                notification reference list or a container calls the notification method.
            </para>

            <para>
                When a <classname>SQLContainer</classname> has its cache notifications set
                enabled, it will call the static
                <methodname>notifyOfCacheFlush()</methodname> method giving itself as a
                parameter. This method will compare the notifier-container to all the
                others present in the reference list. To fire a cache flush event, the
                target container must have the same type of
                <classname>QueryDelegate</classname> (either
                <classname>TableQuery</classname> or <classname>FreeformQuery</classname>)
                and the table name or query string must match with the container that
                fired the notification. If a match is found the
                <methodname>refresh()</methodname> method of the matching container is
                called, resulting in cache flushing in the target container.
            </para>

            <para>
                <emphasis>Note: Standard Vaadin issues apply; even if the
                <classname>SQLContainer</classname> is refreshed on the server side, the
                changes will not be reflected to the UI until a server round-trip is
                performed, or unless a push mechanism is used.</emphasis>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.referencing">
        <title>Referencing Another SQLContainer</title>

        <para>
            When developing a database-connected application, there is usually a need to
            retrieve data related to one table from one or more other tables. In most
            cases, this relation is achieved with a foreign key reference, where a column
            of the first table contains a primary key or candidate key of a row in another
            table.
        </para>

        <para>
            SQLContainer offers limited support for this kind of referencing relation,
            although all referencing is currently done on the Java side so no
            constraints need to be made in the database. A new reference can be
            created by calling the following method:
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[public void addReference(SQLContainer refdCont,
                         String refingCol, String refdCol);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            This method should be called on the source container of the reference. The
            target container should be given as the first parameter. The
            <parameter>refingCol</parameter> is the name of the 'foreign key' column in
            the source container, and the <parameter>refdCol</parameter> is the name of
            the referenced key column in the target container.
        </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis>Note: For any <classname>SQLContainer</classname>, all the
            referenced target containers must be different. You can not reference the same
            container from the same source twice.</emphasis>
        </para>

        <para>
            Handling the referenced item can be done through the three provided set/get
            methods, and the reference can be completely removed with the
            <methodname>removeReference()</methodname> method. Signatures of these methods
            are listed below:
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 70% ?><![CDATA[public boolean setReferencedItem(Object itemId,
        Object refdItemId, SQLContainer refdCont)
public Object getReferencedItemId(Object itemId,
                                  SQLContainer refdCont)
public Item getReferencedItem(Object itemId,
                              SQLContainer refdCont)
public boolean removeReference(SQLContainer refdCont)]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The setter method should be given three parameters:
            <parameter>itemId</parameter> is the ID of the referencing item (from the
            source container), <parameter>refdItemId</parameter> is the referenced
            <parameter>itemID</parameter> (from the target container) and
            <parameter>refdCont</parameter> is a reference to the target container that
            identifies the reference. This method returns true if the setting of the
            referenced item was successful. After setting the referenced item you must
            normally call <methodname>commit()</methodname> on the source container to
            persist the changes to the database.
        </para>

        <para>
            The <methodname>getReferencedItemId()</methodname> method will return the item
            ID of the referenced item. As parameters this method needs the item ID of the
            referencing item and a reference to the target container as an
            identifier. <classname>SQLContainer</classname> also provides a convenience
            method <methodname>getReferencedItem()</methodname>, which directly returns
            the referenced item from the target container.
        </para>

        <para>
            Finally, the referencing can be removed from the source container by calling
            the <methodname>removeReference()</methodname> method with the target
            container as parameter. Note that this does not actually change anything in
            the database; it merely removes the logical relation that exists only on the
            Java-side.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.freeform">
        <title>Making Freeform Queries</title>

        <para>
            In most cases, the provided <classname>TableQuery</classname> will be enough
            to allow a developer to gain effortless access to an SQL data source. However
            there may arise situations when a more complex query with, for example, join
            expressions is needed. Or perhaps you need to redefine how the writing or
            filtering should be done. The <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> query
            delegate is provided for this exact purpose. Out of the box the
            <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> supports read-only access to a database,
            but it can be extended to allow writing also.
        </para>

        <simplesect xml:id="sqlcontainer.freeform.getting-started">
            <title>Getting started</title>

            <para>
                Getting started with the <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> may be done
                as shown in the following. The connection pool initialization is similar
                to the <classname>TableQuery</classname> example so it is omitted
                here. Note that the name(s) of the primary key column(s) must be provided
                to the <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> manually. This is required
                because depending on the query the result set may or may not contain data
                about primary key columns. In this example, there is one primary key
                column with a name 'ID'.
            </para>

            <programlisting><![CDATA[FreeformQuery query = new FreeformQuery(
        "SELECT * FROM SAMPLE", pool, "ID");
SQLContainer container = new SQLContainer(query);]]></programlisting>
            </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="sqlcontainer.freeform.limitations">
            <title>Limitations</title>

            <para>
                While this looks just as easy as with the
                <classname>TableQuery</classname>, do note that there are some important
                caveats here. Using <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> like this
                (without providing <classname>FreeformQueryDelegate</classname> or
                <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname> implementation) it can
                only be used as a read-only window to the resultset of the
                query. Additionally filtering, sorting and lazy loading features will not
                be supported, and the row count will be fetched in quite an inefficient
                manner. Bearing these limitations in mind, it becomes quite obvious that
                the developer is in reality meant to implement the
                <classname>FreeformQueryDelegate</classname> or
                <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname> interface.
            </para>

            <para>
                The <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname> interface is an
                extension of the <classname>FreeformQueryDelegate</classname> interface,
                which returns <classname>StatementHelper</classname> objects instead of
                pure query <classname>String</classname>s. This enables the developer to
                use prepared statetemens instead of regular statements. It is highly
                recommended to use the <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname> in
                all implementations. From this chapter onwards, we will only refer to the
                <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname> in cases where
                <classname>FreeformQueryDelegate</classname> could also be applied.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
                
        <simplesect xml:id="sqlcontainer.freeform.custom-freeformstatementdelegate">
            <title>Creating your own <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname></title>

            <para>
                To create your own delegate for <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> you
                must implement some or all of the methods from the
                <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname> interface, depending on
                which ones your use case requires. The interface contains eight methods
                which are shown below. For more detailed requirements, see the JavaDoc
                documentation of the interface.
            </para>

            <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[// Read-only queries
public StatementHelper getCountStatement()
public StatementHelper getQueryStatement(int offset, int limit)
public StatementHelper getContainsRowQueryStatement(Object... keys)

// Filtering and sorting
public void setFilters(List<Filter> filters)
public void setFilters(List<Filter> filters,
                       FilteringMode filteringMode)
public void setOrderBy(List<OrderBy> orderBys)

// Write support
public int storeRow(Connection conn, RowItem row)
public boolean removeRow(Connection conn, RowItem row)]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                A simple demo implementation of this interface can be found in the
                SQLContainer package, more specifically in the class
                <classname>com.vaadin.addon.sqlcontainer.demo.DemoFreeformQueryDelegate</classname>.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.nonimplemented">
        <title>Non-Implemented Methods</title>

        <para>
            Due to the database connection inherent to the SQLContainer, some of the
            methods from the container interfaces of Vaadin can not (or would not make
            sense to) be implemented. These methods are listed below, and they will throw
            an <classname>UnsupportedOperationException</classname> on invocation.
        </para>

        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public boolean addContainerProperty(Object propertyId,
                                    Class<?> type,
                                    Object defaultValue)
public boolean removeContainerProperty(Object propertyId)
public Item addItem(Object itemId)
public Object addItemAt(int index)
public Item addItemAt(int index, Object newItemId)
public Object addItemAfter(Object previousItemId)
public Item addItemAfter(Object previousItemId, Object newItemId)]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Additionally, the following methods of the <classname>Item</classname>
            interface are not supported in the <classname>RowItem</classname> class:
        </para>
	
        <programlisting><?pocket-size 65% ?><![CDATA[public boolean addItemProperty(Object id, Property property)
public boolean removeItemProperty(Object id)]]></programlisting>

        <simplesect xml:id="sqlcontainer.nonimplemented.getitemids">
            <title>About the getItemIds() method</title>

            <para>
                To properly implement the Vaadin <classname>Container</classname>
                interface, a <methodname>getItemIds()</methodname> method has been
                implented in the <classname>SQLContainer</classname>. By definition, this
                method returns a collection of all the item IDs present in the
                container. What this means in the <classname>SQLContainer</classname> case
                is that the container has to query the database for the primary key
                columns of all the rows present in the connected database table.
            </para>

            <para>
                It is obvious that this could potentially lead to fetching tens or even
                hundreds of thousands of rows in an effort to satisfy the method
                caller. This will effectively kill the lazy loading properties of
                <classname>SQLContainer</classname> and therefore the following warning is
                expressed here:
            </para>

            <warning>
                <para>
                    It is highly recommended not to call the
                    <methodname>getitemIds()</methodname> method, unless it is known that
                    in the use case in question the item ID set will always be of
                    reasonable size.
                </para>
            </warning>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sqlcontainer.limitations">
        <title>Known Issues and Limitations</title>

        <para>
            At this point, there are still some known issues and limitations affecting the
            use of SQLContainer in certain situations. The known issues and brief
            explanations are listed below:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                Some SQL data types do not have write support when using TableQuery:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>All binary types</listitem>
                    <listitem>All custom types</listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        CLOB (if not converted automatically to a
                        <classname>String</classname> by the JDBC driver in use)
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        See
                        <classname>com.vaadin.addon.sqlcontainer.query.generator.StatementHelper</classname>
                        for details.
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    When using Oracle or MS SQL database, the column name
                    "<parameter>rownum</parameter>" can not be used as a column name in a
                    table connected to <classname>SQLContainer</classname>.
                </para>
                <para>
                    This limitation exists because the databases in question do not
                    support limit/offset clauses required for paging. Instead, a generated
                    column named 'rownum' is used to implement paging support.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            The permanent limitations are listed below. These can not or most probably
            will not be fixed in future versions of SQLContainer.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                The <methodname>getItemIds()</methodname> method is very inefficient -
                avoid calling it unless absolutely required!
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                When using <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> without providing a
                <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname>, the row count query is
                very inefficient - avoid using <classname>FreeformQuery</classname>
                without implementing at least the count query properly.
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                When using <classname>FreeformQuery</classname> without providing a
                <classname>FreeformStatementDelegate</classname>, writing, sorting and
                filtering will not be supported.
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    When using Oracle database most or all of the numeric types are
                    converted to <classname>java.math.BigDecimal</classname> by the Oracle
                    JDBC Driver.
                </para>
                <para>
                    This is a feature of how Oracle DB and the Oracle JDBC Driver
                    handles data types.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
