<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Copyright 2000-2012 Vaadin Ltd                                         -->
<!-- All Rights Reserved                                                    -->
<!-- This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs    -->
<!-- License (CC-BY-ND) Version 3.0. Full license text is available at:     -->
<!-- http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/legalcode                -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="architecture">
	<title>Architecture</title>

	<para>
        In <xref linkend="intro"/>, we gave a short introduction to the general
        architecture of Vaadin. This chapter looks deeper into the architecture at a more
        technical level.
	</para>

	<section xml:id="architecture.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            Vaadin provides two development models for web applications: for the
            client-side (the browser) and for the server-side. The server-driven
            development model is the more powerful one, allowing application development
            solely on the server-side, by utilizing an AJAX-based Vaadin Client-Side
            Engine that renders the user interface in the browser. The client-side model
            allows developing widgets and applications in Java, which are compiled to
            JavaScript and executed in the browser. The two models can share their UI
            widgets, themes, and back-end code and services, and can be mixed together
            easily.
        </para>

		<figure xml:id="figure.architecture.detailed" float="center" floatstyle="before">
			<title>Vaadin Runtime Architecture</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/arch/architecture-detailed-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="60" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/arch/architecture-detailed-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

        <para>
            <xref linkend="figure.architecture.detailed"/> gives a basic illustration of
            the client-side and server-side communications, in a running situation where
            the page with the client-side code (engine or application) has been intially
            loaded in the browser.
		</para>

		<para>
			Vaadin Framework consists of a <emphasis>server-side API</emphasis>, a
			<emphasis>client-side API</emphasis>, a horde of <emphasis>user interface
			components/widgets</emphasis> on the both sides, <emphasis>themes</emphasis>
			for controlling the appearance, and a <emphasis>data model</emphasis> that
			allows binding the server-side components directly to data. For client-side
			development, it includes the Vaadin Compiler, which allows compiling Java to
			JavaScript.
		</para>

		<para>
			A server-side Vaadin application runs as a servlet in a Java web server,
			serving HTTP requests. The <classname>VaadinServlet</classname> is normally
			used as the servlet class. The servlet receives client requests and inteprets
			them as events for a particular user session. Events are associated with user
			interface components and delivered to the event listeners defined in the
			application. If the UI logic makes changes to the server-side user interface
			components, the servlet renders them in the web browser by generating a
			response. The client-side engine running in the browser receives the responses
			and uses them to make any necessary changes to the page in the browser.
		</para>

		<para>
			The major parts of the server-driven development architecture and their
			function are as follows:
		</para>

		<!-- Spacing must be compact for small format book. -->
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>User Interface</term>
				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        Vaadin applications provide a user interface for the user to
                        interface with the business logic and data of the application. At
                        technical level, the UI is realized as a
                        <emphasis>&ui;</emphasis> class that extends
                        <classname>com.vaadin.ui.&uiclass;</classname>. Its main task is
                        to create the initial user interface out of UI components and set
                        up event listeners to handle user input. The &ui; can then be
                        loaded in the browser using an URL, or can be embedded to any HTML
                        page. For detailed information about implementing a
                        <classname>&uiclass;</classname>, see <xref
                        linkend="application"/>.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        Please note that the term "UI" is used throughout this book to
                        refer both to the general UI concept as well as the technical UI
                        class concept.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>User Interface Components/Widgets</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        <indexterm><primary>component</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>widget</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>field</primary></indexterm>

						The user interface of a Vaadin application consists of components
						that are created and laid out by the application. Each server-side
						component has a client-side counterpart, a
						"<emphasis>widget</emphasis>", by which it is rendered in the
						browser and with which the user interacts. The client-side widgets
						can also be used by client-side applications. The server-side
						components relay these events to the application logic. Field
						components that have a value, which the user can view or edit, can
						be bound to a data source (see below). For a more detailed
						description of the UI component architecture, see <xref
						linkend="components"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Client-Side Engine</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        <indexterm><primary>Client-Side Engine</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>HTTP</primary></indexterm>

						The Client-Side Engine of Vaadin manages the rendering of ther UI
						in the web browser by employing various client-side
						<emphasis>widgets</emphasis>, counterparts of the server-side
						components. It communicates user interaction to the server-side,
						and then again renders the changes in the UI. The communications
						are made using asynchronous HTTP or HTTPS requests. See <xref
						linkend="architecture.client-side"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Vaadin Servlet</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        <indexterm><primary>VaadinServlet</primary></indexterm>

                        Server-side Vaadin applications work on top of the Java Servlet
                        API (see <xref linkend="architecture.technology.servlet"/>. The
                        Vaadin servlet, or more exactly the
                        <classname>VaadinServlet</classname> class, receives requests from
                        different clients, determines which user session they belong to by
                        tracking the sessions with cookies, and delegates the requests to
                        their corresponding sessions. You can customize the Vaadin servlet
                        by extending it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Themes</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        <indexterm><primary>theme</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>CSS</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>SASS</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>HTML templates</primary></indexterm>

						Vaadin makes a separation between the appearance and component
						structure of the user interface. While the UI logic is handled as
						Java code, the presentation is defined in
						<emphasis>themes</emphasis> as CSS or SCSS. Vaadin provides a
						number of default themes. User themes can, in addition to style
						sheets, include HTML templates that define custom layouts and
						other resources, such as images. Themes are discussed in detail in
						<xref linkend="themes"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Events</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        <indexterm><primary>events</primary></indexterm>

						Interaction with user interfafce components creates events, which
						are first processed on the client-side by the widgets, then passed
						all the way through the HTTP server, Vaadin servlet, and the user
						interface components to the event listeners defined in the
						application. See <xref linkend="architecture.events"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Data Binding</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        <indexterm><primary>Data Model</primary></indexterm>
                        <indexterm><primary>Data Binding</primary></indexterm>

						In addition to the user interface model, Vaadin provides a
						<emphasis>data model</emphasis> for binding data presented in
						field components, such as text fields, check boxes and selection
						components, to a data source. Using the data model, the user
						interface components can update the application data directly,
						often without the need for any control code. All the field
						components in Vaadin use this data model internally, but any of
						them can be bound to a separate data source as well.

                        <indexterm><primary>SQL</primary></indexterm>

                        For example, you can bind a table component to an SQL query
                        response. For a complete overview of the Vaadin Data Model, please
                        refer to <xref linkend="datamodel"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Client-Side Applications</term>
				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        In addition to server-side web applications, Vaadin supports
                        client-side application modules, which run in the browser.

                        Client-side modules can use the same widgets, themes, and back-end
                        services as server-side Vaadin applications. They are useful when
                        you have a need for highly responsive UI logic, such as for games
                        or for serving a large number of clients with possibly stateless
                        server-side code, and for various other purposes, such as offering
                        an off-line mode for server-side applications. Please see <xref
                        linkend="clientsideapp"/> for further details.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Back-end</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        Vaadin is meant for building user interfaces, and it is
                        recommended that other application layers should be kept separate
                        from the UI. The business logic can run in the same servlet as the
                        UI code, usually separated at least by a Java API, possibly as
                        EJBs, or distributed to a remote back-end service. The data
                        storage is usually distributed to a database management system,
                        and is typically accessed through a persistence solution, such as
                        JPA.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

	</section>

	<section xml:id="architecture.technology">
		<title>Technological Background</title>

		<para>
            <indexterm><primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary></indexterm>

			This section provides an introduction to the various technologies and designs
			on which Vaadin is based. This knowledge is not necessary for using Vaadin,
			but provides some background if you need to make low-level extensions to
			Vaadin.
		</para>

		<section xml:id="architecture.technology.html">
			<title>HTML and JavaScript</title>

			<para>
                The World Wide Web, with all its websites and most of the web
                applications, is based on the use of the Hypertext Markup Language
                (HTML). HTML defines the structure and formatting of web pages, and allows
                inclusion of graphics and other resources.  It is based on a hierarchy of
                elements marked with start and end tags, such as <literal>&lt;div&gt;
                ... &lt;/div&gt;</literal>. Vaadin specifically uses XHTML, which is
                syntactically stricter than regular HTML. Vaadin supports (X)HTML 4, which
                is the current and the most widely supported version. In addition, it
                supports some features of HTML5, which is the upcoming version.
            </para>

			<para>
                JavaScript, on the other hand, is a programming language for embedding
                programs in HTML pages. JavaScript programs can manipulate a HTML page
                through the Document Object Model (DOM) of the page. They can also handle
                user interaction events. The Client-Side Engine of Vaadin and its
                client-side widgets do exactly this, although it is actually programmed in
                Java, which is compiled to JavaScript with the Vaadin Client Compiler.
            </para>

			<para>
                Vaadin largely hides the use of HTML, allowing you to concentrate on the
                UI component structure and logic. In server-side development, the UI is
                developed in Java using UI components and rendered by the client-side
                engine as HTML, but it is possible to use HTML templates for defining the
                layout, as well as HTML formatting in many text elements. Also when
                developing client-side widgets and UIs, the built-in widgets in the
                framework hide most of HTML DOM manipulation.
            </para>
        </section>

		<section xml:id="architecture.technology.html">
			<title>Styling with CSS and Sass</title>

			<para>
                While HTML defines the content and structure of a web page,
                <emphasis>Cascading Style Sheet</emphasis> (CSS) is a language for
                defining the visual style, such as colors, text sizes, and margins. CSS is
                based on rules that are matched with the HTML structure by the
                browser. The properties defined in the rules determine the visual
                appearance of the matching HTML elements.
            </para>

			<para>
                <emphasis>Sass</emphasis>, or <emphasis>Syntactically Awesome
                Stylesheets</emphasis>, is an extension of the CSS language, which allows
                the use of variables, nesting, and many other syntactic features that make
                the use of CSS easier and clearer. Sass files are compiled automatically
                to CSS with a compiler included with Vaadin.
            </para>

            <para>
                Vaadin handles styling with <emphasis>themes</emphasis> defined with CSS
                or Sass, and associated images and other resources. The use of themes is
                documented in detail in <xref linkend="themes"/>, which also gives an
                introduction to CSS.
            </para>
        </section>

		<section xml:id="architecture.technology.ajax">
			<title>AJAX</title>
			<para>
                <indexterm significance="preferred"><primary>AJAX</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>XML</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>JavaScript</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>XHTML</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>CSS</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>DOM</primary></indexterm>
                <indexterm><primary>XMLHttpRequest</primary></indexterm>

				AJAX, short for Asynchronous JavaScript and XML, is a technique for
				developing web applications with responsive user interaction, similar to
				traditional desktop applications. Conventional web applications, be they
				JavaScript-enabled or not, can get new page content from the server only
				by loading an entire new page. AJAX-enabled pages, on the other hand,
				handle the user interaction in JavaScript, send a request to the server
				asynchronously (without reloading the page), receive updated content in
				the response, and modify the page accordingly. This way, only small parts
				of the page data need to be loaded.

                This goal is archieved by the use of a certain set of technologies: XHTML,
                CSS, DOM, JavaScript, and the XMLHttpRequest API in JavaScript. XML is
                just one way to serialize data between the client and the server, and in
                Vaadin it is serialized with the more efficient JSON.
			</para>

			<para>
				The asynchronous requests used in AJAX are made possible by the
				<methodname>XMLHttpRequest</methodname> class in JavaScript. The API
				feature is available in all major browsers and, as of 2006, it is under
				way to become a W3C standard.
			</para>

			<para>
				Communication of complex data between the browser and the server require
				some sort of <emphasis>serialization</emphasis> (or
				<emphasis>marshalling</emphasis>) of data objects. The Vaadin servlet and
				the client-side engine handle the serialization of shared state objects
				from the server-side components to the client-side widgets, as well as
				serialization of RPC calls from the widgets to the server-side components.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="architecture.technology.gwt">
			<title>Google Web Toolkit</title>

			<para>
                <indexterm significance="preferred"><primary>Google Web Toolkit</primary></indexterm>

                The client-side framework of Vaadin is based on the Google Web Toolkit
                (GWT), of which purpose is to enable the development of client-side web
                user interfaces easily with Java instead of JavaScript. Client-side
                modules are developed with Java and compiled into JavaScript with the
                Vaadin Compiler, which is an extension of the GWT Compiler. The
                client-side framework also hides much of the HTML DOM manipulation and
                enables handling browser events in Java.
			</para>

			<para>
				GWT is essentially a client-side technology, normally used to develop user
				interface logic in the web browser. Pure client-side modules still need to
				communicate with a server using RPC calls and by serializing any data. The
				server-driven development mode in Vaadin effectively hides all the
				client-server communications and allows handling user interaction logic in
				a server-side application. This makes the architecture of an AJAX-based
				web application much simpler. Nevertheless, Vaadin allows developing also
				client-side applications when needed, as described in <xref
				linkend="clientsideapp"/>.
			</para>

			<para>
				See <xref linkend="architecture.client-side"/> for a description of how
				the client-side framework based on GWT is used in the Client-Side Engine
				of Vaadin. <xref linkend="clientside"/> provides information about the
				client-side development, and <xref linkend="gwt"/> about the integration
				of client-side widgets with the server-side components.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="architecture.technology.servlet">
			<title>Java Servlets</title>

            <para>
                A Java Servlet is a class that is executed in a Java web server (a
                <emphasis>Servlet container</emphasis>) to extend the capabilities of the
                server. In practice, it is normally part of a <emphasis>web
                application</emphasis>, which can contain HTML pages to provide static
                content, and JavaServer Pages (JSP) and Java Servlets to provide dynamic
                content. This is illustrated in <xref
                linkend="figure.architecture.technology.servlet"/>.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.architecture.technology.servlet"> <!--  float="center" floatstyle="before" -->
			<title>Java Web Applications and Servlets</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/arch/java-servlet-lo.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata scale="75"  smallscale="80%" align="center" fileref="img/arch/java-servlet-hi.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                Web applications are usually packaged and deployed to a server as
                <emphasis>WAR</emphasis> (<emphasis>Web application ARchive</emphasis>)
                files, which are Java JAR packages, which in turn are ZIP compressed
                packages. The web application is defined in a
                <filename>WEB-INF/web.xml</filename> deployment descriptor, which defines
                the servlet classes and also the mappings from request URL paths to the
                servlets. This is described in more detail in <xref
                linkend="application.environment.web-xml"/>. The class path for the
                servlets and their dependencies includes the
                <filename>WEB-INF/classes</filename> and <filename>WEB-INF/lib</filename>
                folders. The <filename>WEB-INF</filename> is a special hidden folder that
                can not be accessed by its URL path.
            </para>

            <para>
                The servlets are Java classes that handle HTTP requests passed to them by
                the server through the <emphasis>Java Servlet API</emphasis>. They
                generate HTML content as a response. JSP pages, on the other hand, are
                HTML pages, which allow including Java source code embedded in the
                pages. They are actually translated to Java source files by the container
                and then compiled to servlets.
            </para>

            <para>
                The UIs of server-side Vaadin applications run as servlets. They are
                wrapped inside a <classname>VaadinServlet</classname> servlet class, which
                handles session tracking and other tasks. The server-side UIs are
                implemented as classes extending the <classname>UI</classname> class, as
                described in <xref linkend="application"/>. The class is given as a
                parameter to the Vaadin Servlet in the <filename>web.xml</filename>
                deployment descriptor.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Client-Side Engine as well as client-side Vaadin applications
                are loaded to the browser as static JavaScript files. The client-side
                engine, or widget set in technical terms, needs to be located under the
                <filename>VAADIN/widgetsets</filename> path in the web application. The
                precompiled default widget set is served from the
                <filename>vaadin-client-compiled</filename> JAR by the Vaadin Servlet.
            </para>
        </section>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="architecture.client-side">
		<title>Client-Side Engine</title>

		<para>
            <indexterm significance="preferred"><primary>Client-Side Engine</primary></indexterm>

            The user interface of a server-side Vaadin application is rendered in the
            browser by the Vaadin Client-Side Engine. It is loaded in the browser when the
            page with the Vaadin UI is opened. The server-side UI components are rendered
            using <emphasis>widgets</emphasis> (as they are called in Google Web Toolkit)
            on the client-side. The client-side engine illustrated in <xref
            linkend="figure.architecture.client-side"/>.
        </para>
           
		<figure xml:id="figure.architecture.client-side"> <!--  float="center" floatstyle="before" -->
			<title>Vaadin Client-Side Engine</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/arch/clientside-arch-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="75"  smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/arch/clientside-arch-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

        <para>
            The client-side framework includes two kinds of built-in widgets: GWT widgets
            and Vaadin-specific widgets. The two widget collections have significant
            overlap, where the Vaadin widgets provide a bit different features than the
            GWT widgets. In addition, many add-on widgets and their server-side
            counterparts exists, and you can easily download and install them, as
            described in <xref linkend="addons"/>. You can also develop your own widgets,
            as described in <xref linkend="clientside"/>.
        </para>

        <para>
            The rendering with widgets as well as the communication to the server-side is
            handled in the <classname>ApplicationConnection</classname>. Connecting the
            widgets with their server-side counterparts is done in
            <emphasis>connectors</emphasis>, which are one of each widget. The framework
            handles serialization of component state transparently, and includes an RPC
            mechanism between the two sides. Integration of widgets with their server-side
            counterpart components is described in <xref linkend="gwt"/>.
        </para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="architecture.events">
		<title>Events and Listeners</title>

		<para>
            Vaadin offers an event-driven programming model for handling user interaction.
            When a user does something in the user interface, such as clicks a button or
            selects an item, the application needs to know about it. Many Java-based user
            interface frameworks follow the <emphasis>Event-Listener pattern</emphasis>
            (also known as the Observer design pattern) to communicate user input to the
            application logic.  So does Vaadin. The design pattern involves two kinds of
            elements: an object that generates ("fires" or "emits") events and a number of
            listeners that listen for the events. When such an event occurs, the object
            sends a notification about it to all the listeners. In a typical case, there
            is only one listener.
		</para>

		<para>
            Events can serve many kinds of purposes. In Vaadin, the usual purpose of
            events is handling user interaction in a user interface. Session management
            can require special events, such as for time-out, in which case the event
            would actually be the lack of user interaction. Time-out is a special case of
            timed or scheduled events, where an event occurs at a specific date and time
            or when a set time has passed.
		</para>

		<para>
            To receive events of a particular type, an application must register a
            listener object with the event source. The listeners are registered in the
            components with an <methodname>add*Listener()</methodname> method (with a
            method name specific to the listener).
		</para>

		<para>
			Most components that have related events define their own event class and the
			corresponding listener class. For example, the <classname>Button</classname>
			has <classname>Button.ClickEvent</classname> events, which can be listened to
			through the <classname>Button.ClickListener</classname> interface.
        </para>

        <para>
            In the following, we handle button clicks with a listener implemented as an
            anonymous class:
        </para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[final Button button = new Button("Push it!");

button.addClickListener(new Button.ClickListener() {
    public void buttonClick(ClickEvent event) {
        button.setCaption("You pushed it!");
    }
});]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			<xref linkend="figure.eventlistenerdiagram"/> illustrates the case where an
			application-specific class inherits the
			<classname>Button.ClickListener</classname> interface to be able to listen for
			button click events. The application must instantiate the listener class and
			register it with <methodname>addClickListener()</methodname>. It can be an
			anonymous class, such as the one above. When an event occurs, an event object
 			is instantiated, in this case a <classname>Button.ClickEvent</classname>. The
			event object knows the related UI component, in this case the
			<classname>Button</classname>.
		</para>

        <!-- TODO: No SVG file for this drawing. -->
		<figure xml:id="figure.eventlistenerdiagram">
			<title>Class Diagram of a Button Click Listener</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/arch/events-classdiagram-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="75"  smallscale="80%" align="center" fileref="img/arch/events-classdiagram-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>
			In the ancient times of C programming, <emphasis>callback functions</emphasis>
			filled largely the same need as listeners do now. In object-oriented
			languages, we have only classes and methods, not functions, so the application
			has to give a class interface instead of a callback function pointer to the
			framework. However, Vaadin supports defining a method as a listener as well,
			using the <classname>MethodListener</classname> wrapper.
		</para>

        <para>
            <xref linkend="application.events"/> goes into details of handling events in
            practice.
        </para>
	</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
