<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="charts">
    <title>Vaadin Charts</title>

    <section xml:id="charts.overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            Vaadin Charts is a feature-rich interactive charting library for Vaadin. It
            provides a <classname>Chart</classname> component, which can illustrate data
            in many available chart types. The charts allow flexible configuration of all
            the chart elements as well as the visual style. The library includes a number
            of built-in visual themes, which you can extend further.
        </para>

		<figure xml:id="figure.charts.overview" float="center" floatstyle="before">
			<title>Vaadin Charts with Bar, Column, Area, and Pie Charts</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata scale="70" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/charts/charts-overview.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

        <para>
            This chapter covers the basic use of Vaadin Charts and the chart
            configuration. For detailed documentation of the configuration parameters and
            classes, please refer to the JavaDoc API documentation of the library.
        </para>

        <para>
            Vaadin Charts is based on Highcharts JS, a charting library written in
            JavaScript.
        </para>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Licensing and Trial Period</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin Charts is licensed under the Commercial Vaadin Add-on Licence
                (CVAL) version 2.0. The per-developer license is available for Vaadin Pro
                Account subscribers as explained at <link
                xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/pro">vaadin.com/pro</link>.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="charts.installing">
        <title>Installing Vaadin Charts</title>

        <para>
            Vaadin Charts can be installed either as an installation package,
            downloaded from the Vaadin Directory, or as a Maven dependency. You can also
            create a new JPAContainer-enabled Vaadin project using a Maven archetype.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
