<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="mobile.considerations">
	<title>Considerations Regarding Mobile Browsing</title>

    <para>
        When developing applications that support mobile browsing, you need to consider
        various issues that are different from non-mobile use.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="mobile.considerations.bandwidth">
        <title>Mobile Human Interface</title>

        <para>
            Mobile devices use very different human interface than regular
            computers.
        </para>

        <para>
            Perhaps the most evident feature is that the user can easily change the
            orientation of the display to switch between portrait and landscape
            views. This may change not just the dimensions of the display, but also the
            most useful layout.
        </para>

        <para>
            There is often no physical but a virtual keyboard. You need to ensure that,
            when the virtual keyboard pops up, it does not hide the input field to which
            the user is trying to enter data. This should be handled by the browser, but
            you should in any case check that it does. This is largely a testing issue.
        </para>

        <para>
            There is no "right-finger-button" and double-tap is not normally used in
            mobile user interfaces unlike the double-click with mouse. Instead, a "long
            tap" usually has the same meaning as the double click. Finger gestures also
            play a large role, such as using a vertical wipe gesture for scrolling instead
            of a scroll bar and horizontal wipe for browsing between views or "tabs".
        </para>

        <para>
            TouchKit helps with many of these special requirements for mobile
            applications.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="mobile.considerations.bandwidth">
        <title>Bandwidth</title>

        <para>
            Mobile Internet connections are often significantly slower than with fixed
            lines. With a common 384 kbps connection, just loading the Vaadin client-side
            engine can take several seconds. This can be helped by compiling a widget set
            that includes only the used components.
        </para>

        <para>
            Even with mobile broadband, the latency can be significant factor, especially
            with highly interactive rich applications. The latency is usually almost
            unnoticeable in fixed lines, typically less than 100 ms, while mobile Edge
            connections typically have latency around 500 ms, and sometimes much higher
            during hiccups. You may need to limit the use of the immediate mode, text
            change events, and polling.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="mobile.considerations.features">
        <title>Mobile Features</title>

        <para>
            Phones and tablets have many integrated features that are often available in
            the browser interface as well. Location-awareness is one of the most recent
            features. And of course, you can also make phone calls.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="mobile.considerations.x">
        <title>Compatibility</title>

        <para>
            The mobile browsing field is currently evolving at fast pace and the special
            conventions that are introduced by leading manufacturers may in the next few
            years stabilize as new web standards. The browser support in TouchKit
            concentrates on WebKit, which appears to be emerging as the leading mobile
            browser core. In addition to Apple's products, also the default browser in
            Android uses WebKit as the layout engine. Yet there are differences, as the
            Android's JavaScript engine, which is highly relevant for Vaadin, is the
            Google Chrome's V8 engine. TouchKit aims to follow the quickly evolving APIs
            of these major platforms, with the assumption that other browsers will follow
            their lead in standardization.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
