<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
		This chapter provides an introduction to software development with Vaadin,
		including installation of Vaadin, the Eclipse development environment, and any
		other necessary or useful utilities. We look into the design philosophy behind
		Vaadin, its history, and recent major changes.
	</para>

	<section xml:id="intro.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>

		<para>
			The core piece of Vaadin is the Java library that is designed to make creation
			and maintenance of high quality web-based user interfaces easy. The key idea
			in the server-driven programming model of Vaadin is that it allows you to
			forget the web and lets you program user interfaces much like you would
			program any Java desktop application with conventional toolkits such as AWT,
			Swing, or SWT. But easier.
		</para>

		<para>
			While traditional web programming is a fun way to spend your time learning new
			web technologies, you probably want to be productive and concentrate on the
			application logic. With the server-driven programming model, Vaadin takes care
			of managing the user interface in the browser and <firstterm>AJAX</firstterm>
			communications between the browser and the server. With the Vaadin approach,
			you do not need to learn and debug browser technologies, such as HTML or
			JavaScript.
		</para>

		<figure xml:id="figure.intro.architecture">
			<title>General Architecture of Vaadin</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/intro/architecture-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="75" smallscale="100" align="center" fileref="img/intro/architecture-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>
			<xref linkend="figure.intro.architecture"/> illustrates the basic architecture
			of web applications made with Vaadin. Vaadin consists of the
			<emphasis>server-side framework</emphasis> and a <emphasis>client-side
			engine</emphasis> that runs in the browser as a JavaScript program, rendering
			the user interface and delivering user interaction to the server. As the
			application runs as a persistent Java Servlet session in an application
			server, you can easily bind your application to data and logic tiers.
		</para>

		<para>
			Because HTML, JavaScript, and other browser technologies are essentially
			invisible to the application logic, you can think of
			the web browser as only a thin client platform. A thin
			client displays the user interface and communicates
			user events to the server at a low
			level. The control logic of the user interface runs on
			a Java-based web server, together with your business
			logic. By contrast, a normal client-server
			architecture with a dedicated client application would
			include a lot of application specific communications
			between the client and the server. Essentially
			removing the user interface tier from the application architecture makes our approach a
			very effective one.
		</para>

		<para>
            As the Client-Side Engine is executed as JavaScript in the browser, no browser
            plugins are needed for using applications made with Vaadin. This gives it a
            sharp edge over frameworks based on Flash, Java Applets, or other
            plugins. Vaadin relies on the support of GWT for a wide range of browsers, so
            that the developer doesn't need to worry about browser support.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Behind the server-driven development model, Vaadin makes the best use of AJAX
			(<firstterm>Asynchronous JavaScript and XML</firstterm>) techniques that make
			it possible to create Rich Internet Applications (RIA) that are as responsive
			and interactive as desktop applications. If you're a newcomer to AJAX, see
			<xref linkend="architecture.technology.ajax"/> to find out what it is and how
			AJAX applications differ from traditional web applications.
		</para>

		<para>
			Hidden well under the hood, Vaadin uses <firstterm>GWT</firstterm>, the
			<firstterm>Google Web Toolkit</firstterm>, for rendering the user interface in
			the browser. GWT programs are written in Java, but compiled into JavaScript,
			thus freeing the developer from learning JavaScript and other browser
			technologies. GWT is ideal for implementing advanced user interface components
			(or widgets in GWT terminology) and interaction logic in the browser, while
			Vaadin handles the actual application logic in the server. Vaadin is designed
			to be extensible, and you can indeed use any 3rd-party GWT components easily,
			in addition to the component repertoire offered in Vaadin. The use of GWT also
			means that all the code you need to write is pure Java.
		</para>

		<informalfigure floatstyle="right">
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="img/intro/intro-themes-faded-lo.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata scale="50" fileref="img/intro/intro-themes-faded-hi.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</informalfigure>
		
		<para>
			The Vaadin library defines a clear separation between user interface
			presentation and logic and allows you to develop them separately. Our
			approach to this is <firstterm>themes</firstterm>, which dictate the visual
			appearance of applications. Themes control the appearance of the user
			interfaces using CSS and (optional) HTML page templates. As Vaadin
			provides excellent default themes, you do not usually need to make much
			customization, but you can if you need to. For more about themes, see
			<xref linkend="themes"/>.
		</para>

		<para>
			We hope that this is enough about the basic architecture and features of
			Vaadin for now. You can read more about it later in <xref
			linkend="architecture"/>, or jump straight to more practical things in <xref
			linkend="application"/>.
        </para>
    </section>

	<section xml:id="intro.walkthrough">
		<title>Example Application Walkthrough</title>

		<para>
			Let us follow the long tradition of first saying "Hello World!" when learning
			a new programming environment. After that, we can go through a more detailed
			example that implements the model-view-controller architecture. The two
			examples given are really simple, but this is mostly because Vaadin is
			designed to make things simple.
		</para>

		<example xml:id="ex.helloworld">
			<title>HelloWorld.java</title>
			<programlisting><?pocket-size 75% ?><![CDATA[import com.vaadin.ui.*;

public class HelloWorld extends com.vaadin.Application {

    public void init() { 
        Window main = new Window("Hello window"); 
        setMainWindow(main);
        main.addComponent(new Label("Hello World!")); 
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>
		
		<para>
			The first thing to note is that the example application extends
			<classname>com.vaadin.Application</classname> class. The
			<classname>Application</classname> class is used as the base class for all
			user applications. Instances of the <classname>Application</classname> are
			essentially user sessions, and one is created for each user using the
			application. In the context of our HelloWorld application, it is
			sufficient to know that the application is started when the user first
			accesses it and at that time <methodname>init</methodname> method is
			invoked.
		</para>

		<para>
			Initialization of the application first creates a new window object and sets
			"Hello window" as its caption. The window is then set as the main window of
			the application; an application can actually have many windows. This means
			that when a user launches the application, the contents of the "main window"
			are shown to the user in the web page. The caption is shown as the title of
			the (browser) window.
		</para>

		<para>
			A new user interface component of class
			<classname>com.vaadin.ui.Label</classname> is created. The label is
			set to draw the text "Hello World!". Finally, the label is added to the main
			window. And here we are, when the application is started, it draws the text
			"Hello World!" to the browser window.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The following screenshot shows what the "Hello World!" program will look like
			in a web browser.
		</para>

		<screenshot>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/intro/HelloWorld.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>

		<para>
			Before going into details, we should note that this example source code is
			complete and does not need any additional declaratively defined template files
			to be run. To run the program, you can just add it to your web application, as
			explained in <xref linkend="application.environment" />.
		</para>
    </section>

	<section>
		<title>Support for the Eclipse IDE</title>

		<para>
			While Vaadin is not bound to any specific IDE, and you can in fact easily use
			it without any IDE altogether, we provide special support for the Eclipse IDE,
			which has become the standard environment for Java development. The support
			includes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Import the installation package as a QuickStart demo project in Eclipse</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Install the Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse, which allows you to:</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Create new Vaadin projects</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>Create custom themes</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>Create custom client-side widgets and widget sets</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>Edit components with a visual (WYSIWYG) editor</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>Easily upgrade to a newer version of the Vaadin library</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
			The Vaadin Plugin for Eclipse is our recommended way of installing Vaadin; the
			actual installation package contains demos and documentation that are
			available also from the website, so you do not normally need to download and
			install it, unless you want to experiment with the demos or try debugging.
		</para>

		<para>
			Installing and updating the plugin is covered in <xref
			linkend="getting-started.environment.eclipse-plugin"/> and the creation of a
			new Vaadin project using the plugin in <xref
			linkend="getting-started.first-project.creation"/>. See <xref
			linkend="themes.eclipse"/>, <xref linkend="gwt.eclipse"/>, and <xref
			linkend="eclipse"/> for instructions on using the different features of the
			plugin.
		</para>
	</section>

    <section xml:id="intro.overview.goals">
        <title>Goals and Philosophy</title>

        <para>
            Simply put, Vaadin's ambition is to be the best
            possible tool when it comes to creating web user interfaces for business
            applications. It is easy to adopt, as it is designed to support both
            entry-level and advanced programmers, as well as usability experts and
            graphical designers.
        </para>

        <para>
            When designing Vaadin, we have followed the philosophy inscribed in
            the following rules.
        </para>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Right tool for the right purpose</title>

            <para>
                Because our goals are high, the focus must be clear. This toolkit is
                designed for creating web applications. It is not designed for
                creating websites or advertisements demos. For such purposes, you 
                might find (for instance) JSP/JSF or Flash more suitable.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Simplicity and maintainability</title>

            <para>
                We have chosen to emphasize robustness, simplicity, and
                maintainability. This involves following the well-established best
                practices in user interface frameworks and ensuring that our
                implementation represents an ideal solution for its purpose without
                clutter or bloat.
			</para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>XML is not designed for programming</title>
            <para>
                The Web is inherently document-centered and very much bound to the
                declarative presentation of user interfaces. The Vaadin framework frees the
                programmer from these limitations. It is far more natural to create user
                interfaces by programming them than by defining them in declarative
                templates, which are not flexible enough for complex and dynamic user
                interaction.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect>
            <title>Tools should not limit your work</title>
            <para>
                There should not be any limits on what you can do with the framework:
                if for some reason the user interface components do not support what
                you need to achieve, it must be easy to add new ones to your
                application. When you need to create new components, the role of the
                framework is critical: it makes it easy to create re-usable components
                that are easy to maintain.
            </para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="intro.overview.background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>
            The library was not written overnight. After working with web user
            interfaces since the beginning of the Web, a group of developers got
            together in 2000 to form IT Mill. The team had a desire to develop a new
            programming paradigm that would support the creation of real user
            interfaces for real applications using a real programming language.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The library was originally called Millstone Library. The first version was
            used in a large production application that IT Mill designed and
            implemented for an international pharmaceutical company. IT Mill made the
            application already in the year 2001 and it is still in use. Since then,
            the company has produced dozens of large business applications with the
            library and it has proven its ability to solve hard problems easily.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The next generation of the library, IT Mill Toolkit Release 4, was
            released in 2006. It introduced an entirely new AJAX-based presentation
            engine. This allowed the development of AJAX applications without the need
            to worry about communications between the client and the server.
        </para>
        
        <simplesect xml:id="intro.overview.background.toolkit-5">
            <title>Release 5 Into the Open</title>

            <para>
                IT Mill Toolkit 5, released initially at the end of 2007, took a
                significant step further into AJAX. The client-side rendering of the user
                interface was completely rewritten using GWT, the Google Web Toolkit.
            </para>

            <para>
                IT Mill Toolkit 5 introduced many significant improvements both in the
                server-side API and in the functionality. Rewriting the Client-Side Engine
                with GWT allowed the use of Java both on the client and the
                server-side. The transition from JavaScript to GWT made the development
                and integration of custom components and customization of existing
                components much easier than before, and it also allows easy integration of
                existing GWT components. The adoption of GWT on the client-side did not,
                by itself, cause any changes in the server-side API, because GWT is a
                browser technology that is hidden well behind the API. Also themeing was
                completely revised in IT Mill Toolkit 5.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Release 5 was published under the Apache License 2, an unrestrictive
                open source license, to create faster expansion of the user base and make
                the formation of a developer community possible.
            </para>

            <para>
                Stabilization of the release 5 took over a year of work from the
                development team. It introduced a number of changes in the API, the
                client-side customization layer, and the themes. Many significant changes
                were done during the beta phase, until the stable version 5.3.0 was
                released in March 2009.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

		<simplesect>
			<title>Birth of Vaadin Release 6</title>

			<para>
				IT Mill Toolkit was renamed as <emphasis>Vaadin</emphasis> in spring 2009
				to avoid common confusions with the name (IT Mill is a company not the
				product) and to clarify the separation between the company and the open
				source project. Vaadin means a female semi-domesticated mountain reindeer
				in Finnish.
			</para>

			<para>
				The most notable enhancements in Vaadin 6 are the external development
				tools:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>Eclipse Plugin</listitem>
				<listitem>Visual user interface editor under Eclipse (experimental)</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				The Eclipse Plugin allows easy creation of Vaadin projects and custom
				client-side widgets. See <xref
				linkend="getting-started.environment.eclipse-plugin"/> for details. The
				visual editor, described in <xref linkend="eclipse"/> makes prototyping
				easy and new users of Vaadin should find it especially useful for
				introducing oneself to Vaadin. Like Vaadin itself, the tools are open
				source.
			</para>

			<para>
				While the API in Vaadin 6 is essentially backward-compatible with IT Mill
				Toolkit 5.4, the package names and some name prefixes were changed to
				comply with the new product name:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>Package name <package>com.itmill.toolkit</package> was renamed as <package>com.vaadin</package>.</listitem>
				<listitem>The static resource directory <literal>ITMILL</literal> was changed to <literal>VAADIN</literal>.</listitem>
				<listitem>Client-side widget prefix was changed from "<literal>I</literal>" to "<literal>V</literal>". </listitem>
				<listitem>CSS style name prefix was changed from "<literal>i-</literal>" to "<literal>v-</literal>". </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				Other enhancements in Vaadin 6 are listed in the Release Notes for Vaadin
				6.0.0, which also gives detailed instructions for upgrading from IT Mill
				Toolkit 5.
			</para>

		</simplesect>
    </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
