<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- Converted from the original Calendar Manual in ODT format in July 2011 -->
<!-- Original authors Tomi Virtanen (tomi.virtanen@itmill.com) and          -->
<!-- Risto Yrjana (risto.yrjana@itmill.com)                                 -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<chapter xml:id="addons.calendar">
    <title>Vaadin Calendar</title>

    <para>
        The Vaadin Calendar is a commercial add-on component for organizing and displaying
        calendar events. It can be used to view and manage events in monthly and weekly
        views.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="addons.calendar.overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            The main features of the Vaadin Calendar include:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                Manage calendar by server side API
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Two types of events: "All day" events and events with a time range
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                One minute accuracy of the timeline
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                A monthly and a weekly view for showing events
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Control the range of the visible dates
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Date or time range drag selecting
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Draggable and resizable events
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Support for localization and timezones
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Support for most common browsers
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            The API of the <classname>Calendar</classname> component allows managing its
            events, date range, styling, localization, and timezone. The data source of
            the calendar may be practically anything, as its events are queried
            dynamically by the component. You may use containers, or any other data source
            by implementing an <emphasis>event provider</emphasis> for the calendar.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="figure.addons.calendar.overview.views.monthly" float="center" floatstyle="before">
            <title>Monthly view with All-Day and Normal Events</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/addons/calendar-monthly.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/addons/calendar-monthly.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Book of Vaadin currently includes only an introduction to Vaadin
            Calendar. Please refer to the product documentation included in the
            installation package for further details.
        </para>

        <simplesect xml:id="addons.calendar.overview.views">
            <title>Views</title>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Calendar has two different type of views that are shown
                depending on the Calendar's date range. The Calendar displays a week by
                default. Calendar will be shown in a monthly view when date range is over
                than one week (seven days) long. Date range is always calculated in a
                accuracy of one millisecond.
            </para>

            <para>
                The monthly view, shown in <xref
                linkend="figure.addons.calendar.overview.views.monthly"/>, can easily be
                used to control all events, but it is best suited for longer
                events. Events that last for several days can easily be displayed and
                moved in the monthly view. In the figure, you can see two longer events
                that are highlighted with a blue and green background color. Other
                markings are shorter day events that last less than a 24 hours. These
                events cant be moved.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="figure.addons.calendar.overview.views.weekly" float="center" floatstyle="before">
                <title>Weekly View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="img/addons/calendar-weekly.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata scale="100" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/addons/calendar-weekly.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                When date range is over seven days long, the weekly view will be used.
                Weekly view can show any number of days from one to seven.
            </para>

            <para>
                In <xref linkend="figure.addons.calendar.overview.views.weekly"/>, you can
                see four normal day events and also all-day events at the top of the time
                line grid.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="addons.calendar.overview.event">
            <title>Calendar Event</title>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Calendar handles displayed events through the
                <classname>CalendarEvent</classname> interface. The concrete class of the
                event is decided by the implementor of the specific
                <classname>CalendarEventProvider</classname> used. By default,
                <classname>Calendar</classname> uses a
                <classname>BasicEventProvider</classname> to provide events. The
                <classname>BasicEventProvider</classname> uses
                <classname>BasicEvent</classname> instances.
            </para>

            <para>
                The Vaadin Calendar does not depend on any particular data source
                implementation. Events are queried by the <classname>Calendar</classname>
                from the provider that just has to implement the
                <classname>CalendarEventProvider</classname>. It is up to the event
                provider that <classname>Calendar</classname> gets the correct events.
            </para>

            <para>
                Event queries are done by asking the event provider for all the events
                between two given dates. The range of these dates is guaranteed to be at
                least as long as the start and end dates set for the component. The
                component can, however, ask for a longer range to ensure correct
                rendering. In particular, all start dates are expanded to the start of the
                day, and all end dates are expanded to the end of the day.
            </para>

            <para>
                A calendar event requires a start time and an end time. These are the only
                mandatory properties. In addition, an event can also be set as an all-day
                event by setting the <literal>all-day</literal> property of the event. You
                can also set the <literal>description</literal> of an event, which is
                displayed as a tooltip in the user interface.
            </para>

            <para>
                If the <literal>all-day</literal> field of the event is
                <literal>true</literal>, then the event is always rendered as an all-day
                event. In the monthly view, this means that no start time is displayed in
                the user interface and the event has an colored background. In the weekly
                view, all-day events are displayed in the upper part of the screen, and
                rendered similarly to the monthly view. In addition, when the time range
                of an event is 24 hours or longer, it is rendered as an all-day event in
                the monthly view.
            </para>

            <para>
                When the time range of an event is equal or less than 24 hours, with the
                accuracy of one millisecond, the event is considered as a normal day
                event. Normal event has a start and end times that may be on different
                days.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect xml:id="addons.calendar.overview.interaction">
            <title>Interaction</title>

            <para>
                The date and week captions, as well as events, are clickable and the
                clicks can be listened for by the server. Also date/time range selections,
                event dragging, and event resizing can be listened by the server. Using
                the API, you have full control over the events caused by user interaction.
            </para>

            <para>
                The weekly view has navigation buttons to navigate forward and backward in
                time. These actions are also listened by the server. Custom navigating is
                can be implemented using event handlers<!-- TODO LINK which are described
                in section 2.7.2-->.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most of the handlers related to calendar events have sensible default
                handlers. These are found in the <package>com.vaadin.ui.handler</package>
                package. The default handlers and their functionalities are described
                below.
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <classname>BasicBackwardHandler</classname>. Handles clicking the
                    back-button of the weekly view so that the viewed month is changed to
                    the previous one.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <classname>BasicForwardHandler</classname>. Handles clicking the
                    forward-button of the weekly view so that the viewed month is changed
                    to the next one.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <classname>BasicWeekClickHandler</classname>. Handles clicking the
                    week numbers int the monthly view so that the viewable date range is
                    changed to the clicked week.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <classname>BasicDateClickHandler</classname>. Handles clicking the
                    dates on both the monthly view and the weekly view. Changes the
                    viewable date range so that only the clicked day is visible.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <classname>BasicEventMoveHandler</classname>. Handles moving the
                    events in both monthly view and the weekly view. Events can be moved
                    and their start and end dates are changed correctly, but only if the
                    event implements <classname>CalendarEventEditor</classname>
                    (implemented by <classname>BasicEvent</classname>).
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <classname>BasicEventResizeHandler</classname>. Handles resizing the
                    events in the weekly view. Events can be resized and their start and
                    end dates are changed correctly, but only if the event implements
                    <classname>CalendarEventEditor</classname> (implemented by the
                    <classname>BasicEvent</classname>).
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                All of these handlers are automatically set when creating a new
                <classname>Calendar</classname>. If you wish to disable some of the
                default functionality, you can simply set the corresponding handler to
                <literal>null</literal>. This will prevent the functionality from ever
                appearing on the user interface. For example, if you set the
                <classname>EventMoveHandler</classname> to <literal>null</literal>, the
                user will be unable to move events in the browser.
            </para>
        </simplesect>

        <section xml:id="addons.calendar.overview.licensing">
            <title>Licensing</title>

            <para>
                Vaadin Calendar is a commercial product licensed under a dual-licensing
                scheme. The AGPL (GNU Affero General Public License) allows open-source
                development, while the CVAL (Commercial Vaadin Add-On License) needs to be
                purchased for closed-source use, including web deployments and internal
                use.
            </para>

            <para>
                Commercial licenses can be purchased from the Vaadin Directory, where you
                can also find the license details and download the Vaadin Calendar.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
