<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="rapid.cloudfoundry">
    <title>Deploying to Cloud Foundry</title>

    <para>
        Cloud Foundry (<literal>http://cloudfoundry.com/</literal>) is a new platform-as-a-service solution from 
        springsource. Cloud Foundry makes it extremely easy to deploy applications created with Spring Roo and Vaadin to
        the cloud.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        Before you can deploy to Cloud Foundry, you must register for an account at
        <literal>http://cloudfoundry.com/</literal>. The activation might take some time, so you should do this several
        days before you need it.
    </para>
    
    <section xml:id="rapid.cloudfoundry.plugin">
        <title>Installing the Cloud Foundry Plug-in in STS</title>
        <para>
            Installing the Cloud Foundry plug-in is easy. Open the STS Dashboard and select the "Extensions" tab in the
            lower-left corner of the dashboard view. Scroll down to the "Server and Clouds" section and choose the Cloud
            Foundry integration plug-in from there. Click install and follow the on-screen instructions.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="rapid.cloudfoundry.deploy">
        <title>Deploying the Application</title>
        <para>
            Deploying the application is also very simple. Open the 'Servers' view, right click in it and create a new
            server. Choose VMWare->Cloud Foundry and click 'Next >'. Fill in the account information that you received
            by e-mail from cloudfoundry.com and choose 'VMware Cloud Foundry - http://api.cloudfoundry.com' from the URL
            dropdown. You can click 'Validate Account' to make sure that you filled in your password correctly. Click
            'Finish' to finish the installation of the Cloud Foundry server.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Once the new server is installed you can add your project to it, just like you would add your project to any
            other server using the 'Servers' view. Once added, right click on the project and choose 'Start'. This will
            ask for a name that identifies your project in the cloud as well as the URL to deploy to. After giving this
            information, the project will be uploaded and started in the cloud. After a few seconds you should be able
            to visit the URL you provided and see your project in action.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="rapid.cloudfoundry.mysql">
        <title>Binding to the MySQL Service</title>
        <para>
            TODO - haven't gotten this to work yet, waiting for an answer to a support request.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->
