<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<appendix xml:id="vaadin">
	<title>Songs of Vaadin</title>

    <para>Vaadin is a mythological creature in Finnish folklore, the goddess and
    divine ancestor of the mountain reindeer. It appears frequently in the poetic mythos,
    often as the trustworthy steed of either <emphasis>Seppo Ilmarinen</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>Väinämöinen</emphasis>, the two divine hero figures. In many of the stories,
    it is referred to as <emphasis>Steed of Seppo</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>Seponratsu</emphasis> in Finnish. An artifact itself, according to most
    accounts, Vaadin helped Seppo Ilmarinen in his quests to find the knowledge necessary
    to forge magical artefacts, such as <emphasis>Sampo</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Some of the Vaadin poems were collected by <emphasis>Elias Lönnrot</emphasis>,
    but he left them out of <emphasis>Kalevala</emphasis>, the Finnish epic poem, as they
    were somewhat detached from the main theme and would have created inconsistencies with
    the poems included in the epos. Lönnrot edited Kalevala heavily and it represents a
    selection from a much larger and more diverse body of collected poems. Many of the
    accounts regarding Vaadin were sung by shamans, and still are. A shamanistic
    tradition, centered on the tales of Seppo and Vaadin, still lives in South-Western
    Finland, around the city of Turku. Some research in the folklore suggests that the
    origin of Vaadin is as a shamanistic animal spirit used during trance for voyaging to
    <emphasis>Tuonela</emphasis>, the Land of Dead, with its mechanical construction
    reflecting the shamanistic tools used for guiding the trance. While the shamanistic
    interpretation of the origins is disputed by a majority of the research community in a
    maximalist sense, it is considered a potentially important component in the collection
    of traditions that preserve the folklore.</para>

    <para>Origin or birth poems, <emphasis>synnyt</emphasis> in Finnish, provide the most
    distinct accounts of mythological artefacts in the Finnish folklore, as origin poems
    or songs were central in the traditional magical practices. Vaadin is no exception and
    its origin poems are numerous. In many of the versions, Vaadin was created in a mill,
    for which Seppo had built the millstone. After many a year, grinding the sacred acorns
    of the <emphasis>Great Oak</emphasis> (a version of the <emphasis>World
    Tree</emphasis> in Finnish mythology), the millstone had become saturated with the
    magical juices of the acorns. Seppo found that the stone could be used to make
    tools. He cut it in many peaces and built a toolkit suitable for fashioning spider web
    into any imaginable shape. When Seppo started making Sampo, he needed a steed that
    would help him find the precious components and the knowledge he required. The magical
    tools became the skeleton of Vaadin.</para>

    <blockquote><literallayout><emphasis>				"Lost, his mind was,
				gone, was his understanding,
				ran away, were his memories,
				in the vast land of hills of stone.
				Make a steed he had to,
				forge bone out of stone,
				flesh out of moss,
				and skin of bark of the birch.
				The length of his hammer,
				he put as the spine and the hip,
				bellows as the lungs,
				tongs as the legs, paired.
				So woke Vaadin from the first slumber,
				lichen did Seppo give her for eating,
				mead did he give her for drinking,
				then mounted her for the journey."</emphasis></literallayout>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Other versions associate the creation with Väinämöinen instead of Seppo
    Ilmarinen, and give different accounts for the materials. This ambiguity can be
    largely explained through the frequent cooperation between Väinämöinen and Seppo in
    the mythos. Nevertheless, the identity of the steed or steeds is largely implicit in
    the myths and, because of the differences in the origin myths, can not be
    unambiquously associated with a unique identity.</para>

    <para>The theme of animal ancestor gods is common in the Finnish myth, as we can see
    in the widespread worship of <emphasis>Tapio</emphasis>, the lord of the bear and the
    forest. With respect to Vaadin, the identification of the animal is not completely
    clear. The Finnish word <emphasis>vaadin</emphasis> refers specifically to an adult
    female of the semi-domesticated mountain reindeer, which lives in the Northern Finland
    in Lapland as well as in the Northern Sweden and Norway. On the other hand, the
    Finnish folklore represented in Kalevala and other collections has been collected from
    Southern Finland, where the mountain reindeer does not exist. Nevertheless, Southern
    Finnish folklore and Kalevala do include many other elements as well that are
    distinctively from Lapland, so we may assume that the folklore reflects a record of
    cultural interaction. The distinction between the northern mountain reindeer and the
    deer species of Southern Finland, the forest reindeer and the elk, is clear in the
    modern language, but may not have been in old Finnish dialects. For example,
    <emphasis>peura</emphasis>, reindeer, may have been a generic word for a wild animal,
    as can be seen in <emphasis>jalopeura</emphasis>, the old Finnish word for lion. The
    identification is further complicated by the fact that the line of poems included in
    Kalevala often refers to a horse. This could be due to the use of the word for horse
    as a generic name for a steed. While a mountain reindeer is not suitable for riding,
    animal gods are typically portrayed as uncommonly large in mythology, even to the
    extremes, so the identification fits quite well in the variety of magical
    mounts.</para>

    <para>The mythology related to Vaadin, especially as represented in Kalevala, locates
    some important characters and people in <emphasis>Pohjola</emphasis>, a mythical land
    in the north from where all evil originates, according to most accounts. For example,
    <emphasis>Louhi</emphasis> or Pohjolan emäntä, Queen of Pohjola, is the primary
    antagonist in the Kalevala mythos. Both Seppo Ilmarinen and Väinämöinen make services
    to Louhi to earn the hand of her daughters for marriage. Vaadin is often
    mentioned in connection with these services, such as the making of Sampo. On the
    other hand, as Sampo can be identified with the mill mentioned in creation stories
    of Vaadin, its identification in the stories becomes unclear.</para>

    <para>While beginning its life as an artifact, Vaadin is later represented as an
    antropomorphic divine being. This is in contrast with the <emphasis>Bride of
    Gold</emphasis>, another creation of Seppo, which failed to become a fully living and
    thinking being. Finding magical ways around fundamental problems in life are central
    in Kalevala. In some areas, magical solutions are morally acceptable, while in others
    they are not and the successes and failures in the mythos reflect this ethic. Research
    in the folklore regarding the Bride of Gold myth has provided support for a theory
    that creating a wife would go against very fundamental social rules of courting and
    mating, paralleling the disapproval of "playing god" in acts involving life and death
    (though "cheating death" is usually considered a positive act). The main motivation of
    the protagonists in Kalevala is courting young daughters, which always ends in
    failure, usually for similar reasons. Animals, such as Vaadin, are outside the social
    context and considered to belong in the same category with tools and machines. The
    Vaadin myths present a noteworthy example of this categorization of animals and tools
    in the same category at an archetypal level.</para>

	<para>The Vaadin myths parallel the <emphasis>Sleipnir</emphasis> myths in the
	Scandinavian mythology. This connection is especially visible for the connection of
	Väinämöinen with <emphasis>Odin</emphasis>, who used Sleipnir in his journeys. The use
	of tongs for the legs of Vaadin actually suggests eight legs, which is the
	distinguishing attribute of Sleipnir. While Sleipnir is almost universally depicted as
	a horse, the exact identification of the steed may have changed during the
	transmission between the cultures.</para>

	<para>The <emphasis>Bridle of Vaadin</emphasis> is a special artifact itself. There is
	no headstall, but only the rein, detached from the creature, kept in the hand of the
	rider. The rein is a chain or set of "gadgets" used for controlling the creature. The
	rein was built of web with special tools, with Seppo wearing magnifying goggles to
	work out the small details.</para>

	<para>The significance and cultural influence of Vaadin can be seen in its
	identification with a constellation in the traditional Finnish constellation
	system. The famous French astronomer <emphasis>Pierre Charles Le Monnier</emphasis>
	(1715-99), who visited Lapland, introduced the constellation to international star
	charts with the name <emphasis>Tarandus vel Rangifer</emphasis>. The constellation was
	present in many star charts of the time, perhaps most notably in the
	<emphasis>Uranographia</emphasis> published in 1801 by <emphasis>Johann Elert
	Bode</emphasis>, as shown in <xref linkend="vaadin.uranographia"/>. It was later
	removed in the unification of the constellation system towards the Greek
	mythology.</para>

    <!-- Image source: http://www.ianridpath.com/startales/rangifer.htm -->
    <!-- Copyright should be expired in >200 years.                     -->
	<figure xml:id="vaadin.uranographia">
		<title>Constellation of Tarandus vel Rangifer in Bode's Uranographia (1801)</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="fo">
				<imagedata scale="80" smallscale="100%" align="center" fileref="img/rangifer.jpg"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

</appendix>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:("/etc/sgml/catalog" "/usr/share/xemacs21/xemacs-packages/etc/psgml-dtds/CATALOG")
sgml-local-ecat-files:("ECAT" "~/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/share/sgml/ECAT" "/usr/local/lib/sgml/ECAT")
End:
-->

